<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
b'<item><bodyText>\n\n\n\n\n\nForeign Relations of the United States\n\n\nHome\nSearch\nBrowse\nCopyright\nHelp\nUWDC\n\n\n\n\nDisplay:\n\nGallery view\nPage image\nPDF of section (86.4 MB) \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Contents&#160;\n&#160;Section&#160;\n&#160;Page&#160;\n&#160;\n\n\n\n\nPage View\nUnited States Department of State / Foreign relations of the United States. Conference at Quebec, 1944\n\t\t\t(1944)\n\n Substantive preparatory papers,&#160;&#160; pp. 48-278\n\t\t\t\n PDF (86.4 MB) \n\n\n\nPage 176\n\n\nTHE SECOND QUEBEC CONFERENCE\na period of hard commercial bargaining before the negotiations reach\ntheir eventual conclusion. In the nature of things, we have no interest\ninl giving the Argentines any particular reason to suppose that a suc-\ncessful outcome is assured in advance or in agreeing to terms which\nthey could interpret as reflecting any condonation of their political\nshortcomings.\n  Mr. Stettinius, in his recent conversation with the Minister of State,3\nexpressed the hope that the contract would cover only a short term.4\nThe question of the duration of the contract is, of course, a relative\none, but we have to look to the needs of ourselves and our Allies dur-\ning the cricitical post-war period as well as for the period of actual\nhostilities. We have no desire to conclude a contract running for a\nlonger period than is strictly necessary. If nothing else, our own in-\nterests would dictate that the duration of the contract should be as\nshort as possible since our meat purchases constitute one of the few\nweapons which we have left to protect our large interests in Argen-\ntina, which are threatened as never before by the present virulently\nnationalistic regime. This weapon would, for instance, normally be\nextremely useful in, say, a couple of years\' time, when the imminent\ntermination of the Mitre Law 5 (in 1947) governing our railway con-\ncessions will leave these particularly vulnerable. But our paramount\nduty both to our own people and to certain of our Allies is to ensure\nthat, during the acutely difficult post-war years, they shall be ade-\nquately fed; and the case made out by our Ministry of Food that only\na longer contract will ensure this as regards meat is entirely con-\nvincing. I need not, I think, go into all the technical details including\nthe reasons why it is so important that the Combined Food Board\nshould be able to count not merely on obtaining Argentine meat at a\nreasonable commercial price, but on continuing to command the total\nexportable surplus. The British Food Mission in Washington are, of\ncourse, in possession of all the technical details involved and if it\nwould interest the State Department to have a complete summary\nof the technical aspects of this complex question, we shall be ready to\narrange for this to be given to them. Meanwhile, I trust that we can\ncontinue to enjoy the confidence of the United States Government\nwhile we play our difficult hand in this important matter which we\nshall hope to do without giving the Argentines any avoidable political\nadvantages. We shall do our best to keep the Argentines guessing about\nall the aspects of this negotiation as far as is consistent with eventually\nbringing it to a successful conclusion and to see to it that the present\nregime derives no strength or authority from this commercial trans-\naction in their own or anybody else\'s eyes. In this we should, of course,\nbe helped by the absence of embarrassing press speculation, whether\nemanating from Washington or London."\n  3Richard Law.\n  See Foreign Relations, 1944, vol. vii, p. 342.\n  5 The reference is to article 8 of Argentine Law No. 5315 of October 1,\n1907. The\nprovisions of this article, which dealt with duty-free importation of materials\nused in railroad development in Argentina, were to expire in 1947. For text\nof\nthe law, see Registro nacional, vol. iv, 1907, p. 441. For an English translation,\nsee General Railway Law and Regulations, translated by the Buenos Aires Great\nSouthern and Buenos Aires Western Railways (Buenos Aires: The English\nPrintery, 1940), p. 191.\n176\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Top of Page\n\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Contents&#160;\n&#160;Section&#160;\n&#160;Page&#160;\n&#160;\n\n\nAs a work of the United States government, this material is in the public domain.| For information on re-use see: http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/Copyright\n\n\nContent/Navigation Questions\nTechnical Assistance\nUniversity of Wisconsin Digital Collections\nAccessibility Information\n\n\n \n&#169; This compilation (including design, introductory text, organization, and descriptive material) is copyrighted by University of Wisconsin System Board of Regents.\nThis </bodyText><pdf><value>http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value><value>http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value></pdf><name /><urls><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Search.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Browse.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Copyright.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Help.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;isize=S</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;isize=M</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;isize=L</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;isize=XL</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=gallery&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;posn=curr&amp;curr=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;isize=M</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0009&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0011&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0102&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0231&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0233&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0009&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0011&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0102&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0231&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0233&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value></urls><id>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0232&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</id></item>'