<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
b'<item><bodyText>\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nLibraries\n.st0{fill:#FFF}\n\n\nUW \n\nMyUW\nEmail/Calendar\nLearn@UW\nBox\nGoogle Apps\n\n\n\nAsk \n\n\n\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\tChat\n\n\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\tEmail\n\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\tCall\n\n\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\tMore\n\n\n\nAccount\n\nGive\nSearch the Library Website\n\n\n\n\n\n\nSearch UWDC\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nUWDC\nAbout\nBrowse\n \n\nLibrary\n\nLibraries\nASK\nAccount\nGive\nSearch\n\n\n\nUW-Madison\n\nMyUW\nEmail/Calendar\nLearn@UW\nBox\nGoogle Apps\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nMenu \n\n\n\nUW Digital Collections\n\n\n\nAbout\nBrowse\n \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nForeign Relations of the United States\n\n\nCitation URL:\nhttp://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/FRUS\n\n\n\n\n\nURLs to browse or search the collections\n\nBrowse the collectionSearch the full text \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nBrowse\n\n\n\nForeign Relations of the U.S.\n\n\nForeign Relations of the United States, 1952-1954: volume II. National Security Affairs.\nThis digital facsimile of Foreign Relations of the United States is a project of the University of Wisconsin-Madison Libraries in collaboration with the University of Illinois at Chicago Libraries. This is a&#160;nearly complete&#160;run from 1861-1960 with missing volumes being added as they can be acquired and processed. If your library is interested in donating material for this project, please contact the University of Wisconsin Digital Collections Center.\nSpecial thanks are owed to the University of Chicago Libraries for contributing FRUS volumes for digitization. Thanks also to these other contributing libraries: Southwestern University (Los Angeles) Library, the University of Connecticut&#8217;s Homer Babbidge Library, Georgia Southwestern State University&#8217;s James Earl Carter Library, University of Indiana-Bloomington Libraries, Brigham Young University&#8217;s Howard W. Hunter Law Library, Columbia University Libraries, Des Moines Public Library, Jefferson County (Colorado) Public Library, Michigan State University Libraries, Ouachita Baptist University&#8217;s Riley-Hickingbotham Library, University of Michigan-Flint&#8217;s Thompson Library, University of Minnesota, University of Mississippi&#8217;s J. D. Williams Library, University of South Alabama&#8217;s University Library and the Wisconsin Historical Society.\nThe objective of the project is to drive down the cost of digitization and scale up production of valuable information resources in digital format. It is hoped that the development of low-cost digitization methods will inspire further collaboration among research libraries to enlarge the public domain of knowledge accessible via the Internet.\nThe Foreign Relations of the United States series is the official documentary historical record of major U.S. foreign policy decisions that have been declassified and edited for publication. The series is produced by the State Department&#8217;s Office of the Historian and printed volumes are available from the Government Printing Office.\nFRUS begins with the administration of Abraham Lincoln in 1861. There are two cumulative indexes covering 1861-1899 and 1900-1918. The organization of FRUS is generally chronological, but the dates of the volumes do not necessarily reflect the dates of documentary history. For example, the volumes for 1900-1918 do not include the records dealing with World War I or the Russian Revolution. Each volume has a subject and author index. There is also typically a table of sources and abbreviations at the beginning of each volume.\nMany volumes published since 1945 are available online on the State Department website that is maintained by the University of Illinois at Chicago. A full description of Foreign Relations of the United States, including a listing of the online FRUS volumes, is available from the Office of the Historian website.\nQuestions or comments about the site should be directed to the University of Wisconsin Digital Collections Center, University of Wisconsin Libraries.\n\nImage Source: Foreign relations of the United States, 1952-1954. National security affairs (in two parts),(1952-1954).\n\n\n\nCopyright\n\n\nClick to read our  Copyright  statement \n\nThis compilation (including design, introductory text, organization, and descriptive material) is copyrighted by University of Wisconsin System Board of Regents.\nThis copyright is independent of any copyright on specific items within the collection. Because the University of Wisconsin Libraries generally do not own the rights to materials in these collections</bodyText><pdf /><name /><urls><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Browse.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Search.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS195254v02p2.p0005&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS195254v02p2&amp;isize=M</value></urls><id>https://uwdc.library.wisc.edu/collections/FRUS/</id></item>'