<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative











D&#233;tente Conference - Conferences




Home

Conferences

U.S.-Soviet Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente, 1969-1976






U.S.-Soviet Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente, 1969-1976









Schedule
Monday, October 22, 2007:

9:00-9:55: Registration
9:55-10:00: Welcome and Introductory Remarks: Dr. Marc J. Susser, The
                        Historian, U.S. Department of State
10:00-10:20: Keynote Address by Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice
                        [Transcript and Video]
10:25-12:00: Roundtable Discussion of Former Government Officials
                        [Transcript]
Chair: Dr. Marc Susser, The Historian, U.S. Department of State
Dr. Henry Kissinger, National Security Advisor, 1969-1975; Secretary of
                        State, 1973-1977
General Alexander Haig, Jr., U.S. Army (ret.), Military Assistant to the
                        National Security Advisor, 1969-1970; Deputy National Security Advisor,
                        1970-1973; White House Chief of Staff, 1973-1974; Secretary of State,
                        1981-1982 (Unable to attend)
Dr. James Schlesinger, Director of Central Intelligence, 1973; Secretary
                        of Defense, 1973-1975
Question and Answer
12:00-2:00: Lunch
2:00-2:20: Welcome and Introduction of Joint Volume: Dr. Marc J. Susser,
                        The Historian, U.S. Department of State and Ambassador Konstantin Provalov,
                        History and Records Department, Russian Ministry of Foreign Affairs
2:20-3:50: Scholarly Interpretations of the Joint Volume and D&#233;tente
Chair: Dr. Edward Keefer, Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of
                        State
Dr. Sergey M. Rogov, Director of the USA and Canada Institute of the
                        Russian Academy of Sciences (Unable to attend)
Professor Robert Schulzinger, University of Colorado at Boulder
Professor Jeremi Suri, University of Wisconsin-Madison
Professor Vladislav Zubok, Temple University
4:00-6:00: Reception (by invitation only)

Tuesday, October 23, 2007:

8:15-8:55: Registration and Breakfast - Enter from Virginia Avenue and
                        21st Street
8:55-9:00: Welcome
9:00-10:30: Panel 1 - D&#233;tente and Europe: Transnational Perspectives
 Chair/ Commentator: Professor Thomas Schwartz, Vanderbilt University
"Recognizing the Soviet Sphere of Influence? U.S.-Soviet D&#233;tente and
                        Eastern Europe, 1969-1976," Professor Douglas Selvage, Embry-Riddle
                        Aeronautical University
"Operation Hullabaloo: Henry Kissinger, British Diplomacy, and the
                        Agreement on the Prevention of Nuclear War," Dr. Stephen Twigge, Foreign and
                        Commonwealth Office
"The 'Confidential Channel': Documenting the Secret Diplomacy of D&#233;tente,
                        1969-1972," David C. Geyer, Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of
                        State
10:30-10:45: Break
10:45-12:15: Panel 2 - Selling the End of the Cold War at Home
Chair/ Commentator: Professor David Engerman, Brandeis University
"Voices from Below: Public Opinion and U.S.-Soviet Dialogue, 1969-1973,"
                        Professor Andrey Edemskiy, Slavic Studies Institute, Russian Academy of
                        Sciences
"The Legitimation of the Nixon-Kissinger Grand Design and Grand Strategy,"
                        Professor Dan Caldwell, Pepperdine University
"National Security Centrism and the Politics of D&#233;tente, 1969-1976,"
                        Professor Julian Zelizer, Princeton University
 12:15-1:45: Lunch
 1:45-3:15: Panel 3 - D&#233;tente in Theory and Practice
Chair/ Commentator: Dr. Bernd Schaefer, German Historical
                        Institute/Woodrow Wilson Center
"A Sea of Confusion: The US, the USSR, and the Mediterranean, 1969-1974,"
                        Dr. Effie G. H. Pedaliu, University of West England-Bristol
 "D&#233;tente, Entente, or Linkage? The Helsinki CSCE in U.S.-Soviet
                        Relations," Professor Angela Romano, University of Florence
 "Vietnam as an Irritant to U.S.-Soviet D&#233;tente and Sino-American
                        Rapprochement, 1971-1973," Professor Lorenz L-thi, McGill University
 3:15-3:30: Break
3:30-5:00: Panel 4 - D&#233;tente by Other Means: Science, Culture, and Human
                        Rights
Chair/ Commentator: Dr. Christian Ostermann, Woodrow Wilson Center
"The Politics of D&#233;tente-Era Cultural Texts, 1969-1976," Professor
                        Kathleen Parth, University of Rochester
 "The Cold War as a Science Race: Examining the Consequences of the
                        Biological Revolution on D&#233;tente, 1969-1975," Professor Shelley Hurt, Vassar
                        College
 "Human Rights, D&#233;tente, and the Making of the Helsinki Final Act,"
                        Michael Morgan, Yale University



Opening Remarks at the Office of the Historian's Conference on U.S.-Soviet
                    Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente, 1969-1976, Secretary Condoleezza Rice, East
                    Auditorium Washington, DC, October 22, 2007
View Video
Secretary Rice makes opening remarks by at the Department of State Conference on
                    U.S.-Soviet Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente, Marshall Center in the East
                    Auditorium.
SECRETARY RICE: Thank you very much, Marc. Thank you for that wonderful
                    introduction. And thank you also for your leadership and hard work over these
                    years.
And good morning, and welcome, everyone, to the Department of State.
What brings us together today is a truly remarkable achievement, both in the
                    history of diplomacy and the diplomacy of history. Only two decades ago, the
                    United States and the Soviet Union stood as enemies, separated by mystery and
                    misunderstanding and prepared for war. Today, Americans and Russians are opening
                    our archives, sharing old secrets, and trying to build newfound trust. I want to
                    commend Marc and all the dedicated men and women of our Historian&#8217;s office, as
                    well as their Russian colleagues, for this significant contribution to human
                    knowledge and to U.S.-Russian relations.
I'd especially like to welcome Jim Schlesinger--who has distinguished himself
                    over many decades in the service to our country. Thank you so much. He's been
                    our Director of Central Intelligence, our Secretary of Defense, and our first
                    ever Secretary of Energy. So he's had a few jobs. Thank you very much, Jim.
We are also honored, obviously, today by the presence of the man who is the
                    subject of so much of this history: Henry Kissinger. For academics like me, and
                    for many of you I imagine, Henry Kissinger has always been an inspiration--a
                    living reminder that scholars not only write history; they can make it. And
                    Henry, it has been a pleasure for me to get know you over these years and I
                    benefit from your wisdom, I am honored to call you my friend. Welcome back to
                    the Department of State.
The bureaucracy really misses you, Henry. They told me so. (Laughter.)
I am also very pleased to see Ambassador Yuriy Ushakov, who is in the audience
                    tonight--this afternoon. Thank you very much.
Distinguished gentlemen and ladies, guests: For all of us old enough to recall,
                    and that would include me, the passing of time has not eroded our memory of the
                    daunting challenges that America faced when President Richard Nixon took office.
                    Our nation was in the midst of social upheaval. A contentious war that was
                    sapping our blood and our treasure and turning our country&#8217;s focus inward. And
                    he inherited a relationship with the Soviet Union in which mistrust was
                    deepening, in which tension was growing, and in which the fear of open conflict
                    was real.
President Nixon and Henry Kissinger rose to those challenges with new ideas and
                    with creative diplomacy. They launched, what President Nixon called, an &#8220;era of
                    negotiations&#8221;--most directly through what was known as &#8220;the Channel&#8221; between
                    Henry Kissinger and Ambassador Dobrynin. This dialogue was continued by our
                    people who increasingly met on sports fields and over chessboards, in classrooms
                    and through our joint exploration of the heavens. And as a result, two states
                    with opposing ideologies and many conflicting interests began easing their
                    suspicions and cooperating in areas of mutual concern like reducing nuclear arms
                    and preventing nuclear war.
But perhaps the most lasting achievement of that time was in many ways the least
                    expected. Because in that period and beyond, the demand for freedom and human
                    rights that began growing among the Russian people became evident. In the
                    Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe, begun on Dr. Kissinger&#8217;s
                    watch, some saw the recognition of a divided Europe. What we now know is that
                    the Helsinki Accords laid a foundation of moral principle favorable to our
                    values. It encouraged and empowered Russian patriots to demand their liberties
                    and their rights. And in their aspirations we saw the beginning of the end of
                    the &#8220;the long twilight struggle.&#8221;
These remarkable events are chapters of world history that I have studied in
                    great detail and in which I had the good fortune to participate. I got to be the
                    White House Soviet specialist at the end of the Cold War. And I'll just tell
                    you, it doesn't get much better than that. I got to participate in what I had
                    thought would be unimaginable events: The unification of Germany, the liberation
                    of Eastern Europe, and the peaceful eclipse of the Soviet Union.
But when you look back on those unbelievable days, you have to think that the
                    role that my colleagues and I played in 1989 and 1990 and 1991 was just really
                    harvesting good decisions that had been taken long before; in 1947, in 1948 and
                    1949, by people like Truman, and Acheson, and Vandenberg; in 1969, in 1970,
                    1971, by Nixon, and Kissinger; and in 1981 until 1989 by Ronald Reagan.
The end of the Cold War created a new opportunity for comity between America and
                    Russia. Today, there is, to be fair, still a certain distance between us, and I
                    have long thought that that reason for this difference is rooted in history
                    itself; in different ways that our two nations continue to tell the story of the
                    last decade.
For us, and for many in Russia too, the collapse of the Soviet Union was a
                    triumph--ushering in a new promise of international security and stability; a
                    new hope of a Europe whole, free, and at peace; and a new era of liberty, and
                    opportunity, and justice for all Russians. But we need to realize, too, that for
                    many ordinary Russians, who saw the end of the Cold War differently, it was
                    remembered as a decade of great uncertainty, and lawlessness, and weakness, and
                    perhaps even humiliation; a revolution in its truest meaning, when the only
                    social order that most ever knew overturned with devastating abruptness, when
                    the state collapsed and the public wealth of an unsuspecting nation was pocketed
                    by too few.
I firmly believe that we cannot understand Russia today, and we cannot fully
                    connect with the Russian people, unless we continue working to see our shared
                    history in common terms. This can not, and it will not, lead to apologize for
                    Russian actions that never should have happened. But a deeper understanding
                    between our peoples will help our governments to work with each other, not talk
                    past each other, and to continue to build a better relationship; something that
                    we both want and surely that we both need.
I was just in Moscow with Secretary Gates and I can tell you that the United
                    States and Russia share many common interests and we are cooperating to address
                    a wide range of common challenges: regional and global.
Our two nations are partners in the cause of peace in the Middle East; working
                    together, through the Quartet, to advance the goal of two states, Israel and
                    Palestine, living side by side in peace and security.
Like us, Russia has been a victim of terrorism, and we are working productively
                    together; sharing intelligence, coordinating law enforcement efforts, and
                    protecting both our peoples from this new global threat. We are doing the same
                    when it comes to stemming the spread of weapons of mass destruction. The United
                    States and Russia are leading the Global Initiative to Combat Nuclear Terrorism.
                    And we are working with common purpose in the Six Party Talks to rid the Korean
                    Peninsula of nuclear weapons and to support a future of peace on the Korean
                    Peninsula.
And in the case of Iran, the United States and Russia may differ from time to
                    time over tactics and the timing of how we address this challenge, but what is
                    most important is that we are united in our common conviction that a nuclear
                    weapon in the hands of the Iranian Government would be disastrous for
                    international peace and security, and we have forged together a common
                    diplomatic strategy, with two paths: one with incentives if Iran chooses
                    cooperation; the other with consequences if Iran continues choose to continue to
                    confront the international community. The United States and Russia have acted
                    together in the UN Security Council to impose two sets of Chapter 7 sanctions on
                    the Iranian Government, and we are now working together to raise costs for
                    Iranian intransigence even further, including finalizing the text of a new
                    resolution.
Now, the fact that Russia and the United States have common interests is not to
                    say that we do not have differences. We do. Yet Russia is not the Soviet Union.
                    Like many of you, I visited the Soviet Union, I studied in the Soviet Union, and
                    I will tell you: Russia today is not the Soviet Union. And the chattering that
                    we hear of a new Cold War obscures and distorts reality. We can all be thankful
                    that the only damage that the Cold War is causing today is a few headaches for
                    historians gathered here.
We must understand the Russians&#8217; view of their recent past, but we need not
                    agree with conclusions that some seem to have drawn from that experience. Russia
                    has regained some of its strength and its cohesion. But at times, perhaps
                    reflecting the view of the 1990s, we fear that this is sometimes seen in
                    zero-sum terms of another era. We respect Russia&#8217;s interests, but no interest is
                    served if Russia uses its great wealth, its oil and gas wealth, as a political
                    weapon, or that if it treats its independent neighbors as part of some old
                    sphere of influence.
Nor do we believe that Europe&#8217;s unity and liberty since 1991 is unjust. The
                    freedom of people to choose their own governments and the freedom of nations to
                    make their own way is a source of security, not a threat to it. So we hope that
                    Russia will also recognize that we can work together for a Kosovo solution that
                    contributes to peace in Europe.
We recognize that Russians today enjoy greater security and opportunity, and
                    even greater personal freedom than at any point in Soviet or Tsarist history.
                    But this is a standard to which Russians themselves do not wish to be held. They
                    wish to be held to a higher standard. And so we will continue to speak for those
                    principles of liberty, and democracy, and openness that we believe can best
                    ensure the long-term success of the Russian people and contribute to a
                    partnership with us that is rooted not just in shared interests, but in shared
                    ideals.
We want a 21st century partnership with Russia building on our common interests.
                    We want Russia to be strong, strong in 21st century terms &#8211; not just with a
                    strong center, but with strong, independent institutions: an independent
                    judiciary and legislature, and an independent civil society, with a free media
                    and a vibrant nongovernmental sector. Democratic institutions and a free society
                    are not a source of weakness; they are a source of strength in a dynamic and
                    modern world.
When we disagree, we will address Russia&#8217;s views seriously and we will express
                    our own ideas candidly. It was in this spirit that Secretary Gates and I went to
                    Moscow and offered constructive ideas to address Russia&#8217;s concerns about our
                    missile defense systems. This desire for cooperation also leads us to think that
                    Russia can work with us to fully ratify and implement the Adapted CFE Treaty,
                    rather than to suspend its obligations under the old treaty.
Ladies and gentlemen, it can be easy and perhaps even tempting today for both
                    Americans and Russians to become consumed by our differences and to let those
                    differences define us. That was true during the Cold War, especially before the
                    rise of the era that we study today, d&#233;tente.
But what history teaches us is that it is possible for the United States and
                    Russia to disagree, even to disagree vehemently, but not to let our differences
                    destroy the positive work that we can, and must, do together.
Our work in the present is being aided immensely by you, our scholars of the
                    past. You are helping Americans and Russians alike to understand our shared
                    experience, both the good and the bad. You are strengthening the friendship
                    between our peoples. And most importantly, you are reminding us that today&#8217;s
                    headlines are rarely the same as history&#8217;s judgment.
America&#8217;s relationship with Russia will remain large and complex: a mix of
                    cooperation and competition, friendship and friction. This has always been the
                    case. But we have achieved great things together before. We are doing so again
                    today. And I am confident that with patience and hard work, dialogue and
                    understanding, our future can be brighter than our past.
Thank you very much. (Applause.)
2007/902
Released on October 22, 2007


Introduction to Roundtable Discussion of Former Government Officials 
DR. SUSSER: After two decades of Cold War between the United States and the
                    Soviet Union, President Richard Nixon and Communist Party General Secretary
                    Leonid Brezhnev began to forge a new kind of relationship which introduced a new
                    diplomatic term to much of the American public: D&#233;tente. It was during this era
                    that National Security Advisor Henry Kissinger opened a confidential channel of
                    communication with the Soviet Union. In a relationship that was known to only a
                    select few in Washington, Dr. Kissinger met regularly with the longtime Soviet
                    Ambassador Anatoly Dobrynin to discuss major issues of the day.
This Kissinger-Dobrynin confidential channel provided a means for each side to
                    reach out to the other, to probe, to test the waters and to move the bilateral
                    relationship from outright enmity to an era of lessened tension. We are indeed
                    fortunate to have with us today Dr. Kissinger and one of his colleagues from the
                    Nixon and Ford administrations, Dr. James Schlesinger, who also filled, as the
                    Secretary pointed out, more than one key position during this era.
Unfortunately, General Alexander Haig was hospitalized last week and is under
                    doctor's orders not to leave his house. We will send him a copy of the volume
                    and we send him our good wishes for a speedy recovery.
There are brief biographies of our panelists in your program, but I believe I can
                    accurately say that for students of the Nixon-Ford era, Dr. Kissinger and Dr.
                    Schlesinger really need no further introduction. Each of them has, I believe,
                    some opening remarks prepared. So, Dr. Kissinger, would you begin?


Opening Remarks by Dr. Henry Kissinger
DR. KISSINGER: Thank you very much. Let me--I've been asked to keep my remarks to
                    15 minutes, in which case you can all say you were present at a historic
                    occasion. (Laughter.)
Let me make my remarks on three major points. One, what was the situation that
                    President Nixon and his Security Advisor found when they entered office?
                    Secondly, how did--what was the channel? What were we trying to accomplish? And
                    third, what are the conclusions one can perhaps draw from this?
First, whatever various historians in this room may have written, I had never met
                    President Nixon until he had been elected as President. And I had reached that
                    eminence by opposing him in three presidential campaigns, primary campaigns, as
                    the principal foreign policy advisor of Governor Rockefeller.
So President Nixon arrived into office with very clearly formed opinions about
                    the nature of the international situation, and so did I. And those opinions were
                    congruent, no matter what comments you may find in phone conversations at the
                    end of the day which prove preconceived ideas. In fact, one could say that
                    whatever was achieved in the Nixon Administration was due to the fact that there
                    was a substantial philosophical agreement about what was attempted to be done.
The Nixon Administration took office six months after the Soviet invasion of
                    Czechoslovakia, in the midst of the Vietnamese War in which there were 520,000
                    Americans in Vietnam, and their number was still increasing for the first three
                    months of the Nixon Administration on a schedule established by our
                    predecessors. In the previous five years, there had been two assassinations in
                    America, the most recent, less than a year before Nixon achieved office. The
                    country was as divided as it had ever been in its history and the issue whether
                    the administration desired peace--any administration, our predecessors and we
                    ourselves--was a crucial issue in the American domestic debate. The defense
                    appropriations were under constant attack and it was possible to maintain the
                    defense program of our predecessors and the slightly modified program of the
                    Nixon Administration only against the most intense opposition. The missile
                    defense program of the Nixon Administration was passed by one vote in the
                    authorization process and then reduced every year in the appropriations process.
Now, that was the situation in which we found ourselves. Now, the Soviet Union
                    had started a massive buildup of its strategic weapons, which in numbers
                    exceeded our own. At the same time, we faced what we considered to be an
                    obligation to end the oscillation in this country between extremes of commitment
                    and extremes of withdrawal, and anchor it into some permanent perception of the
                    American national interest.
Secondly, we felt we owed it to the American public to demonstrate a permanent
                    commitment to a period of what President Nixon called negotiation, a commitment
                    to the desirability of peaceful resolutions of disputes, and to make permanent
                    efforts to bridge the gaps that existed between us and the Soviet Union, between
                    us and China, and to solve the Vietnam War on a basis which we considered
                    honorable, which meant that we were not prepared to turn over the people who, in
                    reliance on American promises by our predecessors, had staked their fate on
                    America.
Those were the principles which governed our strategy. And it was expressed in,
                    on the one hand, resistance to any expansion of the Soviet sphere based on the
                    use or the threat of force; a maintenance of a strategic equilibrium between us
                    and the Soviet Union. But it was also based on a serious effort to open a
                    negotiating channel.
Now then, how did what is called "the channel" in this book come into existence?
                    It is fair and correct to say that President Nixon entered office with a
                    profound distrust of this Department. That was based partly on his experiences,
                    or as he described his experiences, when he was traveling as a defeated
                    candidate in the 1960 elections and as an aspirant candidate from '64 to '68. He
                    perceived that he had been treated inappropriately and with condescension. I can
                    make no comment because I did not witness it, but it would be wrong to
                    underestimate the depths of his feelings.
Secondly, it was equally important to understand, because I participated in that,
                    when it came time to organize the structure of national security after his
                    election, the person on whom he relied most was General Goodpaster. I had no
                    fixed views on that subject at the time because I didn't have enough experience
                    at that time.
And General Goodpaster and I called on President Eisenhower, and President
                    Eisenhower passionately stated that whatever else was done, the chairmanship of
                    all inter-departmental committees could not be in the Department of State; it
                    had to be, according to President Eisenhower, in the White House. I pointed
                    out--I--m not arguing these points. I just want to give you the history of how
                    this all evolved. And this combined with President Nixon's already settled view
                    that he wanted to run foreign policy out of the White House that he had stated
                    in the election campaign. So from the very beginning, before my relationship
                    with Nixon was firmly established, he told the Soviet Ambassador, as you will
                    see in this book, in the very first meeting that he wanted a special channel
                    that would--ran from Dobrynin to me. And this was three weeks after I met Nixon
                    for the first time.
Now, again, if we are dealing here with historians, Nixon was reinforced in this
                    view by a tendency of this building, which you will--some of you may agree,
                    others not--which is this. When the State Department is overruled on something
                    by the White House, its basic assumption is not that it was wrong or that the
                    President has stated a view; its basic assumption is that it was misunderstood
                    and that it has to take another shot at it, and another shot and the
                    modifications of what had been originally produced. So one is engaged in an
                    endless guerrilla war unless the State Department is run by somebody who is very
                    close to the President. And that difference doesn't arise. What cannot happen,
                    in my view, bureaucratically, is that the State Department wins a bureaucratic
                    battle with the White House, no matter who is right, and that is however what
                    happened. On many of the key issues--linkage, could one proceed on a broad basis
                    with the Soviet Union, the timing of the initiation of negotiations, how best to
                    proceed with China--there were not only disagreements, which can be helpful, but
                    there were disagreements that couldn't end, that wouldn't ever end. And there
                    are many explanations for that and I've offered to meet with the historians here
                    separately to go into that. But there was a real problem. It was not just an
                    invention of the President or of myself. And I can tell you, as somebody who had
                    to manage this process, it had a nightmarish quality when the Department which
                    had all the diplomats was going one way, the White House was going another way,
                    and you could never be 100 percent sure who was saying what to whom.
Now, then it's important to understand how the channel actually operated. It's
                    often presented by people who write on it as if the White House just invented
                    its strategy and went ahead on its own. But this isn't actually how it operated.
                    General Goodpaster, and I suppose myself in the interim between the election and
                    the inauguration of the President, established a very systematic national
                    security procedure which operated through various regional groups, through a
                    senior review group, to the National Security Council. And I would urge
                    historians who now seem to me to specialize on finding a sentence in a phone
                    conversation that demonstrates what they thought they already knew to begin
                    with, and do it more as a criminal investigation than as a historical
                    investigation. I urge them to read these inter-departmental meetings, the
                    Washington Special Action Groups, which were done in great detail. What we did
                    in the channel was we took the material from these special--from these groups
                    and we selected one of the options, so everybody participated in creation of the
                    options but not everybody participated in the choice of the options. And this is
                    how the channel--how it was possible to conduct this wide array of negotiations
                    with the Soviet Union basically through a channel restricted to two individuals
                    because, actually, the input of the bureaucracy was very decisive. And
                    ironically, it worked very well as long as the bureaucracy didn't know that the
                    channel existed, because then they put forward their best efforts to find a
                    consensus in the inter-departmental process.
Once it became clear that the channel existed, in late '72, then each of the
                    elements in this process would put forward their maximum position and let the
                    White House worry about resolving it. So, actually, by the time I became
                    Secretary of State, the channel, as the channel was breaking--was not breaking
                    down as a channel, but the bureaucratic backup for it was breaking down, D&#233;tente
                    got on a violent controversy. And so then when I was made Secretary of State,
                    the channel in its old sense didn't exist anymore because it moved into the
                    State Department. I could use State Department backup, and all it was then was a
                    very intense conversation between the Secretary of State and the Soviets, and
                    the Soviet Ambassador, who was outstanding.
One of the attributes of this channel was that we could spend time on
                    philosophical issues. We did not come to each meeting with a formal position and
                    begin negotiating. We would have sessions which I described, or which we
                    described to each other, as thinking out loud. And I would say, for example,
                    "Let me tell you how we think about this problem. We haven't made a proposal
                    yet, but when we make a proposal, you ought to understand the thinking that is
                    behind it. And if there is a crisis, you ought to understand what we are trying
                    to achieve." And I think that brought--there must be many documents to that
                    effect in here, and this helped negotiations.
Nor should it be thought that the channel was an idyllic friendship (inaudible).
                    On what we called the month of crisis, when simultaneously a Soviet submarine
                    base was built in Cienfuegos, Soviet troops appeared along the Suez Canal,
                    Syrian troops invaded Jordan, that was not what you would describe as an idyllic
                    period. But the channel continued to work. Similarly, during the India-Pakistan
                    crisis, which was not--which was handled as far as the White House was concerned
                    as a Soviet-Indian cooperation, in the interval between my visit to China in
                    19--in July and Nixon's visit to China in February. So it had to us a
                    geopolitical consequence which transcended the Bangladesh issue.
But I think I've given you a flavor, but what emerged out of this was a degree of
                    confidence in understanding each other's perceptions, of the necessities of
                    handling crises and of a larger view. As far as the American public was
                    concerned, we felt it imperative to demonstrate a commitment to peace. As far as
                    the Soviet Union was concerned, we felt it important to demonstrate to the
                    Soviet Union that if they conducted the foreign policy of a normal great power,
                    we would have differences but they would be manageable differences. What would
                    drive differences out of control was the attempt to achieve domination in areas
                    that were of vital interest to us or vital interest to both of us.
And it is based on these assumptions that a number of agreements were made. And
                    for example, the Strategic Arms Limitation Agreement, which was really an
                    attempt by us to cap the growth of the Soviet missile force, and whose numbers,
                    even though it became very controversial, whose numbers were never altered in
                    the 25 years that followed it or in the 20 years that followed it. The statement
                    of certain principles of international conduct--of course, we knew countries
                    would not consult their lawyers and see what principles, but they would create a
                    basis from which one could either come together or come to a place of
                    resistance.
Access to Berlin was handled in this manner and led to an agreement that lasted
                    for the entire Cold War period.
Then, in America we had Watergate, which was unpredictable, and the collapse of
                    executive authority, and even more the collapse of the comity between the
                    Congress and the Executive Branch and between the media and the Executive
                    Branch, so that issues became highly controversial that normally would have been
                    considered as part of tactical disagreements within an agreed framework. But
                    despite all of this, which was symbolized in part by the issue of Jewish
                    emigration, which we had handled in the channel and in which we had managed to
                    increase emigration from the Soviet Union from 900 to 40,000 and which once it
                    became a public issue dropped down to 10--15,000--it never went back--we did it
                    by doing--operating through the channel. And I'm not going to--the point here
                    it's not the degree of publicity one should give policy.
But with all of this, we managed to conclude the European Security Conference
                    which established certain moral principles or human rights principles, which
                    later on proved of the greatest significance.
Now, what does it mean for the current period? I must say I agreed completely
                    with what the Secretary of State said here. I think she expressed exactly what
                    my views would be on this issue. Russia is in a new and complex position. It has
                    lost 300 years of its history. Its borders are back to where they were under the
                    Peter the Great. This is bound to be an event of tremendous emotional
                    significance and it is bound to produce an attempt to reassert themselves.
Secondly, Russia borders three problematical borders from a geopolitical point of
                    view: a long border with China on the one side of which is highly
                    under-populated, on the other side it's over a billion people, in territory that
                    has been historically contested; a border with Russia--with the Muslim world
                    which is in the throes of a jihadist attempt to overthrow the state system as it
                    was developed; and then a western border which sort of one would say should be a
                    border of peace but which has been identified in the Russian mind with histories
                    such as in Ukraine or Georgia which have been part of Russian history and which
                    make it hard for Russia to think of them as totally foreign countries. But in
                    each of these borders, America and Russia have some common interests and
                    therefore should be able to cooperate to some considerable extent. And therefore
                    the question is how do we do it. I'm not saying that the methods used in the
                    Nixon Administration were ideal. Ideally, the relationship should be a very
                    strong Secretary of State, very close to the President; then the system works.
                    And that's substantially what is happening now.
But it is important to have a dialogue with--a permanent dialogue with Russia and
                    not one that is just geared to the immediate issues, a dialogue that can look
                    five years ahead. And I think that this visit of the Secretary of State and the
                    Secretary of Defense in Russia provides a forum where this can go and take
                    place. And of course, all of us in this room know it won't end with this
                    administration. The new administration will have to pick up where this
                    administration ends. And hopefully, not by eradicating everything that's gone
                    before, but to try to establish a level of permanence that's actually, since
                    Russia is also changing administrations to some degree, this is a requirement
                    (inaudible) as well. I have proved that I can't talk in 15 minutes. (Laughter.)
                    If you could hear me in German, it would go on even longer and you wouldn't get
                    to the verb until the end of 20 minutes. (Laughter.)
DR. SUSSER: Thank you, Dr. Kissinger. Dr. Schlesinger, please.


Opening Remarks by Dr. James Schlesinger
DR. SCHLESINGER: Thank you, and danke sch--n, Herr Kissinger. (Laughter.)
As the Secretary indicated, I was kind of a utility infielder during the early
                    years of the Nixon Administration. I had four separate jobs, the first of which
                    was handling national security for the old Bureau of the Budget and presiding
                    over what was a substantial administration-ordered decline in the defense budget
                    associated with the President's intent to reduce substantially our forces in
                    Vietnam and leading, by the way, to the first balanced budget in fiscal 1971
                    that we had enjoyed for some time.
Before moving into the Bureau of the Budget, I had been the Director of Strategic
                    Studies at the Rand Corporation, at which our central concern was the growth of
                    a Soviet counter-deterrent to America's strategic forces and what that might
                    imply about America's credibility for extended deterrence protecting our allies
                    in Europe. I shall return to that in a while.
The years of this volume, 1969 through 1972, I was wholly unencumbered with what
                    passed through the channel. The existence of such a channel comes as no
                    surprise, and should not have come as a surprise, and was quite welcome -- a
                    subject that I will come back to later on.
But Henry has covered some of the important details of the period leading up to
                    the administration. I remind you of some of them.
First, he has mentioned that the President had a profound contempt for the
                    Department of State. I will add that he had a profound contempt for the Central
                    Intelligence Agency as well. In 1968, the view in the intelligence community was
                    that the Soviet Union was only going to try to match us with regard to strategic
                    forces, that as we had leveled off at a thousand missiles, just over that,
                    1,056, all that the Soviet Union was prepared to do was to go up to that level,
                    match us, and then stop deploying missiles.
It did not turn out that way. And incidentally, for you scholars, it was not the
                    first time--or more recently is not the first time that intelligence assessments
                    may have been influenced by the attitudes of the political authorities, who felt
                    that the Soviets really felt endangered, that D&#233;tente was the way to deal with
                    that problem, and that they would indeed stop.
Now, this was in the period just after the announcement of the Brezhnev Doctrine
                    and the Soviet Union was feeling its oats in this period. America was
                    preoccupied, or so they felt, with Vietnam. There were some of our diplomats who
                    believed that that the Soviets really wanted to help us out in Vietnam. That was
                    rather an illusion.
The Soviets were talking about the correlation of forces, in which through the
                    forces of history, inevitably the balance of force was moving in favor of the
                    Soviet Union and against the West generally, and the United States in
                    particular.
As Henry has mentioned, in 1968 the Soviets had moved into Czechoslovakia. This
                    came as a surprise to the Office of the Secretary of Defense. It was astonished
                    because it was the feeling in the administration that the Soviets would not act
                    in a way that would endanger D&#233;tente. They did.
Incidentally, for people in the Operations Directorate as opposed to the
                    Intelligence Directorate at the CIA, Soviet action came as no surprise. They
                    felt that the Soviets had no alternative but to move into Czechoslovakia or
                    their empire in Eastern Europe would begin to fall apart.
Let me turn now to the central issue as far as I was concerned, which was the
                    arms issue. The Soviets, in the eyes of all and in particular in the eyes of our
                    European allies, had total conventional arms dominance. The allies, in
                    particular, felt that within days of a hypothetical Soviet move against the
                    West, that the Western position would collapse and that we would turn, or should
                    turn, to the use of nuclear weapons. That was the standard view.
And up until that time, they had had great confidence in the threat of nuclear
                    retaliation by the United States. But the growth of the Soviet
                    counter-deterrent, which basically started at the time of Cuba when the Soviets
                    discovered how naked they were compared to the United States, went on and slowly
                    the Soviets had built up.
So our concern was that the Soviets might marry strategic nuclear dominance to
                    their already conventional dominance. To deal with this, we strengthened our
                    conventional deterrent--ultimately, a story that we may come back to later--but
                    also changed our strategic doctrine.
The Europeans, as I mentioned, were squeamish in this period. Some, as the French
                    were under Charles de Gaulle, believing that the Americans would never trade New
                    York for Hamburg, as you may remember, and they were particularly squeamish
                    because they had lost confidence in the United States reflecting Vietnam.
The Seventh Army, which had been stripped of its most valuable personnel to be
                    shipped off to Vietnam, was in dreadful shape and the Europeans knew it. There
                    was widespread use of drugs and there was their great protector--in their eyes,
                    mistakenly--caught in Vietnam and with the declining forces and a declining
                    capability to protect Europe. That went on for some years and I will come back
                    to that.
In 1973, I became the Director of Central Intelligence, and in an early briefing
                    to the National Security Council I pointed out what the immense advantages of
                    the Soviet Union in terms of throw-weight might be if it were married to
                    accurate MIRVed missiles or MIRVed reentry vehicles.
After the agreement on May the 14th of 1972, there was an explosion after the
                    agreement of research and development activities in the missile area by the
                    Soviets. We saw new missiles going--being tested, and in particular the SS-18
                    and the SS-19, which were substantial improvements over the earlier generation
                    of missiles, the SS--11, the SS--13 and the like.
I publicly--by that time, I was the Secretary of Defense--I pointed out to the
                    press at that time this explosion of R&amp;D activity and what it might
                    imply with regard to the arms balance. And indeed, I announced our plans to
                    proceed with the MX missile, which was a large throw-weight missile.
At the same time, in respect to D&#233;tente and the need for avoiding the ability to
                    attack or undermine the capacity of either side to retaliate, that we were
                    prepared to give up on the MX missile if the Soviet Union were prepared to pull
                    down its own throw-weight. However, if the Soviet Union proceeded in the
                    direction that it was going, that we would indeed deploy the MX missile.
At the same time, I announced a change in our nuclear strategy which stressed
                    that indeed we would be prepared to use strategic forces against the Soviet
                    Union but that we would avoid cities in an attempt to persuade the Soviets in
                    response to any initiation by the United States attacking our own cities. And
                    following up on the discussion of the channel, that we would continue to seek to
                    have intra-ward communications with the Soviet leadership under those
                    circumstances. I think it important that during wartime that one--during a
                    nuclear exchange, that one sustain those communications so that there would be
                    less a risk of misunderstanding of what we were doing and presumably what they
                    would be doing.
In 1972, you will recall the part of the Moscow agreement was the basic
                    principles regarding coexistence. Those basic principles were substantially
                    blown apart with the start of the Middle Eastern war in 1973. The Soviets came
                    in strongly in support of their client-states; indeed, more importantly from our
                    standpoint, they had been egging on their client-states to attack Israel. That
                    was not consistent with the basic principles in which each side would avoid
                    taking advantage of circumstances to improve their marginal position, in this
                    case in the Middle East.
The 1973 war brought a significant change with regard to our standing in the
                    world, and particularly with our allies. With the start of the airlift to
                    Israel, of which most of our allies disapproved and some disapproved vehemently,
                    starting with the French Government, but notably the British Government as well,
                    that even though they disapproved of the airlift they did take note of the fact
                    that the United States was quite competent in carrying out that airlift, that
                    within 36 hours American supplies were landing in Israel to shore up the Israeli
                    position.
And the squeamishness that many of our allies had had to that point began to
                    disappear in that they recognized that the United States was quite capable of
                    effective action despite their European misgivings about Vietnam.
I think that I will simply point out that with regard to SALT II that the Soviet
                    negotiating stance was always one of seeking advantage relative to the United
                    States despite their full knowledge that undermining the American strategic
                    position would have consequences in terms of the Soviet standing in Western
                    Europe.
For example, the Soviets were always seeking to force us to withdraw our
                    so-called forward-based forces, forward-deployed forwards, and pull them back to
                    the United States at the same time that they would pull their own
                    forward-deployed forces back to within the borders of the Soviet Union. That is,
                    we would withdraw 3,500 miles, they would withdraw a couple of hundred miles. I
                    was always a strong supporter of the concept of D&#233;tente, but I wanted it to be a
                    balanced D&#233;tente.
Henry mentioned General Goodpaster. I should point out that General Goodpaster
                    had been a principal in the so-called Solarium conference at the start of the
                    Eisenhower Administration in 1961, and that President Nixon, when he was Vice
                    President, was fully aware of the existence of the Solarium conference.
Thus, the Nixon Administration was lodged with something called NSSM-1, which
                    was, in effect, a review by the larger bureaucracy under the guidance of Henry
                    Kissinger, of the position of the United States in the world. NSSM-1 came to the
                    conclusion that the military forces of the United States should not be prepared
                    for two and a half wars, but for one and a half wars, that there was a
                    recognition that our relationship with China that had been previously quite
                    hostile was undergoing change and would undergo further change. NSSM-1 was a
                    splendid example of how a government coming--a new administration coming into
                    power should review what it inherits from the past. I might point out that we
                    will have a new administration in 2009 and I commend to that administration
                    those kinds of procedures, recognizing the difficulties that now face American
                    foreign policy and the likelihood that a new administration will be tested early
                    on after 2009.
Thank you. (Applause.)


Relations between U.S. and Soviet Diplomats
DR. SUSSER: Thank you, Dr. Schlesinger. I'd like to remind everyone that you do
                    have index cards in your folders if you'd like to write down a question and pass
                    it to one of our people on the aisles if you have a question for our panelists.
Let me start by asking you both, a lot of commentary in the newspapers focuses on
                    the relationship between the President and President Putin and the Secretary and
                    her counterparts. Could you perhaps talk a little bit about the chemistry you
                    had with your counterparts and the chemistry President Nixon had with his Soviet
                    counterparts?
For example, Dr. Kissinger, in your forward, you note that Ambassador Dobrynin*
                    inscribed his memoirs to you as opponent, partner and friend. And you've already
                    said that it was not an idyllic friendship. Perhaps you could start by
                    explaining what the relationship was.
DR. KISSINGER: Well, the first thing you understand is that Dobrynin* was a
                    representative of the Soviet system. He, while he was Ambassador, became a
                    member of the Central Committee. Once he retired as Ambassador, he became head
                    of the Foreign Department of the Central Committee, which is a position nearly
                    equivalent of maybe--more than equivalent of that of the foreign minister.
So he clearly was there to achieve the strategic objectives of the Soviet Union,
                    and the strategic objectives of the Soviet Union at that time were correctly
                    described by Jim as serving the strategic advantage of the Soviet Union. They
                    were encouraging the Vietnam War, or certainly doing nothing to ease it. We had
                    a big disagreement with them about the invasion of Czechoslovakia, the
                    containment in Eastern Europe, a whole host of issues.
But we also had a number of common objectives. One was to avoid a nuclear
                    catastrophe for mankind. Secondly, gradually, as our dialogue continued, a
                    emerging attempt to find a long-term cooperation between the two countries.
                    Again, if you look at the record here, you will find that roughly until 1971
                    most of the channel consisted of dealing with various crises. After 1971, that
                    is, after my visit to China, the relations, the Soviet foot-dragging about the
                    possibility of a summit suddenly stopped, and then from the need to prepare a
                    summit emerged closer cooperation.
In 1973, there's a book that had been published by a notetaker of the Politburo
                    discussions which shows that the Soviet Union during that war was sort of
                    divided between those who wanted to serve D&#233;tente and those who felt that the
                    Soviet Union had an obligation towards liberation, and Soviet policy found
                    itself in the middle between those two, those two objectives.
But through that period I developed very great respect for the professionalism
                    and dedication of Anatoly Dobrynin. And I had no illusion that I could charm him
                    into doing something that was contrary to either his instructions or his
                    perception of Soviet interests. But I thought that within the margin that
                    diplomats sometimes have he would attempt to give a reasonable turn to it. And
                    if one reads his dispatches--I sometimes, as I pointed out in my introduction,
                    think he fell occasionally into the habit of diplomats of claiming more than the
                    conversation permitted. But on the big issues he gave a very accurate account,
                    and in the conduct of our negotiations on the factual material there was, as he
                    pointed out in his memoirs and as I confirmed, there was no substantial
                    difference in our perception. So the confidence we developed in Dobrynin helped
                    us to assess the reports that he was communicating to us.
But I never believed, and Nixon even less than I believed, that personal
                    relationships can overcome the fundamental strategic orientation of states, and
                    that our task was to effect a strategic orientation, not to have a good personal
                    relationship.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Of course, Al Haig is not here today, but I should point out
                    that when he became Secretary of State he rather ostentatiously cut off
                    Ambassador Dobrynin's access to the garage of the Department of State which he
                    had previously enjoyed as a signal of a change in U.S. policy. I'm not sure that
                    that was either effective or necessary, but that did occur.
DR. KISSINGER: Which he was one of those who arranged the access to the State
                    Department to begin with. (Laughter.)


Relations between the White House and U.S. Department of Defense
QUESTION: Dr. Schlesinger, you've observed that along with the profound contempt
                    that he had for the Department of State, President Nixon had a similar feeling
                    towards the CIA. What about the Defense Department?
DR. SCHLESINGER: President Nixon, to some extent, met his match in the Department
                    of Defense. (Laughter.) As did Henry Kissinger. (Laughter.) I refer not to my
                    tenure but the existence of one Mel Laird. Mel Laird was quite capable of taking
                    a different view on issues from those of the White House and he would reveal
                    these things in his intimate conversation with his old buddies down there on
                    Capitol Hill. And what do you know? As a result of that, you would find at the
                    end that Capitol Hill seemed to insist that we not do something that the White
                    House was inclined to do, but indeed followed the preferred route of Mel Laird.
I might add to that, Mel Laird liked to have a drink in the evening. This, I
                    hope, is not a surprise to anyone here.
DR. KISSINGER: He liked to have what?
DR. SCHLESINGER: A drink, with his friends. And one evening, he was sitting there
                    in his office at the Pentagon and he observed with regard to his Deputy
                    Secretary, he said, "The trouble with David Packard is that he thinks that the
                    shortest distance between two points is a straight line." That tells you
                    something about David Packard, but it tells you a lot more about Mel Laird.
                    (Laughter.)
DR. KISSINGER: Of course, I do not think that among the qualifications of a
                    cabinet member should be necessarily his ability to sabotage the preferences of
                    the President. (Laughter.) And while it's important to have cabinet members who
                    are prepared to challenge the President, at the end of the day an administration
                    has to be coherent. And I had--actually, I had high regard for Laird. The
                    disagreements between Schlesinger and Laird had often to do with the rate of
                    withdrawal from Vietnam, not about the total numbers but who would get credit
                    for what increment of withdrawal. And some student of political science will
                    study it someday.
And Nixon was no slouch in maneuvering either, so the question was who would
                    get--the rate of withdrawal was not usually--was not--there was no disagreement
                    about the rate so much but about who would make the announcement and in what
                    increments. And when an increment was announced, for example, if 150,000 were
                    announced, do you frontload it, take most of them out at the beginning, or take
                    most of them out at the end? And on those things Mel got his share of the
                    credit. It was not of, I think, historic significance but it was for a student
                    of bureaucratic maneuvering it showed that Mel would have been a proud member of
                    the Harvard faculty to participate in its maneuvering. (Laughter.)
DR. SCHLESINGER: On that particular point, Mel had strong inclinations going back
                    to his Wisconsin roots that we nearly ought to draw in our horns, and
                    particularly with regard to Vietnam. By the summer of '72 when General Abrams
                    left Vietnam, we had essentially destroyed the Vietcong in South Vietnam and we
                    had neutralized the North Vietnamese. One could argue, I have argued, that we
                    had by that time won the war and then we subsequently threw it away.
But the constraints that were placed by the Pentagon on General Abrams were
                    substantial and, in my view, debilitating with regard to the speed of
                    withdrawal. And General Abrams was the good soldier; he took all of these orders
                    and carried them out, but he was not happy to do so.
DR. KISSINGER: On the whole, Nixon was for the slower rate.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Mm-hmm.


Differences in Policy between Nixon and Ford Administrations
DR. SUSSER: Perhaps you could comment on the difference in the way the
                    bureaucracy functioned and in the way the White House functioned with the
                    cabinet agencies when the changeover came from Nixon to Ford.
DR. KISSINGER: Ford had never run for the presidency. He was as close to a normal
                    human being as we'll ever get in that office. (Laughter.) He was not driven by
                    public relations. And Nixon had had a very complicated life, and Nixon did not
                    like to face disagreement face-to-face. So if one wanted to have an impact on
                    Nixon, it was much better to do it with memoranda than in a cabinet meeting or
                    in a--or through a--Ford had no such problems. So the interdepartmental process
                    was calmer under Ford than it was under Nixon, and there wasn't that dual system
                    anymore of a Security Advisor and a Secretary of State so that had a quality of
                    calming it down.
For awhile, I was both Secretary of State and Security Advisor, which is a bad
                    system because it gives one person too great an influence. It also creates an
                    anomalous situation when you appear as Security Advisor and the Deputy Secretary
                    of State represents the State Department. But he'd be mad if he disagreed with
                    his Secretary as Security Advisor. (Laughter.) It was not a good system and it
                    was correctly abandoned.
So as it turned out, towards the end of the Ford Administration, however, the
                    country was so divided on the issue of D&#233;tente that the governmental process
                    didn't work so well anymore. There was always a lot of discussion about
                    disagreements between Jim and me when he was Secretary of Defense, but in fact
                    we lived in the same universe and we were going to come to an agreement
                    somewhere along the line.
When Rumsfeld came in, and I've said that often publicly, who was a political
                    figure, and we had a disagreement, there was no way of solving the political
                    dispute that had arisen, so that the negotiations became stalemated until there
                    was a new administration. I don't think that would have happened--I said so at
                    the time--when Jim was in office. So one had to consider that. But I had
                    personally huge affection for Ford and I think he contributed enormously toward
                    the healing of the country that was in very bad shape when he took it over.
DR. SUSSER: Dr. Schlesinger, would you like to talk a little bit about taking
                    over Defense from Mel Laird?
DR. SCHLESINGER: Well, I didn't take it over from Mel Laird, as a matter of fact.
                    I took it over from Elliot Richardson.
DR. SUSSER: Right, right.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Elliot Richardson having been handed the Department of Justice
                    after the departure of the previous attorney general. Elliot, who was always a
                    good soldier, or tried to be, tried to broker, as it were, the problems of the
                    President with regard to the issues of Watergate. But there was only so far that
                    he would go, and so Elliot, through the rest of his life, observed that the best
                    job he ever had in Washington was being Secretary of Defense. And he didn't
                    comment on his opinion about the Department of Justice, but I don't think that
                    he liked it as much as he had Health, Education and Welfare.
Taking over--as Henry mentioned, on many strategic issues he and I saw eye to
                    eye, at least in the large if not with regard to details. So even when I was
                    Director of Central Intelligence he made use of me, if I may put it that way, in
                    dealing with certain of our problems, of our international problems. So when I
                    took over as Secretary of Defense, I was in a position, having known Henry on
                    and off for 40 or 50 years, to share with him many of his strategic goals. As I
                    said earlier, I was for D&#233;tente. I was for a balanced D&#233;tente.
DR. KISSINGER: I might tell you an instance of the channel breaking down. When I
                    was in Moscow in 1973 at the end of the October war, my strategy was to gain as
                    much time as possible because the Israeli situation was improving and our
                    negotiating position would therefore improve. And so the President had invited
                    me to dinner on a Saturday night just after I arrived and said we have to settle
                    this as quickly as possible. I said to him, "Yes, but of course you realize that
                    I have to check everything with President Nixon and so you have to take this
                    into account." And he pulled out a cable he had received that day from President
                    Nixon giving me full powers to do--(laughter)--so when I got back to the guest
                    house, even though I knew the lines were open, I called up Haig and I said,
                    "Have you lost your mind? Why would a cable like this be sent to me?" And kept
                    going on in my emphatic way. (Laughter.) And Haig said, "Will you get off my
                    back? I have problems of my own." (Laughter.) And I said, "What problems can you
                    possibly have on a Saturday night in Washington?" It turned out it was the night
                    of the Saturday night massacre when everything went to hell.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Incidentally, there was the Saturday night massacre that led to
                    our special concern growing into the so-called nuclear alert that occurred a
                    week later after Brezhnev's stiff letter about moving into the Middle East with
                    us or without us, as he put it. And we feared that after the Saturday night
                    massacre--you had the first calls in the Congress for Nixon's impeachment. There
                    hadn't been such calls, basically, since the impeachment of President Johnson in
                    1865 or '6, so that was a new experience at that time. Subsequently, cries for
                    impeachment of the President seemed to be quite common. (Laughter.)
And we feared that the Soviets might be concluding that the American Government
                    was paralyzed, that it could not act, and it was for that reason, amongst
                    others, that we responded to Brezhnev's note with the so-called nuclear alert,
                    which incidentally was not just nuclear, it was our forces all over the world.
DR. KISSINGER: And which had been done more or less before in 1970 during--when
                    Syria invaded Jordan and more or less the same procedure was used, except in
                    1970 it didn't leak until the crisis was over. In '73, it leaked within two
                    hours.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Well, you can't put a couple of million people on alert all over
                    the world without its passing to the press.
DR. KISSINGER: No, but that was the purpose. (Laughter.) No, the purpose was not
                    necessarily to get it into the press. The purpose was to--
DR. SCHLESINGER: Yeah, was to convey it to the Russians.
DR. KISSINGER: We were sending a message to the Soviet Union and we wanted to
                    make sure that they understood we meant it.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Well, there was alerting the Air Defense Forces, which were all
                    in the reserves, so at 2 a.m. in the morning somebody would get a call and begin
                    to dress to go down to base, and his wife would say to him, "Where are you going
                    at 2 a.m. in the morning?" And he would respond, "I can't tell you because it's
                    a secret." That isn't the way it works. He would say quite clearly, "I've been
                    summoned back to the base because we've gone to alert status." So there was no
                    way that as far as the domestic scene was concerned that we going to be able to
                    keep this kind of thing secret.
DR. KISSINGER: But before we see horror stories here again of the imminence of
                    nuclear war, it was not an alert status that brought us close to nuclear war. It
                    was an alert status that showed that we were getting ready for the actions that
                    Brezhnev had threatened.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Quite right.
DR. KISSINGER: What we thought Brezhnev had said.


The Opening to China
DR. SUSSER: You mentioned risk of war. And again, in your forward you comment
                    here that when you were thinking about the opening to China you had four senior
                    ambassadors--Kennan, Bohlen, Kohler and Thompson--who all warned that an opening
                    to China would run the risk of a war with the Soviet Union. Obviously, you
                    discounted that, but perhaps you could go a little bit into--
DR. KISSINGER: But one had to understand the structure of the State Department at
                    that time. The China hands had been more or less purged in the 1950s so there
                    was really were very few, I would say none, no senior State Department people,
                    that could come to the attention of the President on China. I'm sure there were
                    desk officers, but the emphasis of the State Department as a result of the Cold
                    War had been on Russia. So there were experts like Kennan, Tommy Thompson, Chip
                    Bohlen, Foy Kohler, who had developed very strong views.
Now, we decided in--well, we decided right away, but we decided formally in May
                    of '69 when we became concerned of a possible Soviet attack on China that a
                    successful Soviet attack on China would affect the global equilibrium in such a
                    way that we needed to prevent it even though we had no relations whatsoever with
                    China. So we began to make a series of moves. Secretary Richardson made a speech
                    on China relations and we started doing relatively minor things, like for
                    example lifting the prohibition against buying Chinese goods by permitting
                    Chinese--by permitting American tourists in Hong Kong to buy $100 worth of
                    Chinese goods. And there were a number of other things of a minor nature that
                    which these State Department people that I mentioned--those four--were very
                    sensitive to that. And they realized what--they understood what we were doing,
                    and so they asked for an appointment with President Nixon.
And they warned him that the Soviet Union would not accept this and that it would
                    lead to a breakdown of relations and probably to war. And we decided that the
                    benefits of the course on which we had decided were too great and that we could
                    not exclude that part of the human race by--because of Soviet blackmail. But
                    these were superior Foreign Service officers who had made a great contribution,
                    but that was a strong view in the Department at the time.
There were others, like say Alex Johnson, who was not a China expert but an Asia
                    expert, who once we had made the move proved extremely helpful in helping us
                    implement it.
DR. SCHLESINGER: I need scarcely point out to this audience that the greatest
                    achievement in a way of the Nixon Administration was the breakthrough with
                    China. I am hesitant to sort of suggest that somebody like George Kennan, with
                    all of his wisdom, may have been a bit parochial on that occasion, not to
                    mention Foy Kohler or Chip Bohlen. But there is a tendency to fall in love with
                    one's client, and the reaction of the Russians inevitably, in my judgment, was
                    going to be to be much more attentive to the United States as we quite clearly
                    moved into triangular diplomacy.
DR. KISSINGER: That's exactly what happened.
Using --the Channel-- to Facilitate Jewish Migration out of the Soviet Union
DR. SUSSER: In your opening comments, you remarked that you used the confidential
                    channel to increase Jewish emigration from the Soviet Union from 900 up to
                    40,000. How did you manage to persuade the Soviets to open up the floodgates, so
                    to speak?
DR. KISSINGER: What we did is to say--that was at a time when the Soviet Union
                    had its own reasons to improve relations with the United States. And the only
                    thing different from the then policy to what later became official policy was
                    this: I told Dobrynin that we were constantly being appealed to about some
                    hardship cases that were on the agenda. There were about 700, I think, hardship
                    cases. And when we came in, about 900 Soviet Jews were permitted to emigrate. I
                    told Dobrynin that among the gestures they could make that we would take as a
                    sign of taking seriously the importance of improving relations would be an
                    increase of Jewish emigration; that we would not take advantage of this by
                    publicly taking credit for it. And we said something that human rights advocates
                    will not like: We said we don't claim that we have a right to say this to you.
                    We say that it's a criterion that we will apply to your international relations.
And as a result, every year the number of emigrants increased and reached, I
                    think, 37,500 in 1972. Then, as a result of the summit that was unsuccessful as
                    far as Egyptian concerns were concerned in '72, Soviet advisors were expelled
                    from Arab countries and the Soviet leaders became nervous about their relations
                    with the Arab world in which they, up to then, had been dominant, and started
                    putting an exit tax on Jewish emigration.
Jackson, Senator Jackson, then came up with the Jackson Amendment, which at first
                    we sort of welcomed, but then the Soviet Union gave in on the exit visa but
                    Jackson continued on his course and a dispute developed between the
                    administration and Jackson, for whom we had very high regard. At any rate, the
                    emigration never reached the level that it had had before. But I don't claim
                    universal applicability to this method. This is how it was done between '69 and
                    '72. It's not the way it can be done today.
DR. SCHLESINGER: I should point out the Jackson-Vanik Amendment is still in the
                    law and is still--what shall I say?--a bothersome element in the U.S.-Russian
                    relationship today.
In the first paragraph of his forward, Henry observes to Dobrynin, "'When we are
                    both out of government service, which will be a lot later for you than for me, I
                    hope you will let me read the reports you send in on me.' This comment was made
                    in the bantering style that Dobrynin and I used in our personal exchanges."
I think that points to the fact that none of us, none of us, expected to see the
                    Soviet Union collapse, that we were going to deal with a more or less perennial
                    state of quasi-hostility, quasi-agreement between the two countries. The
                    ultimate collapse of the Soviet Union, which owed a good deal to the genius of
                    Mr. Gorbachev, came as a surprise to many of us.


Discussion of the Collapse of the Soviet Union
DR. SUSSER: I should note just in passing that I was flipping the channels last
                    night, and just before midnight I turned to C-SPAN and they were broadcasting a
                    February 1992 interview with President Nixon in which his comment was,
                    "Communism committed suicide in the Soviet Union." So I guess he did not foresee
                    it either, in your view?
DR. KISSINGER: No. We thought--what Nixon and I thought was that what was
                    described as the satellite orbit would disintegrate, but not as fast as it did.
                    But we thought that the Soviet Union would not be able to maintain it
                    indefinitely, but we had a question mark in our mind how the Soviet Union would
                    react when its East German satellite would collapse or was in danger of
                    collapsing. And that's, in our mind, if we had been asked to predict the future,
                    would have said (inaudible) it's an element that could lead to a serious crisis.
                    But none of us, neither Nixon nor I nor any of the Soviet advisors we consulted,
                    ever spoke of the disintegration of the Soviet Union. And in fact, if you
                    remember, Bush 41 when he took a trip to Ukraine in '91 after the Soviet Union
                    was already in the process of disintegration made comments that indicated that
                    he was dubious about detaching Ukraine from the Soviet Union.
DR. SCHLESINGER: It was from that experience, by the way, that the Chinese
                    learned, watching Gorbachev start with perestroika and opening up the society to
                    all of the criticisms, and then subsequently start--subsequently beginning
                    restructuring of the Soviet economy, that that was the wrong way to proceed. The
                    Chinese learned, may have over-learned, that you start with restructuring the
                    economy and you are very, very slow in proceeding with perestroika.


Soviet Diplomats as Judges of Domestic Conditions in the United States
DR. SUSSER: How would you say Dobrynin and the Soviet leadership were as judges
                    of what was going in the United States? Were they accurate in their estimate of
                    our domestic politics, our policy? How good were Dobrynin's reports back home?
DR. KISSINGER: I haven't read the whole book but I've read a good slice of it. I
                    think his reports-his reports were quite accurate. He sometimes, I had the
                    impression, collected a lot of things together elsewhere and ascribed them to
                    the highest level people he could find. But diplomats have done that before. But
                    they were essentially accurate, I thought.
I have my doubts that the recipients of these reports had an equally accurate
                    understanding. And for example, in Gorbachev's memoirs, it's clear that Gromyko
                    had a less precise understanding of American domestic politics than Dobrynin
                    did.
DR. SCHLESINGER: Nobody stays in office--no ambassador stays in office for over
                    20 years by continuously sending back reports with which his bosses disagree,
                    particularly if those bosses are running a totalitarian system. So I suspect
                    that Ambassador Dobrynin felt obliged, and certainly did, to pull his
                punches.


Terrorism, Human Rights, and Other Global Issues
DR. SUSSER: The period of the Nixon and Ford administrations--we talked a lot
                    about D&#233;tente, but there were other issues that were coming to the fore during
                    this period, and in fact, the Department of State, for example, was evolving.
                    Terrorism, human rights, environmental issues, refugees--during this period we
                    added new functions and new bureaus. How did you view issues like that in the
                    concept--in the grander picture of relationship with the Soviet Union?
DR. SCHLESINGER: Be careful what you say about human rights. I'm sitting right
                    next to you. (Laughter.)
DR. KISSINGER: Terrorism was at that time not an issue. We dealt with terrorism
                    by refusing any negotiation with terrorists. But it was a minimal issue in our
                    time.
Now, on human rights, we took this position, or I took this position, and I still
                    take this position: America always has to be concerned about human rights. That
                    is part of the American tradition. America is also a great country, a great
                    state, and it has its national interests. And therefore, I do not think we can
                    make an absolute requirement that human rights always trumps the national
                    interests, but we also must not set up an opposition between national interests
                    and human rights.
So on--I mean, there's a lot being written about Chile. When I visited Chile, I
                    made a speech defending the American commitment to human rights. We voted with
                    the Organization of American States on the human rights issue. But when I saw
                    Pinochet, I did not give him a lecture on human rights, but spoke about the
                    practical consequences of his conducting his policy and put the request for
                    releasing prisoners in those terms.
And that's the sort of thing that some 30 years later people pick out one
                    memorandum of conversation. Did we strike the correct balance necessarily? I
                    can't say that. When Ford became President, one of the first things I did was to
                    give him a copy of the Gulag Archipelago and told him to read this, because I
                    considered Solzhenitsyn one of the great figures of our period. But when
                    Solzhenitsyn came to Washington, I was in favor of Bush--Ford seeing him, but
                    not in an ostentatious way in which there would be a lot of pictures taken and
                    could be interpreted as a confrontational pose. Was that the right mix? It
                    certainly received a lot of criticism. Jim, at that time, thought the more
                    ostentatious association was necessary. I made no effort to stop him from doing
                    that.
But my basic view is, has been and in way is, that yes, human rights is a
                    fundamental aspect of the American experience. But so has to be the concern for
                    national interests, and we have to balance these from case to case. And that
                    will always be controversial.
DR. SCHLESINGER: You know, lecturing other countries on human rights in public is
                    not likely to change their policies. Over the weekend, I was reading George
                    Kennan's, who was earlier mentioned, philosophical memoir written in the last
                    stages of his life called, Around the Cragged Hill, which I commend to all of
                    you. And what Kennan said in there about human rights I think reflects not only
                    the attitude that Henry took or I took, but I think the correct view with regard
                    to American policy: that this is a world of sovereign nations; our ability to
                    adjust the policies of other nations with regard to their internal affairs is
                    quite limited. And in some cases, as we see now with the genocide amendment up
                    before the Congress, likely to be quite counterproductive to our national
                    interest.


Missed Opportunities from the D&#233;tente Years
DR. SUSSER: Do you think that there were any opportunities that you missed during
                    this period? Is there anything you would do differently in retrospect?
DR. KISSINGER: Why don't you answer some questions? (Laughter.)
DR. SCHLESINGER: When you're batting .1000, you can't improve on it. (Laughter.)
DR. SUSSER: Perhaps you could--we haven't really discussed in any great length--
DR. KISSINGER: In (inaudible) retrospect I would say this. And it concerns
                    Vietnam. I agree with Jim that I thought we had won the Vietnam War in
                    September. In October, when the North Vietnamese, when Hanoi accepted the
                    proposals we had made in January, to universal disapproval incidentally as being
                    much too tough, I made the decision on the spot there that I thought that it was
                    based on a misunderstanding by the North Vietnamese of the situation; namely,
                    that they thought our position would improve greatly after the election. But I
                    knew that we would not--that we would probably lose congressional seats and that
                    the Defense Department budget required us to cut down on our B--52
                    augmentations, and that therefore we should hurry the agreement. And we probably
                    could have dragged it out through the election. Nixon did not think he had
                    anything to gain from a Vietnam agreement, but he was willing to make it when he
                    saw it, but he left that essentially up to me. I could have dragged it out until
                    after the election.
In the light of what happened afterwards, I think it might have been better to
                    delay, but then Watergate would have destroyed everything, of which I had no
                    idea. But we couldn't have gotten better terms, but we could have got it in a
                    way that was less upsetting to the South Vietnamese perhaps.
DR. SCHLESINGER: In the summer of '73 in the Appropriations Act which President
                    Ford did approve, the Congress prohibited the use of American forces in and over
                    and offshore the states of the former French Indo-China to announce to North
                    Vietnam that we were unprepared in the future to use any force should have been
                    an early signal to them, but they didn't quite believe it. And it was only as
                    they tested us in the late--at the latter stages, starting in December of '74
                    and early in '75 when we were unable to make a response, that they poured in the
                    18 divisions which ultimately led to the collapse of South Vietnam.
DR. KISSINGER: I don't believe that the collapse of Vietnam in 1975 was
                    inevitable. We cut aid to Vietnam by two-thirds and cut off aid to Cambodia
                    altogether and prohibited any military intervention. Under those conditions,
                    Korea couldn't have survived and maybe some of our European allies couldn't have
                    survived. Could Vietnam have lasted forever? I don't know that. But I felt we
                    owed them an opportunity to see whether they could do what happened in--what
                    finally has happened in South Korea.
But I'm mentioning this, if you ask me what decision would I do differently now
                    if I had known, but I didn't know Watergate. I didn't imagine that the Congress
                    would cut off aid or these other measures, so this is hindsight.


Final Comments by Dr. Kissinger and Dr. Schlesinger
DR. SUSSER: We're just about at the end of our time limit. Perhaps you would each
                    like to just sum up your impressions over the--for a couple of minutes?
DR. SCHLESINGER: Some of our impressions about what?
DR. SUSSER: On the era, your experience, final words? Any advice for future
                    administrations?
DR. KISSINGER: I'd like to pick up a point that Jim made about Nixon (inaudible).
                    New administrations usually bring in with them a bunch of people who were in the
                    campaign and who have been running the campaign on the argument that they could
                    do a lot better. The margin of real choice for a great nation is finite and one
                    cannot keep tearing up trees to see where the roots are. So a new administration
                    should spend a month, or whatever time it takes, to assess where it finds itself
                    and to make a judgment about the range of its real choices. They don't have to
                    be the same as the previous administration's, but they can't be 180 degrees
                    different either.
And I think we are in a--the contribution of Nixon was that he recognized that he
                    was in a new period, we were in a new period with respect to the impact of
                    strategic weapons and the damage they could create, we were in a new period with
                    respect to China. He understood also the importance of reducing the balances in
                    the Middle East. And whatever criticisms one can make of Nixon, he was prepared
                    to undertake a long-range policy and to stick with it through turmoil.
I think a new president is coming in in a situation in which two or three
                    revolutions are going on simultaneously in the world, and these revolutions do
                    not have the same character. And therefore, the attempt to find a magic solution
                    that applies to all of them is going to be unfortunate. But to assess the
                    strength and to attempt to master them, it's essential, especially since we are
                    in a position not of dominance but of great influence, so that the conduct of
                    the United States from here on is going to be very decisive. And I hope this can
                    be done with at the same time removing much of the divisiveness on as much of a
                    nonpartisan basis as we can generate. And I'm sure those of us who are on this
                    platform will certainly cooperate.
DR. SCHLESINGER: An irony is that the United States, this great democracy with
                    all of its impulsiveness and willingness to suddenly change course, has become
                    the leading power in the world. It reflects what I've always called
                    DeTocqueville's challenge, if you remember Democracy in America. He states that
                    democracies have a very difficult time following a consistent foreign policy;
                    they are unable to plan in secret and preserve those secrets; they lack the
                    ability over many years consistently to follow the same policy. At the end of
                    the Cold War, I observed that we had beaten DeTocqueville's challenge because
                    for 40-odd years we had stood the watch on the Elbe, and that would have
                    surprised DeTocqueville. And it's not clear to me that we are in a position to
                    have the same consistency in dealing what is the principal challenge of this
                    era, which is the rise of radical Islam, and to consistently follow a policy
                    that will lead us to victory, survival, survival of the West. It's not clear.
DR. SUSSER: Thank you both. Thank you all for coming.
(Applause.)









Conferences


National Security Policy and
                                SALT I, 1969-1972

Foreign Economic Policy,
                                1973-1976

The American Experience in Southeast Asia,
                                1946-1975

U.S.-Soviet Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente,
                                1969-1976

Transforming the Cold War: The United States
                                and China, 1969-1980







Table of Contents


U.S.-Soviet Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente, 1969-1976

Conference Announcement

Schedule

Opening Remarks at the Office of the Historian's Conference on U.S.-Soviet
                    Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente, 1969-1976, Secretary Condoleezza Rice, East
                    Auditorium Washington, DC, October 22, 2007

Introduction to Roundtable Discussion of Former Government Officials 

Opening Remarks by Dr. Henry Kissinger

Opening Remarks by Dr. James Schlesinger

Relations between U.S. and Soviet Diplomats

Relations between the White House and U.S. Department of Defense

Differences in Policy between Nixon and Ford Administrations

The Opening to China

Discussion of the Collapse of the Soviet Union

Soviet Diplomats as Judges of Domestic Conditions in the United States

Terrorism, Human Rights, and Other Global Issues

Missed Opportunities from the D&#233;tente Years

Final Comments by Dr. Kissinger and Dr. Schlesinger
















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov/.</value><value>https://history.state.gov/.</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/program</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2012-national-security-policy-salt</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2011-foreign-economic-policy</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2010-southeast-asia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/program-anouncement</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/program</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/presentation1</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable1</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable3</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable4</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable5</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable6</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable7</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable8</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable9</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable10</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable11</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente/roundtable12</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente</id></item>