<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States, 1952&#8211;1954, General:
                    Economic and Political Matters, Volume I, Part 1

Document 221






Foreign Relations of the United States, 1952&#8211;1954, General:
                    Economic and Political Matters, Volume I, Part 1








700.5 MSP/12&#8211;754
Memorandum by the Special Assistant to the Secretary of
                            State for Mutual Security Affairs (Nolting) to the Secretary of
                                State1

[Washington,] December 7, 1954.
top secret

eyes only


Subject:
Organization Plans for the Mutual Security Program.

The Under Secretary gave me an outline yesterday evening of the tentative
                        conclusions reached with Secretary Humphrey at your meeting yesterday
                            afternoon.2 I believe you
                        would want me to give you my considered reaction to these proposals, even
                        though my view may run counter to what has already been tentatively
                        agreed.[Page 799]
I should say first that I fully appreciate the difficulties, both substantive
                        and of a personal nature, involved in a decision on this subject and I am
                        very happy that an initiative has been taken to face the issue and to
                        resolve it. However, if I understand correctly the nature of the proposed
                        solution, I must state my conviction that it moves us in the wrong
                        direction. I think those most closely connected with the foreign economic
                        field, including the foreign aid field, are unanimous in their opinion that
                        what is needed is more consolidation, not less. Certainly this is my own
                        conviction. The purpose of all of our actions in the foreign economic field,
                        including the Mutual Security Program with its military segment, is to
                        provide a tool to help fulfill our foreign policy objectives as determined
                        by the President and the Secretary of State. The Mutual Security Program, in
                        particular, is a single tool and can best be utilized to promote our foreign
                        policy when it is regarded and administered as a single tool. To divide this
                        tool among various agencies of government is to diminish its effectiveness,
                        however much cooperation and agreement is achieved among the heads of the
                        departments involved. It has been my experience that the inevitable workings
                        of departmental bureaucracies tend to segment and compartmentalize the
                        activities for which the various departments are responsible, and that no
                        amount of topside coordination can bring about a truly unified effort where
                        the various functional parts are distributed among a number of different
                        agencies and departments. My conclusion on this point, I think, is validated
                        by the history of the Mutual Security Program. Experience and
                        trial-and-error over the past five years has led to the conclusion that the
                        administration of these programs should be consolidated, rather than
                        proliferated. It is not enough, I think, to attempt to consolidate them on a
                            policy level. It is necessary also, in so far as
                        possible, to consolidate them on an operational
                        level.
I believe it is in the United States interest to continue for an indefinite
                        period the major activities of the Mutual Security Program. Changes in the
                        form of assistance, different and better techniques, longer range planning,
                        perhaps a different and better distribution of U.S. resources by area, are
                        doubtless needed and should be under constant consideration. Some of the
                        peripheral activities of the FOA (several of
                        which are imposed by legislation) should be dropped. But the major
                        components of this activity, I believe, are in the interest of the United
                        States so long as the cold war continues, and perhaps thereafter.
I think the decision to acquiesce in the &#8220;Mansfield Amendment&#8221;3 is a
                        wise one, since to buck this amendment would result in the [Page 800]alienation of support for the programs
                        themselves, to an extent that would jeopardize their authorization and the
                        appropriation of necessary funds to conduct them. I am quite clear, however,
                        that what the proponents of this amendment had in mind was not the
                        scattering of these functions throughout the government, but rather the
                        consolidation of the essential ones into two old-line departments of the
                        government&#8212;namely, the Departments of State and Defense.
I understand your reluctance to take back into the State Department a large
                        operating branch. It was, however, the clear desire of the Congress that the
                        non-military parts of the Mutual Security Program should be conceived,
                        formulated, presented, and administered by the Department of State. This was
                        for two reasons: to assure the Congress that these programs are in fact a
                        necessary tool of our foreign policy, and to bring about a unified
                        administration of them, both at home and abroad. It was also the clear
                        intention of the Congress that the military parts of the program should be
                        conducted by the Department of Defense, under the policy guidance of the
                        Secretary of State.
I do not believe the tentative decisions of yesterday, as I understand them,
                        accomplish the objectives of the Congress, nor do I think they are
                        administratively sound. Those proposals, as I understand them, envisage the
                        introduction of at least two and perhaps more operating agencies, and the
                        elimination of one. The two additions would be the Treasury Department and
                        the Commerce Department (for the Battle Act) and perhaps some other agency
                        or agencies for the Technical Cooperation Program, besides the Department of
                        Defense for military programs and for economic &#8220;defense support&#8221; grant
                        assistance. This would presumably leave the responsibility for the
                        coordination of the various programs with the Secretary of State, who could
                        not, in my judgment, exercise adequate control over their operation. I think
                        Mr. Saltzman could give you a first-hand account of the difficulty he
                        experienced in giving policy guidance to the &#8220;Occupied Areas Branch&#8221; of the
                        Defense Department, which was engaged in the economic aid business after
                        World War II, and I feel that such experience is relevant to your
                        consideration of this problem.
As stated in my memorandum to you of yesterday,4 I
                        think that unless the decision is made to take back into the State
                        Department the major non-military programs, the only sensible alternative is
                        to try to persuade the Congress to continue some such central coordinating
                        and operating agency as the FOA.

F. E. Nolting, Jr.




Addressed also to the
                            Under Secretary of State. Another copy of this memorandum is in the
                            Eisenhower Library, John Foster Dulles papers, 1951&#8211;1959, &#8220;ICA
                            Matters&#8221;.&#8617;

Attached to the memorandum of
                            this conversation found in the Dulles papers cited in footnote 1 above is a brief &#8220;Memorandum of
                            Conversation With Mr. Humphrey, Secretary of the Treasury (Mr. Hoover
                            present)&#8221;, Dec. 6, 1954, on the subject &#8220;Reorganization of FOA Functions&#8221;, drafted and signed by
                            Secretary Dulles. It reads as follows: &#8220;There was discussion of the
                                possibility of reorganizing the present functions of FOA along the following
                                lines:
&#8220;1. Military assistance programs and Defense support
                                programs to be administered by the Department of Defense once the
                                policy and amount had been decided on with the concurrence of
                                State.
&#8220;2. Economic assistance to take primarily the form of
                                &#8216;soft&#8217; loans and to be made by the Treasury Department under the
                                direction of the Department of State. Treasury would be authorized
                                to advance funds under these circumstances up to some agreed amount,
                                say $500,000,000 to $1,000,000,000, and when this amount was
                                exhausted then the matter would go back again to the Congress for
                                further authorizations if deemed desirable.
&#8220;3. Policing of
                                the Battle Act to be turned over to the Department of
                                Commerce.
&#8220;4. Handling of Technical Cooperation programs
                                recognized as requiring further study.&#8221;&#8617;

See the memorandum by Nolting to the Secretary of
                            State, July 12, 1954, p. 739.&#8617;

Supra.&#8617;













General: Economic and Political Matters


Preface

List of Sources

List of Abbreviations and Symbols

Foreign policy aspects of administrative transition: November 1952&#8211;January
                    1953 (Documents 1-13)
General foreign economic policy of the united states (Documents 14-30)
United States international trade and commercial policy (Documents 31-69)
United States foreign investment and economic development policy (Documents 70-95)
United States international monetary and financial policy (Documents 96-121)
United States international transportation and communications policy (Documents 122-143)
Foreign assistance policies under the Mutual Security Program (Documents 144-227)







Persons





Abbreviations &amp; Terms

FOAMSP














Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/../frus1952-54v01p1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/d221</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/d220</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/d222</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.14.102.5.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.14.102.10.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_799</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.14.102.14.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_800</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.14.102.17.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.14.102.5.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/d221fn1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.14.102.10.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/pg_739</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.14.102.14.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/d220</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.14.102.17.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/preface</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/sources</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/terms</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/comp1</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/comp2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/comp3</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/comp4</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/comp5</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/comp6</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/comp7</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_FOA1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_MSP1</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1/d221</id></item>