<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969&#8211;1976, Volume
                    XXXII, SALT I, 1969&#8211;1972

Document 262






Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969&#8211;1976, Volume
                    XXXII, SALT I, 1969&#8211;1972








262. Memorandum of Conversation1

Moscow, April 22,
                                1972, 11 a.m.&#8211;4:05
                                p.m.

PARTICIPANTS

Leonid I. Brezhnev,
                                General-Secretary of Central Committee of CPSU

Andrei Gromyko, Foreign
                                Minister
Anatoli Dobrynin,
                                Ambassador to USA

A. Alexandrov-Agentov, Assistant to Mr. Brezhnev

Viktor Sukhodrev, Interpreter
Mr. Samoteykin, Assistant to Mr. Brezhnev

Mr. Henry A.
                                Kissinger

Mr. Helmut Sonnenfeldt,
                                    NSC Senior Staff
Mr. Winston Lord, Special
                                Assistant to Dr. Kissinger

Mr. John Negroponte, NSC
                                Staff
Mr. Peter W. Rodman, NSC
                                Staff

SALT

Brezhnev: Now I would like to make
                            some comments on ABM limitation and the
                            freeze on ICBM&#8217;s. This is an important
                            measure, and we have been discussing it for two years now.
I want to show how the Soviet side solves problems in a constructive
                            spirit. We have taken into account all the communications made to us by
                            President Nixon. We have had quite a few over the past few months, and
                            we have tried to take them all into account, particularly those in the
                            most recent period.
[The General-Secretary then read the Soviet note on ABM&#8217;s:]2

&#8220;It is recognized as expedient to limit ABM systems in the U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A. to
                            covering the capitals and to one area each for the location of
                            land-based ICBM silo launchers.
&#8220;The location of ABM facilities for the
                            covering of the capitals would be limited to an area in the form of a
                            circle with a radius of 150 km whose center would be within the limits
                            of the capital.&#8221;
This is a reflection of your proposal to us.3

Kissinger: One member of our
                            delegation is an adviser to your delegation.[Page 775]
Brezhnev: [resumes reading ABM note:] &#8220;The location of ABM facilities for covering land-based
                                ICBM silo launchers would be
                            limited to an area in the form of a circle with a radius of 150 km whose
                            center for the United States would be in the area of location of ICBM launchers where the deployment of
                                ABM facilities is most
                            advanced.&#8221;
This also reflects your proposal.
&#8220;The quantity of ABMs and their launchers
                            for each side should not exceed 100 units for covering the capitals and
                            100 units for covering land-based ICBM
                            silo launchers.&#8221;
That, too, reflects your proposal.
So now you have something to take back, a proposal from your confidential
                            channel.
Kissinger: The only one which does
                            not reflect our official thinking, but that of a member of our
                            delegation, is the 150 km radius.
Mr. General-Secretary, let me say this is a constructive approach. I will
                            reserve comment until I hear what you say about submarines.
Brezhnev: Nothing.
Kissinger: Nothing.
Brezhnev: Be patient. What can I
                            say about them? They travel under water, we can&#8217;t see them, they&#8217;re
                            silent&#8212;
Gromyko: [in English] Puzzle,
                            puzzle!
Kissinger: You do have something
                            on submarines?
Gromyko: You can&#8217;t read it before
                            Sukhodrev!
[Sukhodrev then reads the text of the note on submarines:]
&#8220;We have thoroughly considered the state of affairs at the strategic arms
                            limitation talks taking into account the considerations expressed by the
                                US side through the confidential
                            channel, relating to the freeze on ballistic-missile carrying
                            submarines.
&#8220;In this connection we believe it appropriate to state the following:
&#8220;1. The question of the freeze on the number of modern ballistic-missile
                            carrying submarines and the total number of launchers thereon is of very
                            significant importance.
&#8220;Ballistic-missile carrying submarines occupy a special place in the
                            composition of strategic offensive weapons and their consideration
                            should not overlook differences in the geographies of the sides, the
                            ballistic-missile carrying submarines at the disposal of the USNATO allies and the US forward submarine bases.
&#8220;As is known, that offers important strategic advantages to the American
                            side, and under these conditions the number of submarines and ballistic
                            missiles thereon at the disposal of the sides cannot be the same.
&#8220;2. In order to bring about relaxation of international tensions,
                            normalization of relations between our two countries and cessation of
                                [Page 776]the strategic arms race we
                            agree to consider the question of including ballistic-missile carrying
                            submarines in the suggested freeze agreement provided, naturally, that
                            there should be established for the sides appropriate limits for such
                            systems taking into account the considerations set forth above.
&#8220;The Soviet Union would agree that the US
                            and their NATO allies should have, for
                            the period of the freeze agreement, up to 50 modern submarines with the
                            total number of ballistic missile launchers thereon of up to 800,
                            including 41 submarines with 656 ballistic missile launchers thereon at
                            the disposal of the United States. Over that period the Soviet Union
                            could have 62 modern submarines with the total number of ballistic
                            missile launchers thereon of no more than 950.
&#8220;It is understood that over that period the sides will reduce the number
                            of land-based ICBMs through dismantling
                            older launchers. The sides would also be entitled to modernize and
                            replace older submarines by new submarines but without increasing in the
                            process the above-mentioned number of modern submarines and ballistic
                            missile launchers thereon.
&#8220;However, since the above proposal would only be a partial compensation
                            for the strategic disbalance in the location of missile carrying nuclear
                            submarines of the sides, the Soviet side proceeds from the premise that
                            the whole of this problem&#8212;and primarily the issue of dismantling US missile submarine bases outside the
                            territory of the United States, should be appropriately resolved in the
                            course of subsequent negotiations.
&#8220;If over the period of the Interim agreement the USNATO allies increase the number of
                            ballistic-missile carrying submarines to the excess of those operational
                            or under construction, the Soviet Union reserves the right to the
                            corresponding increase in such submarines.
&#8220;3. Taking into account the proposals of the US side the Soviet Union could agree to include in the
                            suggested freeze agreement the obligation not to start, in addition to
                                ICBM silo launchers, new
                            construction of fixed soft land-based ICBM launchers as well.
&#8220;4. Moscow believes it possible to have the period of the Interim freeze
                            agreement&#8212;5 years.
&#8220;5. Given understanding in principle on such an approach we would be
                            prepared to give necessary instructions to the Soviet delegation in
                            Helsinki to discuss practical matters related to the final elaboration
                            of the corresponding articles of the Interim agreement on certain
                            measures with respect to strategic offensive armaments having in mind
                            that this Agreement together with the Treaty on the limitation of ABM systems would be signed during the
                            forthcoming meeting in Moscow.&#8221;[Page 777]
Brezhnev: I think that is a very
                            constructive proposal and it is in keeping with the spirit of all those
                            communications you made through Ambassador Dobrynin. I would think President Nixon should think it
                            very constructive. Apart from the constructive nature of our proposals,
                            that paper is another sign of the spirit with which we approach the
                            Summit meeting.
Kissinger: If the
                            General-Secretary says as little on Vietnam as he said on submarines, we
                            will make enormous progress today.
Brezhnev: I&#8217;d have been pleased to
                            say less on Vietnam, but Dr. Kissinger took so much time.
Kissinger: That was meant as a
                            compliment. You had said you&#8217;d say nothing on submarines.
It&#8217;s a very constructive approach. I recognize that it incorporates many
                            of the points we made in the confidential channel. It is a serious
                            effort to address many of our concerns.
May I ask a practical question, simply for my understanding?
When you say, &#8220;Over the period the sides will reduce the number of
                            land-based ICBMs,&#8221; does this mean you
                            accept the obligation I mentioned to Dobrynin to dismantle older land-based missiles once we
                            grant you the right to build more submarines?
Brezhnev: That is what is implied.
                            We have accepted that principle. We won&#8217;t build new ones to replace the
                            ones removed. We will build submarines according to the terms allowed,
                            and we are prepared to inform you of the exact month and date we will
                            dismantle the ICBM facilities.
Kissinger: We will have a problem
                            in explaining to our Congress why you have a greater number of missiles
                            in both categories. If we have an understanding that you will dismantle
                            some of the older missiles, we will instruct our delegation to work out
                            the precise numbers. Semenov can
                            work this out with our delegation. We needn&#8217;t do it here, at this
                            level.
Gromyko: We will instruct
                            accordingly.
Brezhnev: It is very easy. Of
                            course we will be dismantling.
Kissinger: I only want to fix this
                            so we can make this instruction to our delegation and make this part of
                            the negotiation.
Brezhnev: We will give similar
                            instructions.
Kissinger: No problem. But I have
                            one other point. It is difficult for us to discuss limitations on
                            British and French submarines. It would be easier if you make a
                            unilateral declaration. We agree to 41, then if the British and French
                            build more than 9 and if the total number reaches more than 50, then you
                            can respond accordingly. This will be easier, because we have no right
                            to tell the British and French what to do. You will make unilateral
                            deal. We have no right to negotiate the total number.[Page 778]
Brezhnev: Of course. We shall
                            certainly give thought to a unilateral declaration. But the figures are
                            agreed.
Kissinger: The figures are agreed.
                            There is no problem about figures. I will show you what a bad diplomat I
                            am. Gromyko wouldn&#8217;t do this, but
                            I think the submarine matter is acceptable in principle.
Brezhnev: This shows what a strong
                            diplomat you are. I agree our Foreign Ministry would never do that, but
                            that&#8217;s an example of how bad it is.
Gromyko: It&#8217;s your advantage. I
                            would never have said this outright. I would have waited at least three
                            minutes.
Brezhnev: I don&#8217;t want to raise
                            the question at this time, but I do want to mention the serious matter
                            of the U.S. military bases ringing the
                            Soviet Union. This relates to your air force and intermediate range
                            missiles.
Sonnenfeldt: We have no IRBM&#8217;s.
Kissinger: We are going to ground
                                Sonnenfeldt.
Brezhnev: We mean forward-based
                            missiles. It doesn&#8217;t make any difference what kind of rocket you die
                            from.
Kissinger: Sonnenfeldt is right. We have no
                            forward-based missiles that can reach the USSR, but I understand the General-Secretary&#8217;s point.
Brezhnev: Of course it&#8217;s useless
                            to deploy intermediate range missiles in the U.S., so you deploy them abroad.
Kissinger: We have airplanes that
                            can reach the USSR. As it happens, we
                            have no missiles in Europe that can reach the USSR, but we have airplanes that can. But we understand the
                            General-Secretary&#8217;s point and we take it seriously.
Brezhnev: As we see it, this could
                            be the start of an important future process. It could be the start of
                            the strengthening of confidence; this should be followed by further
                            measure of goodwill to strengthen normal relations between our two
                            countries.
Kissinger: Agreed.
Brezhnev: . . . measures that
                            would be in no way prejudicial to obligations each of us has to other
                            countries, and would be at the same time encouraging to the Allies of us
                            both. Therein lies the greatness and noble purpose of our two
                            countries.
Kissinger: This attitude can be a
                            principal result of the Summit.
Brezhnev: These are indeed
                            problems of great importance. First, the statement of principles
                                yesterday,4 then this,&#8212;all this
                            carries great [Page 779]significance. It
                            will last the commentators and analysts about 2 years, until the next
                            Summit. I could write a good commentary. I could write a good article
                            for the U.S. press. How much do you pay
                            for a good article?
Kissinger: My only hope is that
                            the next meeting is sooner than 2 years, and I hope the General
                            Secretary can visit us next year.
Brezhnev: I don&#8217;t think I have an
                            invitation or visa yet.
Kissinger: You will have an
                            invitation when President Nixon comes here. We hope to have that in the
                            final communiqu&#233;.
Brezhnev: Thank you. In the coming
                            4 years, the United States and Soviet Union should take even more
                            important steps to increase the spirit of good will.
Kissinger: As for ABMs, Mr. General Secretary, we have
                            proposed using 2 ICBM fields, rather
                            than Washington and 1 ICBM field, but I
                            consider your proposal constructive.
Brezhnev: Then you said 2 and
                            2.
Kissinger: I will have to discuss
                            this in Washington, but we will do so in very positive attitude.
Brezhnev: Mr. Kissinger&#8212;I would not want this on the
                            record&#8212;this has the advantage for you, which your military are aware of,
                            that yours covers more ICBM&#8217;s than our
                            does.
Kissinger: I understand, but not
                            necessarily if they are 150 km radius. It depends on where you put your
                            fields.
Brezhnev: This won&#8217;t be the case.
                            The area will be clearly defined. It is a secret now, but not for long.
                            Your military will photograph it anyway.
Kissinger: If you can give me
                            informally some idea of the number of ICBMs you will put in this field, it would help persuade
                            some of my people. You don&#8217;t have to tell me the field, just an idea of
                            the number, to tell the President.
Brezhnev: I will tell you that
                            later.
Kissinger: It&#8217;s just for the
                            President.
Brezhnev: But I can say beforehand
                            that we will have fewer than you have.
Kissinger: May I make a
                            suggestion?
Brezhnev: It is not to be made
                            public. Because it is really to your advantage and it would be bad if it
                            came out.
Kissinger: I must be honest with
                            you. Anything in the White House we can keep totally secret. Once it
                            leaves the White House, as your Ambassador can tell you, I can&#8217;t
                            completely control it.
Brezhnev: That&#8217;s why I say I
                            should have invited Rogers in the
                            first place![Page 780]
Kissinger: You would have gotten
                            more publicity. Therefore what you tell me here will not become public.
                            Once agreement is completed, I can&#8217;t guarantee that numbers won&#8217;t become
                            public, but what the General Secretary says here will not.
Brezhnev: In nature of
                            speculation, but not officially.
Kissinger: But once we have a
                            treaty, our people will have to testify before Congressional committees.
                            We will try to control it, but the testimony will only happen several
                            months after an agreement.
Brezhnev: That&#8217;s a procedural
                            matter. If we agree on this principle, procedural matters won&#8217;t be a
                            problem.
Kissinger: The submarine matter is
                            certainly acceptable. The ABM matter I
                            will have to discuss in Washington but it is certainly in the direction.
                            . . .
Brezhnev: I feel it incorporates
                            your latest suggestion and incorporates the principle of equality, and I
                            don&#8217;t foresee changes.
Kissinger: I don&#8217;t see any
                            problems. Let me suggest the following procedure. I will take this up
                            with the President as soon as I return Monday or Tuesday.5 We&#8217;ll then call back our
                            negotiator from Helsinki and simultaneously get together with our
                            military people. All of this will take about a week. We&#8217;ll then instruct
                            our negotiator. If you can send your Ambassador back. . . . If in the
                            meantime Semenov can be kept under
                            restraint so he doesn&#8217;t reveal this, it would speed this matter.
Brezhnev: We have given him
                            instructions. But if you think this is easier, we can send him a
                            telegram to keep it back for a time.
Kissinger: Let me think about
                            it.
Brezhnev: We have enough time to
                            cable him to hold up.
Kissinger: When will he propose
                            it? Monday?
Gromyko: At his discretion. He met
                            with Smith yesterday and said
                            nothing.
Kissinger: He hinted at it.
Brezhnev: On submarines, Semenov knows nothing.
Kissinger: Let him propose it. Let
                            me on second thought talk to the President. I&#8217;ll tell Vorontsov.
Gromyko: We&#8217;ll hold Semenov up.
Brezhnev: We have a closed phone
                            link, so we will phone him immediately.
[Aide goes out to do so.][Page 781]
Kissinger: How should we do it in
                            Helsinki? Should they conclude the whole thing in Helsinki, or should we
                            leave something for the Summit? We can settle certain things privately
                            but not in Helsinki.
Brezhnev: The signing should be on
                            a high level. The final decision and signing should be at the Summit
                            level.
Kissinger: The signing and final
                            decisions should be at the highest level, yes.
Gromyko: Since this matter relates
                            to a text, it may be best for our delegations to finalize as much as is
                            possible. Because it is a text, the lawyers should look at it. If all is
                            done here, there is a risk of not having enough time. But the final
                            decision and signing should be here.
Kissinger: I agree with the
                            Foreign Minister that perhaps we should pick some issues, perhaps one or
                            two&#8212;I don&#8217;t want to take the time of the General Secretary on this&#8212;on
                            which the delegations should write the text, but then, the President and
                            the General Secretary can settle them here.
Gromyko: Deliberately you
                            mean?
Kissinger: Yes.
Brezhnev: But to have reached
                            confidential agreement beforehand?
Kissinger: Confidentially.
Brezhnev: So there will be a
                            special signing ceremony in the Kremlin.
Kissinger: We will have a SALT agreement, there is no question.
Brezhnev: I think so too.
Kissinger: I will let your
                            Ambassador know by the end of the coming week when we can proceed in
                            Helsinki, but it will be very soon.
Brezhnev: Good, because there is
                            not so much time left.
Kissinger: Let them talk about
                            radars this week. They have a lot to talk about.
Brezhnev: Yes. That&#8217;s my view. I
                            don&#8217;t think they&#8217;re in any hurry. They don&#8217;t have much to talk about,
                            but let them talk. Let them talk about the nature of the universe. The
                            Delegations should be locked in a room for the final 3 days without food
                            and told they must get an agreement or not get food for another 3
                            days.
Kissinger: We&#8217;ve reached the point
                            where despite all the efforts of our delegations we will still reach an
                            agreement.
Brezhnev: No matter how hard they
                            try! That&#8217;s our success.
Kissinger: Our delegation is so
                            complex we don&#8217;t understand them anymore.
Brezhnev: You want an example of
                            how to make something very complex? I can pose one or two questions that
                            neither you nor the President can solve for months. So we can consider
                            this closed.



Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, NSC Files, Box 485,
                                President&#8217;s Trip Files, USSR&#8212;Issues
                                Papers, Vol. IV. Top Secret; Sensitive; Eyes Only. The meeting took
                                place in the Guest House on Vorobyevskii Road. The NSC staff extracted this discussion of
                                    SALT from a memorandum of
                                conversation of the entire meeting, which covered a range of topics.
                                The memorandum of conversation is printed in Foreign
                                        Relations, 1969&#8211;1976, volume XIV, Soviet Union, October
                                    1971&#8211;May 1972, Document 139.&#8617;

See
                                    Document 252. All brackets are in the
                                original.&#8617;

Document 194.&#8617;

Brezhnev gave Kissinger this statement at their first meeting on
                                April 21; see Foreign Relations, 1969&#8211;1976, volume XIV, Soviet
                                    Union, October 1971&#8211;May 1972, Document 134. For the text
                                as signed by Nixon and Brezhnev, see Public Papers:
                                    Nixon, 1972, pp. 633&#8211;634.&#8617;

April 24 and 25.&#8617;













SALT I, 1969&#8211;1972


Preface

Sources

Abbreviations and Terms

Persons

SALT I, 1969&#8211;1972

Kissinger&#8217;s Secret Trip to Moscow
                        and Aftermath, April 19&#8211;May 17, 1972 (Documents 259-281)


Index








Persons

Brezhnev, Leonid
                            I.Dobrynin, Anatoly
                                F.Gromyko, Andrei
                            A.Kissinger, Henry
                            A.Lord, WinstonRogers, William
                            P.Semenov (Semyonov),
                                VladimirSmith, Gerard
                            C.Sonnenfeldt,
                            HelmutVorontsov, Yuli
                            M.




Abbreviations &amp; Terms

ABMCPSUICBMIRBMNATONSCSALTUSUSAUSSR














Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/../frus1969-76v32</value><value>https://history.state.gov/d262</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/d261</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/d263</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.2.16.9.4.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.2.16.9.10.4</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.2.16.9.13.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_775</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_776</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_777</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_778</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.2.16.9.74.3</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_779</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_780</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fn:1.3.2.2.16.9.100.3</value><value>https://history.state.gov/pg_781</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v14/d139</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.2.16.9.4.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/d252</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.2.16.9.10.4</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/d194</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.2.16.9.13.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v14/d134</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.2.16.9.74.3</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#fnref:1.3.2.2.16.9.100.3</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/preface</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/sources</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/terms</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/persons</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/comp1</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/ch7</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/index</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_BLI1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_DAF1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_GAA1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_KHA1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_LW1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_RWP1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_SV1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_SGC1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_SH1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/persons#p_VYM1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_ABM1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_CPSU1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_ICBM1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_IRBM1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_NATO1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_NSC1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_SALT1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_US1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_USA1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/terms#t_USSR1</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32/d262</id></item>