<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative











Principal Officers and Chiefs of Mission - People -
            Department History



Home

Department History

People

Principal Officers
                            and Chiefs of Mission







Principal Officers and Chiefs of Mission

Note: The information presented here is for historical
                            research and is not necessarily up-to-date. The Department of State
                            maintains a list of current Senior Officials and
                                Chiefs of
                                Mission.



All Principal
                                    Officers and Chiefs of Mission, Listed by Name

All Principal
                                    Officers and Chiefs of Mission, Listed by Year

Principal
                                    Officers, Listed By Title

Chiefs of Mission, Listed by Country

Chiefs of Mission, Listed By International Organization



Introduction
This online resource continues a 1991 publication of the Office of the
                        Historian, Principal Officers of the Department of State and United
                            States Chiefs of Mission. Our intent is to document the history of
                        U.S. representation abroad and the chief policymakers in the Department of
                        State. To that end, we have provided a chronological listing of principal
                        officers&#8212;essentially all Department officers at the level of assistant
                        secretary or above&#8212;and chiefs of mission. (See below for a discussion of the
                        term, &#8220;chief of mission.&#8221;) These two categories require Presidential or
                        Secretarial designation, and, in some cases, the approval of the Senate. We
                        have made an attempt to comprehensively list all people selected for these
                        positions, even if they were not approved by the Senate, died before taking
                        office, declined the position, or were otherwise unable to serve. For that
                        reason, the pages which list our chiefs of mission by country are split into
                        two categories: &#8220;Chiefs of Mission&#8221; lists those who held the office, and
                        &#8220;Other Nominees&#8221; lists those who did not.
Positions Included
This database includes officers of the Department who were presidential
                        appointees (appointed by the President with the advice and consent of the
                        Senate) and chiefs of bureaus who hold rank equivalent to Assistant
                        Secretary of State. These include: Secretaries, Deputy Secretaries, Under
                        Secretaries, Deputy Under Secretaries, Assistant Secretaries, Counselors,
                        Legal Advisers, Chiefs of Protocol, and certain administrators.
Other positions have, from time to time, been included in the database based
                        on their particular circumstances. The complete lists of heads of the United
                        States Information Agency, for example, are included. USIA was incorporated
                        into the Department in 1999. Other chiefs of mission of particular
                        historical interest have also been included.
Positions Excluded
This database does not include representatives, personal
                        representatives, or special representatives of the President or Department
                        of State; charg&#233;s d&#8217;affaires or charg&#233;s d&#8217;affaires ad interim (except under
                        certain circumstances); individuals holding diplomatic commissions jointly
                        with other representatives; special agents and other individuals on special
                        missions; high commissioners; chiefs of mission in charge of special
                        economic or aid missions; liaison officers; military governors or commanding
                        officers of occupying forces or their political advisers; delegates to
                        international conferences; or consular officers who held only consular
                        commissions.
What is a Chief of Mission?
According to the Foreign Affairs Act of 1980 (Public Law 96-465, Section
                        102(3) (22 U.S.C. 3902)) a Chief of Mission is &#8220;The principal officer in
                        charge of a diplomatic mission of the United States or of a United States
                        office abroad which is designated by the Secretary of State as diplomatic in
                        nature, including any individual assigned under section 502(c) to be
                        temporarily in charge of such a mission or office.&#8221;
The Chief of Mission is often &#8211; but not always &#8211; an Ambassador. There are
                        currently three classes of diplomatic representation established by the 1961 Vienna
                            Convention on Diplomatic Relations, Article 14: ambassador or nuncio
                        (accredited to the Head of State); envoy, minister, or internuncio
                        (accredited to the Head of State); and charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires (accredited to the
                        Minister of Foreign Affairs). These classes have a much longer lineage.
                        Although not a signatory, the United States followed Annex 17 to the
                        Congress Treaty of Vienna (March 19, 1815) which established rank and
                        precedence of diplomatic agents (ambassadors, envoys, and charg&#233;s
                        d&#8217;affaires). The Proces-Verbal of the Conference of Aix-la-Chapelle
                        (November 9, 1818), recognized ministers resident as an intermediate class
                        between Ministers and charg&#233;s d&#8217;affaires.
The United States first used the rank of Ambassador in 1893, when Thomas F.
                            Bayard was appointed Ambassador to Great Britain on March 30 of that
                        year.
A &#8220;charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires ad interim&#8221; refers to a diplomat temporarily acting for
                        an absent chief of mission. This database tracks all charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires and
                        charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires ad interim who served (1) for a continuous period of 12
                        months or more, (2) at the establishment or ending of diplomatic relations
                        with a country, or (3) at the closure or opening of an embassy.
Database Contents
The type of information for each entry included varies based on the type of
                        position. Entries will have some or all of these pieces of information:

Name
When possible, the full name of the appointee has been included.
Years of birth and death
State of residency
The appointee&#8217;s state or territory of legal residence at the time of the
                            appointment is taken from the commission, nomination, or a contemporary
                            official record of legal residence. If the residence was omitted from
                            these sources, the entry does not appear. Some officers changed their
                            legal residence during their careers; in such cases the entry for their
                            various appointments reflects the change in residence.
Career status (in the Foreign Service)
Appointees are not categorized as &#8220;career&#8221; or &#8220;non-career&#8221; before the
                            passage of the Foreign Service Act of February 5, 1915, which
                            restructured the Diplomatic and Consular Services. For Chiefs of Mission
                            holding office at that date, an asterisk by their names in the
                            alphabetical listing denotes those who were at the time of appointment
                            (or who had previously been for at least five years) Foreign Service
                            officers, Foreign Service information officers, or career officers in
                            the Diplomatic or Consular Services. The asterisk also indicates those
                            few individuals who served as diplomatic secretaries, who had then been
                            commissioned before as Chiefs of Mission or as Presidential appointees
                            in the Department of State, who were not serving as Chiefs of Mission in
                            February 1915, but who were subsequently appointed or reappointed as
                            such. All other appointees have no asterisk, even though they may have
                            been career officers in the civil or military services. Career status
                            reflects an individual&#8217;s status at the time of appointment. For example,
                                Richard Holbrooke served in the Foreign Service, but was not a
                            career member of the Foreign Service when appointed to his various
                            positions, so he is listed as &#8220;non-career.&#8221;
Dates of service
These dates are included on a position-by-position basis. Principal
                            officers of the Department who are presidential appointees have a date
                            of appointment, date of entry on duty, and date of termination of
                            appointment. An effort has been made to fix a date for the termination
                            of the diplomatic mission of each representative vis-&#224;-vis the host
                            government and to describe briefly in each individual case (and as
                            precisely as sometimes incomplete records permit) what action or event
                            brought the mission to either a formal or a de facto close. In the
                            nineteenth century it was customary for a Chief of Mission to present
                            his own letter of recall; in current practice most missions terminate in
                            actual fact with the departure of the Ambassador from his post. In all
                            periods there have been special circumstances (e.g., death, declaration
                            of war, severance of diplomatic relations) which have brought some
                            diplomatic missions to an end. It should be emphasized that the
                            effective date of a Chief of Mission's resignation frequently does not
                            coincide with the date shown here for the termination of his or her
                            mission abroad. For those who were designated by the Secretary, the date
                            of appointment is the same as the date of entry on duty. For charg&#233;s
                            d&#8217;affaires ad interim, dates of service are listed from and to the
                            nearest month.

Key Terms

Appointment
The date of appointment is that which appears upon the face of the
                            Presidential commission issued to the appointee. It is frequently
                            referred to as the date of commissioning or the date of attestation.
                            Recess appointments are valid only until the end of the current session
                            of the Senate. If the President wishes to keep a recess appointee in
                            office, the President must re-nominate the appointee.
Commission
A document attesting that the appointee has been appointed as a
                            principal officer of the Department or as a Chief of Mission. It is
                            signed by the President and the Secretary of State and bears the
                            impression of the Great Seal of the United States. &#8220;Commission&#8221; always
                            connotes Presidential action.
Designation
This term covers chiefs of bureaus of the Department who are selected by
                            the Secretary of State. Article II, Section 2 of the Constitution states
                            that &#8220;the Congress may by law vest the appointment of such inferior
                            Officers, as they think proper, in the President alone, in the Courts of
                            Law, or in the Heads of Departments.&#8221; &#8220;Designation&#8221; always connotes
                            Secretarial action.
Nomination
This is the date that the President sends to the Senate the name of a
                            person whom he wishes to appoint to a high-level position. Article II,
                            Section 2 of the Constitution states that the President, &#8220;by and with
                            the Advice and Consent of the Senate, shall appoint Ambassadors, other
                            public Ministers and Consuls, Judges of the supreme Court, and all other
                            Officers of the United States, whose appointments are not herein
                            otherwise provided for, and which shall be established by Law.&#8221; Per Senate Rule XXXI, &#8220;Nominations that are not confirmed or
                            rejected are returned to the President at the end of a session or when
                            the Senate adjourns or recesses for more than 30 days.&#8221;

Steps in Appointment
Nomination is the first step in the appointment process. The President
                        submits the name of the person to be appointed to a high-level position to
                        the Senate for approval by first the Foreign Relations Committee and then by
                        the full Senate. Approval by the full Senate is called &#8220;Confirmation.&#8221; The
                        appointee is then commissioned. After taking the oath of office, he or she
                        enters on duty. Ambassadors, however, are considered to have entered on duty
                        when they present their credentials to their host governments.





Department History


Short
                                History

Buildings of the
                                Department

People

Biographies
                                        of the Secretaries of State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of Mission



Travels

Travels of
                                        the Secretary

Travels of
                                        the President



Visits by Foreign Leaders

World War I and the Department

U.S. Diplomatic
                                Couriers














Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/19232.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/m/dghr/aao/index.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/by-name</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/by-year</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principalofficers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/chiefsofmission/by-country</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/chiefsofmission/by-organization</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/documents/organization/17843.pdf</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/bayard-thomas-francis</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/holbrooke-richard-charles-albert</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.senate.gov/CRSReports/crs-publish.cfm?pid=%270E%2C*P%5C%3F3%22P%20%20%0A</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</id></item>