<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative











China Conference - Conferences




Home

Conferences

Transforming the Cold War: The United States and China,
                    1969-1980






Transforming the Cold War: The United States and China,
                    1969-1980









"Transforming the Cold War: The United States and China, 1969-1980"
Co-sponsored by The U.S. Department of State and The Institute for European, Russian, and Eurasian Studies, at
                        the Elliott School of International Affairs, The George Washington
                        University 

Washington, DCSeptember 25-27, 2006


Program
Monday, September 25, 20062201 C St., N.W., Loy Henderson Conference Room, U.S. Department of
                    State1:00-1:40 Registration - Enter from 23rd Street1:40-1:45 Welcome
                    and Introductory Remarks: Dr. Marc J.
                    Susser, The Historian, U.S. Department of State 1:45-2:30 Scheduled
                    Keynote Speaker: Dr. Philip D. Zelikow, Counselor
                    of the U.S. Department of State 2:30-4:30 Scheduled
                        Panel of Former Diplomats and Government Officials: 
Ambassador Winston S. Lord (ret.), Member of
                            the National Security Council Staff, 1969-1973; Special Assistant to
                            Henry Kissinger, 1970-1973; Director of the Policy Planning Staff,
                            Department of State, 1973-1977
Professor W. Richard Smyser, Operations
                            Staff, National Security Council, 1970-1971 and 1973-1975; Deputy
                            Assistant Secretary and Assistant Secretary for Refugee Programs,
                            Department of State, 1980-1981
Lt. General Brent Scowcroft, U.S. Air
                            Force (ret.), Deputy National Security Advisor, 1973-1975; National
                            Security Advisor, 1975-1977
Dr. Zbigniew Brzezinski, National
                            Security Advisor, 1977-1981
Ambassador Charles W. (Chas.) Freeman,
                                Jr. (ret.), Office of Asian Communist Affairs, Bureau of East
                            Asian and Pacific Affairs, Department of State, 1971-1973; Director for
                            Chinese Affairs, Department of State, 1979-1981
Panelist Comments

Question and Answer


Tuesday, September 26, 20062201 C St., N.W., Loy Henderson Conference Room, U.S. Department of State
                    8:30-9:15 Registration and Continental Breakfast - Enter from 23rd
                    Street9:15-9:30 Welcome9:30-10:00 Scheduled Keynote speaker,
                    Christopher R. Hill, Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and Pacific
                    Affairs 10:00-10:15 Break10:15-12:00 Session 1: Roundtable - Foreign
                    Relations of the United States, 1969-1976, volume XVII, China, 1969-1972 and
                    Scholarly Interpretations of Establishing Relations With China, 1969-1980 
Professor Steven Phillips, Department of History, Towson University
                            (Chair)
Professor Chen Jian, Department of History, Cornell University
Professor Warren I. Cohen, Department of History, University of
                            Maryland, Baltimore County
James Mann, FPI Author-in-Residence, School for Advanced International
                            Studies, Johns Hopkins University

12:00-1:30 Lunch1:30-3:00 Session 2Chair: Dr. Chris Tudda, Office of
                    the Historian, U.S. Department of State 
"Musical Diplomacy in the Opening of China, 1971-1972"Professor
                            Adam Cathcart, Department of History, Hiram College
"Communication and Miscommunication in Sino-Soviet-American Relations,
                            1969"Professor Lorenz L&#252;thi, Department of History, McGill
                            University
"The Romanian Efforts to Facilitate a Sino-American Rapprochement,
                            1969-1971"Mircea Munteanu, Woodrow Wilson International Center for
                            Scholars/The George Washington University

Comments: Professor Gregg Brazinsky, Department of History, The George Washington
                    University3:00-3:15 Break3:15-5:00 Session 3Chair: Dr. Ding
                    Xinghao, President, Shanghai Association of American Studies and Shanghai
                    Institute of American Studies 
"Mobilizing for War: China's Limited Ability to Cope With the Soviet
                            Threat, 1969-1972"Professor David Bachman, School of International
                            Studies, University of Washington
"Between Historical Determinism and Anxiety: The Soviet Union and
                            Sino-American Rapprochement, 1969-1973"Dr. Bernd Schaefer, German
                            Historical Institute
"From Zhenbao Island to Beijing: The 1969 Sino-Soviet Border Conflict
                            and U.S.-China Relations"Professor Dong Wang, Department of History
                            and Political Science, York College of Pennsylvania
"The Sino-American Rapprochement and Chinese-Vietnamese Relations"
                            Professor Qiang Zhai, Department of History, Auburn University
                            Montgomery Comments: Professor Thomas Schwartz, Department of History,
                            Vanderbilt University

Wednesday, September 27, 20061957 E St., N.W., Lindner Family Commons, 6th Floor, Institute for
                    European, Russian, and Eurasian Studies, at the Elliott School of International
                    Affairs, The George Washington University (This portion of the conference is
                    funded by the Henry Luce Foundation)9:00-10:15 Session 1Chair:
                    Professor Hope M. Harrison, History Department and Director of the Institute for
                    European, Russian and Eurasian Studies, The George Washington University 
"U.S. Relations With the People's Republic of China, 1969-1974: The
                            Polish Perspective" Malgorzata Gnoinska, The George Washington
                            University
"Economic Problems in U.S.-China Rapprochement, 1972-1975"William
                            Burr, National Security Archive
"The Chinese Perspective on the U.S.-China
                            Rapprochement"Professor Chen Jian, Department of History, Cornell
                            University

Comments: Patrick Tyler, Woodrow Wilson Center10:15-10:30
                    Break10:30-11:45: Session 2Chair: Dr. Christian Ostermann, Woodrow
                    Wilson Center 
"Zbigniew Brzezinski and the Carter Approach to China: 'The United
                            States Has Made Up Its Mind.' "Professor Patrick Vaughan,
                            Jagiellonian University, Krakow, Poland
"The False Shuffle&#151;Cyrus Vance and the China Card"Breck Walker,
                            Department of History, Vanderbilt University

Comments: Professor David Shambaugh, Department of Political Science and
                    Director, China Program, The George Washington University12:00-1:00
                    Lunch1:00-2:15 Session 3Chair: Professor Gregg Brazinsky, Department
                    of History, The George Washington University 
" 'Maximum Flexibility for Peaceful Change': Jimmy Carter, Taiwan and
                            the Recognition of the People's Republic of China"Brian Hilton,
                            Department of History, Texas A&amp;M University
"The Carter Administration and China: The Culmination of
                            Self-Determination as a Human Right"Professor Itai Sneh, Department
                            of History, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, City University of New
                            York 

Comments: Dr. Richard C. Bush, Director, Center for Northeast Asian Policy
                    Studies, The Brookings Institution2:15-2:30 Break2:30-4:00 Session 4
                    Chair: Professor Edward McCord, Department of History, The George
                    Washington University 
"The Soviet Invasion of Afghanistan and its Effect on Carter's Policy
                            Toward China"Todd Rosa, Department of History, The George
                            Washington University
"'The Vietnamese Lesson': The Carter Administration and the Chinese
                            Attack on Vietnam"Professor Scott Kaufman, Francis Marion
                            University
"The Chinese 'Punitive Invasion' of Vietnam as the 'Baptism of Fire'
                            of a New Strategic Partnership With Washington and its Repercussions on
                            the end of the Cold War"Enrico Maria Fardella, Department of
                            Political Sciences, University of Florence

Comments: Professor James G. Hershberg, Department of History, The George
                    Washington University4:00-5:00 Session 5, Wrap-Up Session: New Evidence on
                    the International History of the Normalization of U.S.-China
                    RelationsProfessor William Kirby, Department of History, Harvard
                    UniversityProfessor Robert S. Ross, Fairbank Center for East Asian
                    Research, Harvard University and Department of Political Science, Boston
                    College


Opening Remarks
MARC SUSSER (Historian of the Department): Thank you. As
                    Amy said, I am the Historian of the Department. I'd like to welcome all of you
                    here to the Department to this conference on "Transforming the Cold War: The
                    United States and China, 1969-1980." This is the fourth annual historical
                    conference sponsored by the Department of State and we are pleased to be
                    co-hosting this with the Elliott School of George Washington University.
As with our previous conferences, this one is linked to the release of several
                    volumes in our official historical documentary series Foreign
                        Relations of the United States. As some of you may know, the Foreign
                    Relations series was started by President Abraham Lincoln and Secretary of State
                    William Seward back in 1861. In that era, when the United States was in the
                    midst of its greatest crisis, all the important documents fit into one volume.
                    Today, the series has grown to over 400 volumes with the Office of the Historian
                    now planning to publish 57 volumes covering just the Nixon and Ford
                    administrations alone. And we will do that at just over 30 years after the
                    events.
Several weeks ago, the Department published the first volume on the Nixon
                    Administration's policy toward China. Today, we are adding to that material with
                    a new publication, an electronic volume which is now available on the internet,
                        Documents on China 1969-72, which supplements the
                    documents that are found in the print volume. The combination of print and
                    internet publication allows us to deal with the ever greater number and variety
                    of documents that are now available to historians. This melding of the two
                    formats allows the Department to provide a comprehensive account of the
                    evolution of U.S. policy toward China during these crucial years.
The 1991 law that governs the Foreign Relations series requires that it be a
                    thorough, accurate and reliable account of U.S. foreign policy, and we believe
                    that is exactly what we provide in these two volumes. Although the broad
                    outlines of the Nixon-Kissinger policy and opening to China are well known, our
                    volumes include many new details not previously available to the public and many
                    not previously available even to scholars in the field. Our historians have had
                    full access to the files of all the agencies and departments involved in the
                    foreign policy process during the years of the administrations of President
                    Nixon and President Ford, and we have selected for publication the key documents
                    that best tell the story of the evolution and development of U.S. policy during
                    this period.
These volumes fulfill the requirements of the law that the published record shall
                    omit no facts that were of major importance in reaching a decision and that
                    nothing shall be omitted for the purpose of concealing a defect of policy. The
                    publication of the Foreign Relations series provides an unrivaled example of
                    transparency and of a government making its business open to public scrutiny.
                    For more than 140 years, the Foreign Relations series has provided a powerful
                    tool enabling the American public and indeed people all over the world to
                    understand our country's foreign policy process.
We do this because we and our Congress believe that in a democracy a government
                    has an obligation to tell its people the truth. We believe that it's important
                    that the American people know what their government has done in its dealings
                    with the rest of the world once sufficient time has passed and still-classified
                    material has been protected. We believe that the best way to maintain the
                    delicate balance of secrecy and trust between citizens and their government is
                    to ensure that the actions of the government are not hidden forever. And that is
                    why the Department of State publishes the Foreign Relations series.
The complete text of this new electronic volume is now available on the internet.
                    The print volume that was released a couple of weeks ago will soon be available
                    for sale from the Government Printing Office and I believe we have CDs of that
                    volume included in your folders today.
We made extensive efforts to ensure broad participation in this conference and we
                    are pleased that we have several scholars with us here today from China. The
                    opening to China and the later normalization of relations dramatically altered
                    the international landscape of the Cold War and set the framework for U.S.-China
                    relations until today. We have with us today some of the key policymakers from
                    the Nixon, Ford and Carter administrations who will share their recollections of
                    these key years.
Also with us today to formally open the conference and to put this period in
                    U.S.-China relations in historical perspective is one of the Department's most
                    senior officials, the Counselor of the Department, Dr. Philip Zelikow.
Dr. Zelikow was appointed Counselor of the Department in February of 2005 and he
                    advises the Secretary of State on a wide range of issues. Before his
                    appointment, he was the staff director of the 9/11 Commission, a trial and
                    appellate attorney, a former career Foreign Service officer, a member of the
                    National Security Council staff and the Director of the Miller Center for Public
                    Affairs at the University of Virginia. He is also a former member of the
                    President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board, and from our perspective here
                    in the Office of the Historian, even more important, a former member of the
                    Department's Historical Advisory Committee.
Dr. Zelikow.


Keynote Speaker: Dr. Philip D. Zelikow, Counselor of the U.S. Department of
                    State
PHILIP ZELIKOW (Counselor of the Department): Ladies and
                    gentlemen, it's an honor to be here today to address this conference. I'd like
                    to begin by acknowledging the Office of the Historian, by acknowledging their
                    patient and determined scholarship from year to year, decade to decade,
                    preserving and publishing the record of American foreign relations.
You'll note that this volume is not just about the record of the Department of
                    State. Increasingly, the Historian's Office has assumed the responsibility of
                    providing a foreign policy record that extends beyond the State Department to
                    include the records of the White House, our intelligence agencies. It really is
                    one of the treasures of our nation's government that just happens to be lodged
                    in the Department of State.
I also want to note in commenting on the role of the Historian's Office and on
                    the role of a conference like this that this is not about official history. A
                    lot of the historians who are at this conference don't like this administration.
                    Why, some of the premier historians of Sino-American relations, like Warren
                    Cohen or Michael Hunt don't like this administration. And that's okay. Their
                    scholarship has earned them the kind of honor and attention that it continues to
                    receive today and it is perfectly normal and natural that scholars should
                    criticize the administration, have different views and provide a wealth of
                    perspectives.
Indeed, when I served on the Historical Advisory Committee I was appointed to
                    that role by a Democratic Secretary of State and members of that committee were
                    involved in constant strife with whichever administration was prevailing at the
                    time, usually pushing harder and harder for more declassification, placing more
                    material in the public records, to always be sure that those values were given
                    attention to.
In other words, the Historian's Office in a conference like this is not about
                    official history. It is instead about an official duty to history that is being
                    discharged. I hope this conference can serve as an example to other historian's
                    offices and other governments elsewhere in the world, including our friends in
                    China and even our friends in Japan on various ways that one can approach
                    sensitive problems in contemporary history.
I want to acknowledge too the quality of scholarship and expertise available to
                    students of U.S.-China relations in particular, the outstanding quality of the
                    primary sources, a tradition of careful documentation that I think is influenced
                    by Chinese culture and traditions in this particular field.
There is something disciplining about the fact that when you believe people
                    really will scrutinize what you say word for word, you're more careful in how
                    you write it down. There's also a rich tradition of interchange of scholarship
                    between public and private work. Stanley Hornbeck, journeying from Harvard with
                    the gentle permission of President Lowell back to join the State Department and
                    serve in public service. Or people like the late Jim Thompson or Ezra Vogel or
                    Ken Lieberthal or many, many others, including the newly appointed Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary of State Tom Christensen, coming to us from Princeton
                    University.
Finally, as I turn to this subject, I want to note that it's really appropriate
                    we're holding this conference on this date to me because it's almost exactly one
                    year since Bob Zoellick spoke last September, September of 2005, about America's
                    relations with China today and the way those relations have really entered a new
                    phase, a phase made possible by the developments and policymakers whose work we
                    are studying today and in the succeeding days.
Of course, American historical memory in these matters can be questioned. I was
                    looking at some different works on this and I stumbled across a wonderful quote
                    after then Defense Secretary Harold Brown visited China in the beginning of
                    January 1980. A Chinese intellectual told the delegation of American China
                    specialists that the potential in Sino-American relations should not be
                    overestimated. The quote from the New York Times article is that, "You Americans
                    are so charming," a Chinese scholar said, "for you have such short memories. We
                    can't forget so fast or so easily what happened between us in the past." Well,
                    this conference is trying to at least contribute to the slight lengthening of
                    our traditionally short national memory.
Let me offer some questions and policy reflections: first, on why normalization
                    occurred when it did; second, what did the United States want from
                    normalization; third, on what I think is a striking continuity in American hopes
                    for China; and fourth, some of the lingering consequences of this history
                    today.
First then, why did normalization occur when it did? It's an interesting question
                    because, of course, the State Department had long wanted to normalize U.S.-China
                    relations and had equally long been ambivalent about what would happen if we
                    did. So there was a constancy of State Department desire to normalize and a
                    constancy too of State Department ambivalence towards the actual prospect
                    because of reactions from Japan, from Southeast Asia, from the Soviet Union and
                    so forth, that naturally were caveats that would have to be taken into account
                    before you actually made such a move.
So then when one looks at the American variables, in addition to that constancy,
                    I think it is interesting to look at the role that Richard Nixon himself played.
                    Nixon's role is interesting in this matter because Nixon was more interested in
                    Asia than many American national leaders were even of his time. It's important
                    to remember that Nixon, for example, in contrast to the life story of Henry
                    Kissinger before 1969, that Nixon was a man of the west and a man of the Pacific
                    Rim in some distinctive ways. Nixon grew up in California. His World War II
                    service was in the Pacific, not in the European theater. The Republican Party in
                    which he had spent his formative years, the Republican Party of the late 1940s
                    and early 1950s was actually a Republican Party that was extremely interested in
                    Asia. One of the characteristic stereotypes of, say, Bob Taft, a leader of the
                    Republican Party on that issue, is to think of these people as isolationist
                    because of their opposition to NATO. In fact, it's important to remember that
                    Taft Republicans may have been isolationist with regards to American engagement
                    in Europe, but they were anything but isolationist when it came to American
                    engagement in the future of East Asia, where their policy prescriptions were
                    very activist and Nixon very much internalized that. Indeed, one of his
                    signature issues when he became Vice President to Dwight Eisenhower was Asia,
                    was an intense interest in the fate of Indochina, for example, in 1953 and 1954,
                    and in the Taiwan Straits crises later in the Eisenhower Administration.
So Nixon comes into office as President as a person conditioned to a constancy of
                    interest in Asia and with a lot of knowledge and interest in America's
                    traditions there. So in his very first foreign trips, when literally he's been
                    in office only weeks, he's already talking about the idea of opening to China.
                    In his meetings with President DeGaulle, for example, he noted -- and this is in
                    the Foreign Relations documents -- that there existed "considerable sentiment in
                    the State Department not only in favor of a Soviet-U.S. d&#233;tente but also for a
                    lineup of the Soviets, Europe and the U.S. against the Chinese." By the way, in
                    this instance I believe that this is a false allegation against the State
                    Department, setting up a straw man to which Nixon could then comment. Because
                    Nixon's comment was such a d&#233;tente against the Chinese might be a good
                    short-range policy, but in the longer term it was in the U.S. interest to
                    recognize that China and the Soviet Union were "great powers" and that we should
                    "build parallel relationships with them." Nixon then conceding that this was
                    "largely theoretical as it was difficult to have relations with the Chinese,"
                    which begins to suggest that the critical variable in the opening was less in
                    Washington and more perhaps in Beijing.
It's not, of course, the place of an American government official to speculate in
                    depth from this podium about the motives and attitudes of Chinese leadership,
                    but it is important to recognize, as many historians have, that this was a
                    period in the late 1960s and especially the beginning of the 1970s when Chinese
                    revolutionary activism and domestic turmoil was appearing to subside, that
                    China's role in the Vietnam War was changing as the Soviet role in supporting
                    the North Vietnamese became primary and the Chinese role becoming secondary, but
                    also a period in which China must have felt an increasing sense of isolation
                    from the communist world and in the world more generally. Relatively few fast
                    friends for China back then, among them countries like Pakistan and Romania,
                    which then both provided back channels to try to facilitate a normalization of
                    relations with the United States. And then there was the Soviet factor, the
                    invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, border clashes, a lot of ominous talk in
                    public and in private.
So why normalization occurred when it did -- yes, there's an American factor,
                    Nixon being important, but also very important to look at the Chinese variable
                    as perhaps even being the critical variable. But as that variable changed, the
                    opportunities for normalization opened and we turn to my second subject, what
                    did the United States seek from normalization, or to put it even more plainly,
                    what did we want from them?
The answer to this question is interesting and I think thought-provoking. Let's
                    start with what Kissinger wanted. There is a lot of evidence and fragments of
                    evidence about Kissinger's views on this subject. I think it's fair to say that
                    for Kissinger the opening to China was very much part of the foreign policy
                    perspective he had focused on the Soviet Union and the broader geopolitical
                    balance of power.
For instance, in October 1971, Kissinger, returning from having met with Zhou
                    Enlai -- again, out of FRUS volume -- Kissinger telling Nixon, "The China trip's
                    the keystone of your foreign policy, Mr. President. You get a good reception in
                    China, which I know you will, you come out with a decent communiqu&#233;, you're in
                    business with the Russians. Then the Russian trip will be a great success,"
                    which they were already thinking about for the spring of 1972.
Or for instance, in an exceptionally revealing meeting that lasted for hours
                    between Nixon and Kissinger on the eve of their departure for China, a meeting
                    that fortunately was caught on tape and painstakingly transcribed by the State
                    editors of the FRUS volume, Kissinger remarks that for the next 15 years, we
                    have to lean towards the Chinese against the Russians; we have to play this
                    balance of power game totally unemotionally; right now, we need the Chinese to
                    correct the Russians and to discipline the Russians.
And then going on, in the very same conversation, Nixon makes some remarks about
                    the Chinese reception for a visiting African leader. Kissinger comes back to his
                    main subject: "Our concern with China right now in my view, Mr. President, is to
                    use it as a counterweight to Russia, not for its local policy." President Nixon
                    says he agrees. Kissinger adds, "As a counterweight to keep it in play in the
                    subcontinent for the time being, but above all, as a counterweight to Russia and
                    the fact that it doesn't -- that China doesn't have a global policy is an asset
                    to us, that it doesn't have global strength yet, and to prevent Russia from
                    gobbling it up. If Russia dominates China, that would be a fact of such
                    tremendous significance."
That gives you a little bit of a sense, some fragments of Kissinger's
                    perspective, of his orientation, but not to what people then wrote about Nixon's
                    orientation, which was different and in some ways more fundamental, more
                    inchoate. For instance, Marshall Green recalling ways that Nixon had expressed
                    himself to him on this subject, especially in 1969 when Green spent a lot of
                    time with Nixon, recalled that "Nixon said to me," Green, "We simply cannot go
                    on indefinitely in a hostile relationship with one-quarter of mankind,
                    especially as the PRC grows in military power."
Or try the recollection of John Holdridge, who was working at State, then went to
                    work with the NSC staff along with Win Lord and others who are here. Holdridge
                    recalled Nixon rationale, which he says he often heard Nixon express, was "It's
                    far better to talk to the Chinese than to fight them," given China's huge
                    population, key geographic location, and important influence. And this is
                    interesting because then, when you look at what did America want from China from
                    the normalization process instrumentally, if the question is, what did we want
                    from them, the answer is not very much. A lot of the agenda was a defensive
                    agenda, how to avoid giving away too much on Taiwan.
It was not an agenda -- unlike the agenda with the Soviet Union, where we really
                    expected dramatic results on, say, Vietnam; why, after the February 1972 summit,
                    shortly thereafter, the Vietnamese launched the Easter Offensive that began on
                    March 30th, 1972 and neither Nixon nor Kissinger appeared to feel betrayed by
                    that. They didn't think they had a deal with the Chinese. Indeed, if anything,
                    the Chinese were kind of urging the Americans to be tougher on the North
                    Vietnamese because of their growing estrangement from the North Vietnamese that
                    was already evident.
But you go through issue after issue, it's hard to find anything that's concrete
                    and instrumental that the Americans are really seeking from the open. There is
                    the balance of power argument put showing that America and China could work
                    together and the chilling effect that would have on the Russians that Kissinger
                    emphasizes. But then it's hard to resist the sense that there is just this more
                    fundamental, inchoate concern which Nixon articulates that's less instrumental
                    and more about, such an opening is an end in itself.
In other words, that to Nixon, he would be earning his place in history simply by
                    ending what Warren Cohen has called "the great aberration," the period of
                    rupture in US-China relations that had lasted for about 20 years. That point is
                    important because it brings us to the third one. If you think about "the great
                    aberration," you think that, for Nixon, in a way, he was returning to a sense of
                    good relations with China that, for him, was part of the natural, normal
                    American context. He was returning to normalization, not creating it new. Then
                    you really capture the sense of the continuity of American hopes for China,
                    which I think is worth dwelling on in some detail.
It is asserted by some Chinese nationalists, not necessarily by the Chinese
                    Government, that the recent tradition of American relations with China is a
                    desire to keep China down, to limit China's power, to limit China's influence.
                    In contrast, I think it's fairer to assert that as long as it has been involved
                    in Asia's politics, for more than 100 years, America's leaders have sought a
                    strong, united, and independent China.
Year in and year out, from one generation to the next, America pursued this goal
                    with a constancy of purpose unique among all the major powers in the region. Of
                    course, America did so to serve America's interests. But America conceived of
                    its interests in a rare harmony with the long-term interests of the Chinese
                    people. And America thus played, again and again, an indispensable historical
                    role in the evolution of a strong and independent China.
Let me offer just a few illustrations. In 1899, immediately after America
                    realized that it is an Asiatic power, Hay and William Rockhill authored the Open
                    Door. The Open Door Note, as I'm sure many of you here know, is commonly
                    remembered for the goal of being sure that the door was not closed to American
                    commerce, as some of the imperial powers were moving to carving up China in the
                    waning years of the Manchu Dynasty.
But it's also worth remembering when one reads the Open Door Note that it had two
                    goals, not only the goal of not excluding the United States and keeping the door
                    open in that sense, but also asserting that China should be allowed to continue
                    to have control of its finances, the issue of control of China's customs
                    revenue. Because if China lost complete control of its finances, its effective
                    independence would come to an end, and the United States had already decided
                    that it was very much in America's interests for China to preserve its
                    independence.
That kind of persistent view of the need for a stable, stronger and more
                    independent China is carried forward in the administration of Theodore
                    Roosevelt, carried forward in the way America distinctively approached the
                    settlement of the Boxer rebellion claims, Roosevelt's own article on the
                    awakening of China. It continues on through the Taft Administration and then on
                    into the Wilson Administration. Remember that after the Chinese Revolution of
                    1912, the Wilson Administration rushed to recognize the new Republic of China
                    and did so unilaterally before the other great powers were willing to go along.
                    Wilson once expressing, as Josephus Daniels noted in his minutes of a cabinet
                    meeting -- Wilson saying his desire to help China was so strong, "that I prefer
                    to err in the line of helping that country than otherwise."
All this coupled with a growing concern about Japan, all of it limited by a keen
                    sense of how little American power there was to project in East Asia and how
                    little one could do to safeguard China or promote China. But America would do
                    what it could.
In 1922, when in the Harding Administration, Charles Evans Hughes, the Secretary
                    of State and Elihu Root decided to create a Washington system for East Asia
                    organized around the Washington conferences. By the way, again, the stereotype
                    of American isolation after the failure of the League of Nations, not at all
                    true when it comes to American policy in Asia. That Washington system they
                    crafted had at its core a Nine Power Treaty designed to secure Chinese
                    independence in a period of disorder, guaranteeing its independence,
                    guaranteeing its territorial integrity, with America as the lead sponsor of
                    those provisions to ensure the Nine Powers respected them.
Not enough for the Chinese nationalists, not enough for them that America
                    couldn't overthrow the regime of unequal treaties that the other powers insisted
                    on; yet even on that score, by 1926, again ahead of the other powers, the United
                    States was ready to discard extraterritoriality and wanted to grant China tariff
                    autonomy. By the way, over active protests from within the Department of State
                    and protests from both London and Tokyo because of American dedication, here now
                    the role of Secretary Kellogg and Nelson Johnson, to this need to preserve a
                    strong and independent China once China could sort out its internal disorder and
                    its internal weaknesses.
Then American interests, while they remained the same, were not so actively
                    pursued until finally, as Japanese aggression on the Chinese mainland grew in
                    the period from 1938 to 1941, the United States of America took supreme risks to
                    protect the strength and independence of China. Finally, at the end of 1938, as
                    the activist Secretary of the Treasury Henry Morgenthau found at last an ally in
                    the Department of State, hitherto preferring to do nothing about these problems
                    except to refuse to recognize either side's claims and not intervene.
Morgenthau over again, asking for another embargo on some Japanese trade. Hull,
                    of course, as usual, disagreeing with Morgenthau. Hull then sending for Stanley
                    Hornbeck. And then Hornbeck arrives and Morgenthau noted in his diaries, "I
                    almost fell out of my chair when Hornbeck agreed that this ought to be done."
                    Hornbeck said, "As a matter of fact, we're working on several other ways to put
                    the screws in the Japanese, and this is just what we ought to do," ushering a
                    period of financial and economic aid to China, then fighting for its life, and
                    financial and economic sanctions against Japan of growing strength and gravity
                    until by 1940 and '41, the risks that were being undertaken by these sanctions
                    flew in the face of America's grand strategy which was, after all, Germany
                    first.
So with a Germany first strategy, you do not want to provoke a war in the Pacific
                    before you come to grips with the main problem in Europe. Yet that is exactly
                    the kind of risk that was being courted by the policy and in fact, the risk that
                    materialized finally in the attack on Pearl Harbor in December 1941. And you are
                    then left with this extraordinary dichotomy of risk and principle that's worth
                    noting because some of the ideas involved have resonance to the present day.
Stanley Hornbeck, reaching the end of his life in the early 1960s, asked about
                    what America should do to meet its present challenges, said -- and here, I'm
                    indebted to the late Jim Thompson for noting this -- "Well, I am sure about some
                    things," Hornbeck said, "our national concern for and regarding principles and
                    practices of freedom, independence, justice and security is greater than is that
                    of any other nation. We should be prepared to go further and to make greater
                    efforts in defense of those principles and practices than is to be expected of
                    any other country."
At the same time, drawing to a close, Hornbeck files a little note in a box
                    marked "Pearl Harbor," in a way leaving a record for posterity, "Did I,"
                    Hornbeck, "underestimate Japan's strength? The answer is: Yes, both in absolute
                    terms and in comparative terms. And so did practically everyone else in the
                    United States, both in the government and out of the government in varying
                    degrees." The results were that America then found itself in a war, a war it had
                    been drawn into in conflict with its grand strategy, in great part because of
                    its stubborn dedication to trying to preserve a united and independent
                    China.
Another key moment arises as the war goes on; who will make up the permanent
                    membership of the United Nations Security Council that will have such an
                    extraordinary role in the postwar order? There was only one voice in the
                    councils of the great powers that said such a seat must be held for China. And
                    that voice was, again, that of the United States. Franklin Roosevelt, for
                    example, insisting on it with Anthony Eden in March of 1943 so that in 1945,
                    that seat is there, the seat which the Peoples' Republic of China now holds, a
                    seat which it could take in 1971 because that seat had been built for it in
                    1945. Had that seat not been there, China might today be, along with other
                    countries, joining the ranks of those asking for the reorganization of the UN
                    Security Council to recognize China's role. But instead, the United States had
                    worked to preserve that role as early as 1943, successfully.
And in 1946, another extraordinary choice that America had to make; as the war
                    came to an end and American policy was fluid on its attitude toward the Chinese
                    communists, the great choice facing the United States Government was: Do you
                    side completely with Jiang and the Guomindang against the communists? And
                    instead, a series of American leaders, especially Byrnes, Acheson, Marshall and
                    John Carter Vincent decided instead to choose mediation and restraint in China's
                    civil war.
There was an extraordinary opportunity for the anti-communists. After all, Stalin
                    had already made his deal with Jiang Jieshi in 1945 as to how he would come to a
                        modus vivendi with Guomindang rule in the new China,
                    and Mao knew it. There were a lot of Americans, Patrick Hurley among them and
                    others, who would have argued that the United States should come down 100
                    percent on the side of the Guomindang, and that the United States chose not to
                    do. Or indeed, in 1947, as the civil war deepened into complete strife with the
                    result that here, where the future of East Asia was arguably at stake, perhaps
                    the most important contest in the emerging Cold War, where a quarter of the
                    world's population was on the table, the United States fundamentally chose not
                    to intervene with its full military might at the time when victory for the
                    Guomindang could have been assured.
We can argue about whether those decisions were right, but the reason for their
                    choice of mediation and restraint was because of their hopes for a strong,
                    united and independent China and that somehow, this was the only way to achieve
                    that unity. We can fault the way they went about it, we can decry the naivet&#233;,
                    but the purpose is important to understand. And even that lingering purpose
                    going on in the Korean War, when in 1950 and 1951, Mao essentially invited
                    America to join World War III, an invitation that, despite the recommendations
                    of some, such as his commander in the Far East, President Truman chose to
                    decline.
In the Taiwan Straits crises, despite Chinese intervention into the Vietnam War
                    in the early and mid-1960s and its threats to the United States that if they
                    sought to solve the Vietnam War by dealing with North Vietnam, they would face
                    war with China, and the American decision therefore to accept the limited war
                    that China insisted on as the choice between that and war with China; again and
                    again, the United States chooses the path of its consistent interests and regard
                    for China, which then brings us back to the issues of the 1970s.
So for America in the 1970s, there was a constancy of interest that now seemed
                    enabled and possible in new ways. And the question is whether that constancy is
                    now coming to fruition. Therefore, I want to turn fourth to the consequences of
                    that normalization and that constancy today.
Looking back at 1969 again, one of the many studies that the White House
                    commissioned was National Security Study Memorandum 14, commissioned in the
                    spring and summer of 1969 to look at U.S. policies towards China. Kissinger
                    famously remarked that these studies were make-work projects to keep the State
                    Department busy. I think this is Kissinger in his more puckish moment. In fact,
                    at the time, I think this particular study was taken quite seriously. A lot of
                    people worked on it, especially at the State Department, and there was a
                    prescient question asked in the State Department's paper answering that
                    study.
In August 1969, the State Department paper responding to NSM 14 posed the
                    following question, which I think was probably written by Marshall Green, John
                    Holdridge and their colleagues, Holdridge at State before he then went over and
                    received the paper on the NSC staff.
"A question can legitimately be posed as to whether or not it is in U.S.
                    interests for Peking to become more engaged in the international scene. If
                    Peking should choose to pursue a more pragmatic and moderate foreign policy,
                    pressures by the nations of Asia for accommodating Peking and for accepting the
                    PRC into international organizations would build rapidly. Peking's emergence
                    from its self-imposed isolation would thus pose new challenges for U.S. policy
                    in Asia and would probably result in certain short-term losses to ourselves and
                    our allies."
And to that prescient question, it is interesting to note a prescient answer. The
                    answer then offered in August '69 was that over the long-term, however,
                    "evolution of Peking's policies toward moderation would offer the prospect of
                    increased stability in East Asia. Since it does not lie within the United
                    States' power to prevent Peking from breaking out of its isolation, the issue
                    posed for the U.S. is whether this evolution will take place in spite of U.S.
                    resistance or whether the U.S. will be seen as willing to accept and live with
                    Peking's entry into the international community and do what it can to take
                    advantage of the change."
Those words do indeed ring true today, as do further cautions in that same
                    memorandum, cautions about limited U.S. power. To what extent, one can ask, can
                    America actually influence the way China approaches the international system if
                    it has these new opportunities? Here again, the study's authors in the summer of
                    '69 wrote, "Future Chinese leaders' perspectives may be altered, however, by
                    considerations of domestic political control, by the need for economic
                    development, and by China's relations with third countries. U.S. actions to
                    alter what Peking perceives as the U.S. 'threat' could contribute to this. This
                    need not be hostile to U.S. interests in the long-run if it allows for
                    continuing U.S. political and economic relations with these countries throughout
                    Asia, even though at a reduced level of intimacy than previously," because we
                    would sacrifice some quality of intimacy because of the growing role of China
                    and their decreasing reliance on us as protection against Chinese influence.
In other words, America made that choice that was forecasted for it in the summer
                    of 1969. It made the choice to embrace the growth of Chinese power. So for
                    example, when Zoellick gave his speech a year ago, he said that "For the United
                    States and the world, the essential question is, how will China use its
                    influence? To answer that question, it is time to take our policy beyond opening
                    doors to China's membership into the international system. We need to urge China
                    to become a responsible stakeholder in that system."
It is essential, then, to understand the historical record and see the continuity
                    across more than a century of the American belief that a strong, independent and
                    united China could contribute to the stability of East Asia and that that role
                    should be welcomed. The address that we gave a year ago on behalf of the
                    Administration made it clear that the argument about whether the United States
                    wanted to contain Chinese power or encourage Chinese power had been settled. The
                    paradigm that we put forward cannot be reconciled with a paradigm of
                    containment. It is a paradigm that welcomes the growth of Chinese power and
                    urges the Chinese to take on their role in strengthening the international
                    system that has enabled its success.
Now the choice is that of China. China has choices it will make about how it
                    approaches its own historical record and its own view of its past, but China
                    also has important choices to make about the future. And when I was trying to
                    think about words with which to talk to the Chinese Government or its people
                    about its choices, about its future, I was very drawn to some lines that Dean
                    Acheson used more than half a century ago in a very different context.
And so paraphrasing Acheson, I will just close by saying: And by no means least
                    of all, it rests with our friends to see that this relationship reaps its true
                    fruits. And I say to them: A great broad highway to a position of equality, of
                    honor, of friendship in the world lies open to you. All the obstacles on that
                    highway have been cleared away so far as governments can clear them away. The
                    obstacles that remain, only you can remove, and you can remove those if you act
                    with other peoples, with understanding, and with generosity and with kindness.
                    All those qualities are inherent in the nature of your people and what we urge
                    you to do is to make those qualities, which are so inherent in your people, the
                    policy of your government.
Thank you.
(Applause.)
SUSSER: Thank you, Counselor Zelikow. We'll now take a
                    moment for our first panel to assemble up here. (Pause.)


Panel of Former Diplomats and Government Officials


Contents





Introductions

Ambassador Winston Lord

Professor Richard Smyser

Lt. General Brent Scowcroft

Dr. Zbigniew Brezinski

Ambassador Charles Freeman

Panelist Comments

Question and Answer









Keynote Speaker: Christopher R. Hill, Assistant Secretary of State for East
                    Asian and Pacific Affairs
ASSISTANT SECRETARY HILL: Thank you very much. It's a
                    real pleasure to be here. I must say it's a little intimidating to be here, too,
                    because as my bio suggested I'm not a China scholar although I did serve in
                    Albania which has a sort of curious Chinese connection. I'll always remember in
                    Albania we were giving them some cotton and weren't sure whether it would work
                    in their textile mill. And I said, well, where did the textile mill come from?
                    They said oh, it came from China. So we had a couple of experts go and check it
                    out. And it said something like Moscow, in Cyrillic, on it, 1890. And what we
                    realized was it was a gift of the Soviet people to the Chinese people who
                    promptly or maybe not so promptly turned it around and made it a gift to the
                    Albanian people. So I have a little familiarity from China in those days.
But I must say taking up my current position, as you see from my bio, I moved
                    from being Ambassador to Korea to being Assistant Secretary to North Korea. We
                    occasionally have some dealings with China. Every day I walk into my office and
                    I walk past the picture of John Carter Vincent, who at some point I guess took
                    up cigarette smoking because he's there with a cigarette in his mouth. I've been
                    tempted to pick up cigarette smoking as well in this position. I also walk past
                    the photo of W.W. Butterworth. And these are two figures who had my position and
                    who have had to live through I think a very, very tough time in policy terms, a
                    lot of recrimination, just took a lot of courage. And so I frankly find those
                    people quite an inspiration.
It has been more than three decades since President Nixon and Secretary of State
                    and National Security Advisor Kissinger made their historic breakthrough with
                    China. It's, I think, always memorable at the Beijing banquet that honored him
                    in 1972 President Nixon responding to Chou En-lai's toast spoke frankly, he said
                    "Let us recognize at the outset these points. We have at time in the past been
                    enemies. We have great differences today. What brings us together is that we
                    have common interests which transcend those differences. Neither of us will
                    compromise our principles. But while we cannot close the gulf between us, we can
                    try to bridge it so that we may be able to talk across it." And indeed, I think
                    those remarks uttered some 30 years ago at a toast are very much applicable
                    today, very prescient remarks.
I think at a critical juncture when China's own leadership was reassessing its
                    priorities, emerging from the isolation of the Cultural Revolution to engage on
                    an uncertain course of opening to the west, U.S. policymakers decided that our
                    approach to China had to be different from the way we dealt with the Soviet
                    Union. That approach would take deeper roots once China launched its impressive
                    domestic reform program in 1978 and the U.S. and the PRC established diplomatic
                    relations.
Indeed I would say the policies pursued by both administrations, by
                    administrations of both parties, by now some seven Presidents, has been to
                    encourage China's economic reforms, to expand the trade and our contacts with
                    China, and to especially use our influence to integrate and bind China into a
                    rules based international system.
And I would say that policy, that policy that has been for seven Presidents has
                    been extremely successful. China is an active player in the United Nations, a
                    Perm 5 member, a member which we are in constant communication, constant
                    negotiations across international issues across the globe. China's part of the
                    WTO, virtually every other economic organization participates in international
                    endeavors ranging from efforts to stop the spread of infectious diseases to
                    initiatives on the development of clean energy, which is one such effort we have
                    going in China just this month. And increasingly stepping up to take an active
                    role in dealing with regional security issues and a prime example being China's
                    efforts at hosting the six-party talks and dealing with North Korea's very
                    dangerous nuclear ambition, something I'll get to a little later.
And certainly, I think this is very good for China and I think it really reflects
                    to some extent to China's economic rise. It's GDP has grown some ten-fold since
                    1978, per capita income has doubled every eight and a half years. By comparison
                    it took Great Britain 58 years to double its per capita income in the early 19th
                    Century. It took the U.S. 47 years. It took Japan 34 years after
                    industrialization.
China recently surpassed Italy and the United Kingdom to become the world's
                    fourth largest economy. It trails only the U.S., Japan and Germany. But -- and
                    I'll go back to the famous -- I call it a quote, but I hate to do that in front
                    of historians because it's probably more apocryphal than anything else. But when
                    President Nixon congratulated Mao Tse-tung on the enormous changes in China, Mao
                    is reported to have said, "In fact, Mr. President, I've only been able to change
                    a few places around Beijing."
And indeed, I think when people do go outside of Shanghai and outside of Beijing,
                    you still see that China remains in many respects a very poor country, a per
                    capita income that ranks 133 in the world at $1200. Over 160 million people have
                    moved fitfully from China's rural areas to cities looking for employment, really
                    the largest internal migration in world history. And this floating population
                    now accounts for almost 20 percent of Beijing's residents, almost 20 percent of
                    Shanghai's residents. Indeed it's because of this migration in less than a
                    decade Shanghai's population has increased by a number equal to the population
                    of China.
And of course, as we are very aware, and I would say the Chinese Government is
                    more aware than anybody, average urban incomes are some four times what they are
                    in the rural areas. So by no means is China, as way say, out of the woods in
                    terms of what it has to do economically, but I think it is also fair to say that
                    one should look at some of the enormous progress in that rural area. In fact,
                    despite the disparities, the number of China's rural poor has been cut in half
                    during the 1990s, according to the World Bank, and that a population larger than
                    the entire population of the United States has been pulled out of abject
                    poverty. And I would say that this development in China has been very good for
                    the United States. China is now our fourth largest export market. It -- the
                    trade deficit is a huge issue to be sure, but also I think U.S. exports to
                    China, it's worth pointing out they've doubled since China joined the WTO in
                    2001 and that pace continues this year.
I had the pleasure of accompanying or meeting President Hu Jintao in Seattle.
                    What the Governor of Washington said, this is the real Washington, and you will
                    soon go to the other Washington. And I think she had a very good point, because
                    it was truly stunning to see the volume and depth of our relationship with
                    China.
China is going to be in the market in the next 20 years for some 2800 jets. And
                    when Hu Jintao came to the Boeing factory and was greeted by workers there in
                    overalls and just cheering him like he was their best customer. And there's a
                    reason why they treated him like he was their best customer, he -- it was a real
                    sense among the workers of how important he was. And what I really liked about
                    the meeting -- and I've never had a chance to ask him this but I'd love to ask
                    him, when he looked out on those sea of faces, many people wearing work overalls
                    and baseball hats, I think he realized something very important which is
                    Americans also need jobs now and again. America also needs to export goods now
                    and again. And so I think when he went there he saw really I think a very good
                    face of what our country is about, and it's not just about people in suits and
                    the other Washington, that is in Washington, D.C., but people who are really
                    trying to make a living as workers. And I thought it was a very important visit
                    in that regard.
He also went to the Microsoft campus, as the factory there is called, and saw I
                    think what was important in a number of respects, first of all, the cutting edge
                    technology that goes on in Microsoft. But secondly, when you look at the number
                    of Chinese engineers or people of Chinese extraction, Chinese-Americans, I think
                    he saw not only the connection of our economies but very much the connection of
                    our people.
In short, I think that trip to Seattle which lasted some 24 hours which -- and
                    where he met a lot of people including a lot of Falun Gong protestors I might
                    add, I think he saw and I think we saw in him the fact that our countries are
                    very much linked, very much linked if not entirely by a common past then
                    certainly by a common future.
And as one goes around in Washington, D.C. today, you will hear the occasional
                    person talk about China as the new Soviet Union, but that is extremely rare,
                    extremely rare indeed. I think you see very clearly from Americans of all
                    political persuasions that this is our key relationship. This is the
                    relationship that we have to, above all other relationships in the world,
                    nurture and make it work. We need to make it work in a way that's true to our
                    value, true to our interest but also make it work in a way that makes sure that
                    U.S. and China can work together because the stakes are simply enormous. They're
                    not only stakes in East Asia, they're all over the world and we have to work --
                    we have to find ways to work with China.
I think our engagement with China, which now takes place across many fora both
                    bilaterally and multilaterally, speaks to the importance that we attach to this
                    fundamental relationship. Bilaterally we have -- in the State Department we've
                    had a senior dialog that was first started by then Deputy Secretary Bob Zoellick
                    last year. And in fact, we planned -- of course we'll have a new Deputy
                    Secretary who will continue that dialog, but we didn't want to have too many
                    months go by. And so when I was in China just a couple of weeks ago, I
                    approached the senior foreign policy leadership to see if we could get the
                    dialog going as early as this month and have our Under Secretary for Political
                    Affairs handle it, and the Chinese were very, very happy to pursue that dialog.
                    And I think it was really a reflection of the fact that they appreciate the fact
                    that we sit down systematically go through our political relations and not just
                    issues that are urgent, which is often when you have diplomacy, but also issues
                    that are important. That is, these are dialogs where we try to have the
                    important crowd out the urgent now and again.
So we're looking forward to having the senior dialog continued in the next month
                    by Under Secretary Burns. Of course, you are all aware of Secretary Paulson's
                    strategic economic dialog. This is a dialog where in addition to the specific
                    dialogs where we get down to, you know, discussing imports of chicken parts,
                    this is a dialog that's not going to be discussing imports of chicken parts,
                    it's going to be a dialog that will be on top of the entire economic dialog if
                    you will flying at 20,000 feet to try to oversee some of these economic dialogs
                    and make sure that we can make this really, really work.
In addition to this strategic economic dialogue, we have a number of other
                    economic dialogs. The JCCT, the State Department NDRC dialogue. Our Under
                    Secretary for Global Affairs, Paula Dobriansky, is also pursuing a global issues
                    forum. We have a Department of Energy energy dialog as well. And these are just
                    a few of the examples of how we interact with China today. We have very
                    successful engagement on law enforcement cooperation. We have constant exchanges
                    of teams to discuss areas such as human trafficking, cyber crime, combating
                    corruption. The other day Elaine Chao from the Labor Department had her
                    counterpart over from China and they discussed issues like labor code and
                    especially pensions, an issue that if you've been reading the Chinese press, now
                    is quite an issue in Shanghai.
So we have a very -- it's just -- I've never seen anything quite as comprehensive
                    as the relationship we have with China, and it is comprehensive because it is so
                    fundamentally important. Still, we have to find ways not only to talk to China
                    about things that we agree -- already agree on or things that we already
                    disagree on, we also have to find ways to work with them together. And here I
                    think is the -- is where the six-party process I think plays a key role in the
                    relationship with China. I cannot tell you today that the six-party process is
                    going to succeed in getting North Korea to disarm itself of these nuclear
                    weapons. I think we have -- it has been a difficult process. We are dealing with
                    difficult people. But what I can tell you is that there is a certain early
                    harvest in the six-party process and that is the fact that we are able to work
                    very closely with China, come up with common initiatives, make approaches to
                    North Korea that are coordinated, have work multilaterally in very specific
                    areas such as with the South Koreans and yes, with the Japanese because a lot
                    has been said in recent months and recent years about the difficulty of
                    Sino-Japanese relations. But yet, in the six-party process they actually work,
                    they function and because we all share the interests of getting the North
                    Koreans to give up these weapons.
A key moment, I think, came in early July when against all advice, against all
                    admonitions all over the world North Korea decided to fire off several missiles.
                    There was really a missile for everybody in that barrage. There were some six or
                    seven missiles. There were short-range missiles whose only purpose in practicing
                    would have been to hit South Korea. There were short-range longer-range missiles
                    whose purpose would be threaten Japan, and there was Taepodong-2 missile whose
                    purpose would have to be looked at as an intercontinental missile ultimately
                    with the purpose of reaching the United States. In short, in that missile
                    barrage, the North Koreans essentially validated the concept of the six-party
                    talks. In that missile barrage, the North Koreans were essentially saying this
                    is not a U.S.-North Korean problem. We in North Korea are going to make it a
                    problem between us, the North Koreans and everyone else. They validated the
                    process of making this multilateral.
And so as soon as these missile launches happened, which was for us in the
                    afternoon of July 4th, the first example of a sense of irony I've ever seen from
                    North Korea, we got in -- went into action diplomatically, and I went off -- I
                    left that next day on the fifth. And normally when I'd make a trip to Asia to
                    discuss North Korea I'd start with our allies, Japan and South Korea. In this
                    case I went right to China. And I sat down with the Chinese and we went through
                    what could be done, what needed to be done. And I could see in China there was a
                    certain -- I should say a sea change in how they dealt with the North Koreans. I
                    was not asked to be more patient. Often the dynamic between me and the Chinese
                    is, as you can predict, the Chinese asking me to show more patience and I asking
                    the Chinese to show less patience. But in fact, I think we got on very quickly
                    to the task of what can we do to convince the North Koreans that they can't do
                    this.
And indeed as we began to discuss the need to respond, the need to respond
                    forcefully and with a sense of unity, the Chinese asked if they could be given
                    an opportunity to get up to Pyongyang and get from the North Koreans a
                    commitment to get back to the talks to re-impose a moratorium. And so we worked
                    that out. We worked that out in a way that our diplomacy going on in New York
                    with the passage -- with the work we're doing especially with the Japanese who
                    are on the Security Council to get the -- to have a strong resolution. We gave
                    the Chinese some time. We worked with the Chinese on their efforts to get up to
                    Pyongyang. They sent a very senior delegation to Pyongyang. And when they came
                    back, in fact I returned to China and we talked some more and we worked out,
                    especially our diplomats in New York, worked out a UN Security Council
                    Resolution 1695.
There are a couple of very important elements to that. The first element, of
                    course, is this was a great credit to Japanese diplomacy because they were the
                    ones who drafted it and began to press forward in the UN. But I think it was
                    also a great credit to our ability to work with China because at the end of the
                    day when 1695 was passed, it was actually the end of the week, it was unanimous
                    and China was on board, on board on a unanimous resolution dealing with a
                    neighboring country and significantly I think the word condemned, that is, the
                    people who supported -- the countries that supported this which included Japan
                    and China, we all used the same word, we condemn these missile launches.
We also called upon all member-states to exercise vigilance in ensuring that
                    North Korea does not get the funds and does not get the technology to continue
                    these types of programs. I saw in the Chinese, with respect to this North Korea
                    missile launch, a real kindred spirit, and I think it was very important. And so
                    someday in the annals of U.S.-China relations, we'll have to give Kim Jong-il a
                    little credit because he brought us much closer together that week.
We have also continued to work with China in other areas of the world. We're
                    working in Iran. We're working very, very feverishly with China to try to come
                    up with a resolution on Iran that would encourage Iran to do the right thing on
                    these weapons of mass destruction. This is a very difficult problem. It's a
                    problem that's also rooted in Iran's situation and its own neighborhood, but
                    it's also routed in the U.S. and China and the other Perm 5 members' desire to
                    see -- to prevent nuclear arms proliferation. And this is an area were I think
                    we're working very closely with the Chinese.
I do not mean to suggest that our relations with China are at this point a walk
                    in the park. We have a lot of issues, a lot of difficult issues where we deal
                    with China. We work with China on human rights issues, on religious freedom
                    questions. These are not easy issues. Some of these issues don't come naturally
                    to China, and we need to work with them and try to work with China on
                    international standards. We're not looking to impose a U.S. view on all of these
                    issues, we're looking to really gain an international consensus on how to
                    approach issues like human rights and religious freedom consistent with China's
                    agreement with the UN charter and consistent with China's desire to live up to
                    these universal values.
We also have to work very hard every day and every hour of every day on getting a
                    level playing field for U.S. businesses. Anyone who's been to China knows that
                    there has been improvement on intellectual property rights in the -- in a de
                    jure sense and in a legislative sense, but on the street the picture can
                    sometimes be different. Although I must say that if you try to buy a counterfeit
                    version of anything to do with the Beijing Olympics, you'll be very hard
                    pressed. In fact, the intellectual property rights of the Beijing Olympics are
                    being very well respected. And let's see if we can use that as an inspiration
                    for everything else including golf clubs.
So that is a work in progress, but I think we have a pretty strong and active
                    dialog with the Chinese on that. We're also working, and I know this is a --
                    this continues to be an enormous issue, to look for more transparency in
                    military budgets, in military doctrine and, in fact, in military intentions.
Now if you look at the U.S. budget, as the Chinese have done, you will notice the
                    U.S. budget somewhat exceeds the Chinese budget, a fact that has been brought to
                    light by Chinese analysts. We're not questioning that for a minute, but you can
                    also find in the U.S. budget exactly where the money is going. You can find the
                    supply of explanatory notes at times exceeding the demand for those same
                    explanations. In short, everyone in Washington has an opinion about our military
                    budget, and it's out for everybody to see.
China has not quite achieved, let me put it, the same degree of transparency. And
                    what we're really looking for from the Chinese is not necessarily to reduce
                    their budget or something like that, we're looking for transparency. What are
                    they doing? Where is the money going? Why is it going there? What is it -- what
                    are the contingencies they're working on? We need clarity on this and we need a
                    good dialog. We are beginning to have a dialog with the Chinese on this. I was
                    just with Admiral Fallon who has gone to China on several occasions, most
                    recently just a few weeks ago. We've had some -- we had some joint exercises
                    with the Chinese recently in San Diego. We are beginning a process to work on
                    ways that we can agree -- we can see what each other is doing because we still
                    do have a mountain of mistrust in this relationship, especially in this military
                    relationship, and we need to work on that.
We're also working in I'd like to mention a couple of other regional areas. I
                    know in Southeast Asia, an area that I also cover, that there are people who say
                    that the U.S. is somehow staging a strategic withdrawal while China is a staging
                    a strategic entry into that area. I really don't buy that frankly. I don't buy
                    the idea that we're leaving, and I don't buy the idea that the Chinese want us
                    to leave. I think there's -- more China in Southeast Asia does not mean less
                    U.S. After all, I think China for years and years, decades and decades, the
                    world has looked for a second engine of growth, and I think many countries are
                    finding that second engine of growth and it's called China. It's called the
                    China economy, and we welcome that. More China does not mean less U.S. there.
                    And so we can work that out.
We're also working in the Pacific island states. You know, people look at the
                    Pacific Island states, they look at the Pacific and they try to find the islands
                    there. Very small countries. I would that say sometimes big problems can come in
                    small places, and we need to make sure that governance issues in the Pacific
                    Island states and capacity issues, tiny places like the Solomon Islands, you
                    know, that those countries develop and don't become centers of problems and,
                    therefore, we need to make sure that countries that are big donors, and China is
                    a big donor in those states, finds ways to make sure that the assistance that
                    China is giving is going to causes that will help those countries develop
                    governance and capacity. And in that regard, we're going to have still another
                    dialog with the Chinese. We're going to sit down and talk about some of our
                    mutual assistance or assistance efforts in some of these countries.
So I think ultimately I feel that there is a real reason for optimism in this
                    relationship. I feel that the people who worked so hard on this relationship in
                    the late '40, early '50s, the people who really I think in some cases went to
                    their graves with a sense that this was going to be a very, very difficult
                    process that may not turn out well can actually, if they're still listening,
                    realize that a lot of their work in those very troubled years has led to some
                    very special developments. We are by no means there. We are by no means there,
                    but I hope that future generations can look back on this period and draw from it
                    a certain inspiration as we move forward.
So, again, I speak as a sort of a person who can maybe give some raw material to
                    your -- to what you are doing. I am not a historian. I probably spend more time
                    looking at the U.S. Civil War than I have at China's various civil wars. But I
                    do believe that to understand our history with China is to understand our future
                    with China. I'm very pleased at the publication of this. I will read every word
                    of it later in the day I guess. But to be sure it is I think an excellent time
                    to be reflecting on where we are with China because there's no relationship in
                    the world that's more important to us than the relationship with China.
Thank you very much. (Applause.)









Conferences


National Security Policy and
                                SALT I, 1969-1972

Foreign Economic Policy,
                                1973-1976

The American Experience in Southeast Asia,
                                1946-1975

U.S.-Soviet Relations in the Era of D&#233;tente,
                                1969-1976

Transforming the Cold War: The United States
                                and China, 1969-1980







Table of Contents


"Transforming the Cold War: The United States and China, 1969-1980"

Program

Opening Remarks

Keynote Speaker: Dr. Philip D. Zelikow, Counselor of the U.S. Department of
                    State

Panel of Former Diplomats and Government Officials

Introductions

Ambassador Winston Lord

Professor Richard Smyser

Lt. General Brent Scowcroft

Dr. Zbigniew Brezinski

Ambassador Charles Freeman

Panelist Comments

Question and Answer



Keynote Speaker: Christopher R. Hill, Assistant Secretary of State for East
                    Asian and Pacific Affairs
















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov/.</value><value>https://history.state.gov/.</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/opening-remarks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/zelikow</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/panel</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/lord</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/smyser</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/scowcroft</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/brzezinski</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/freeman</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/comments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/qa</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/susser</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/lord</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/smyser</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/scowcroft</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/brzezinski</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/freeman</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/comments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/qa</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2012-national-security-policy-salt</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2011-foreign-economic-policy</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2010-southeast-asia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2007-detente</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/program</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/opening-remarks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/zelikow</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/panel</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/susser</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/lord</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/smyser</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/scowcroft</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/brzezinski</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/freeman</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/comments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/qa</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war/hill</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//conferences/2006-china-cold-war</id></item>