<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1993-2000

Intervention in Haiti, 1994&#8211;1995






Milestones: 1993&#8211;2000








Intervention in Haiti, 1994&#8211;1995
On September 30, 1991, a military coup under the leadership of Lieutenant General
                    Raoul Cedras overthrew the government of Jean-Bertrand Aristide, the first
                    popularly elected president in Haitian history. President George H.W. Bush
                    called for the restoration of democracy, and worked with the Organization of
                    American States (OAS) to impose a trade embargo on all goods except medicine and
                    food. During his 1992 presidential candidacy, Bill Clinton criticized the Bush
                    administration for its policy on refugee return and promised to increase
                    pressure on the military junta by tightening economic sanctions.

USS America enroute to Haiti in September 1994,
                        with a unique complement of U.S. Army Special Forces and the 160th Army
                        Special Aviation Regiment embarked.

Unburdened by the Cold War international framework that structured U.S. foreign
                    policy for nearly fifty years, the Clinton administration sought to outline new
                    objectives for U.S. foreign policy, including novel uses for military power.
                    Ambassador to the United Nations Madeleine Albright outlined a U.S. policy of
                    &#8220;assertive multilateralism,&#8221; with an increased role for the United Nations.
                    National Security Advisor Anthony Lake emphasized the role of economic power in
                    the new world order, and argued for a U.S. role in the &#8220;enlargement&#8221; of the
                    community of free nations. The new administration, however, faced multiple
                    challenges in the former Yugoslavia, Somalia, North Korea, and Haiti that
                    complicated their attempts to implement the broad strategies and objectives
                    defined by the administration&#8217;s leaders.
Clinton appointed Lawrence Pezzullo as special envoy for Haiti, and as promised
                    in his campaign, worked to increase economic and diplomatic pressure on the
                    junta. On June 16 the United Nations voted to impose a ban on petroleum sales to
                    Haiti. Cedras agreed to participate in talks sponsored by the United Nations and
                    the OAS. The so-called &#8220;Governors Island Accord&#8221; signed by Aristide and Cedras
                    on July 3 called for Aristide&#8217;s return to Haiti by October 30, 1993, an amnesty
                    for the coup leaders, assistance in modernizing the Haitian Army, and the
                    establishment of a new Haitian police force. The agreement provided for the
                    suspension of U.N. sanctions once Aristide had assumed office in Haiti.
Despite indications that the Haitian military was backing away from the
                    agreement, the United States dispatched the USS Harlan
                        County with 200 U.S. and Canadian engineers and military police on
                    board to prepare for the return of Aristide. On October 11 the ship was met at
                    the pier in Port-au-Prince by a mob of Haitians, appearing to threaten violence.
                    With the street battle in Mogadishu only a week past, the administration proved
                    unwilling to risk casualties in Port-au-Prince. The ship pulled away the
                    following day and returned to the United States, a significant setback for the
                    Clinton administration.
Four days later, the United Nations Security Council imposed a naval blockade on
                    Haiti. Through the following months the administration pursued a dual strategy,
                    planning for military intervention while hoping that the threat of a U.S.
                    invasion would coerce the Haitian leaders to surrender power. Pressure toward
                    action continued to build, with Congressional Black Caucus members especially
                    vocal in demanding an end to military rule in Haiti.
The Clinton administration built the diplomatic foundation for the operation in
                    the summer of 1994, working to secure a United Nations Security Council
                    Resolution (UNSCR) authorizing the removal of the Haitian military regime. On
                    July 31 the Security Council passed UNSCR 940, the first resolution authorizing
                    the use of force to restore democracy for a member nation. It provided for the
                    reinstatement of the Aristide government and a six-month mandate for the United
                    Nations Mission in Haiti (UNMIH), which would maintain order after the
                    operation. The U.N. mandate authorizing the intervention enabled the
                    administration to recruit forces from Caribbean nations to serve in the
                    post-invasion security force.
In early September planning and preparation for the invasion was completed under
                    the code name Operation Uphold Democracy. The invasion force numbered nearly
                    25,000 military personnel from all services, backed by two aircraft carriers and
                    extensive air support. Although the United States provided the vast majority of
                    the forces, a multinational contingent from Caribbean nations agreed to serve in
                    an operation conducted under U.N. mandate. The addition of these multinational
                    forces shifted the operation from a U.S. military intervention to
                    U.N.-sanctioned multinational action. The operation was scheduled for September
                    19.
With military action clearly imminent, former President Jimmy Carter led a
                    delegation to Haiti in search of a negotiated settlement. Carter, Senator Sam
                    Nunn, and General Colin Powell flew to Haiti on September 17, well aware that
                    they had little time to reach agreement. President Clinton approved Carter&#8217;s
                    mission, but insisted that the military operation would proceed as scheduled.
                    The invasion forces launched with the negotiations in progress, without any
                    certainty whether they would make an opposed or a peaceful entry on to Haitian
                    soil.
The Haitian leadership capitulated in time to avoid bloodshed. Having launched
                    the operation with the expectation of a forced-entry assault, the forces
                    conducting the operation displayed remarkable discipline and flexibility in
                    adjusting to this new and uncertain environment. General Hugh Shelton, commander
                    of the invasion force, was transformed enroute to Haiti from commander to
                    diplomat, charged with working out a peaceful transition of power. Shelton and
                    Cedras met on September 20, 1994, to begin the process, and Aristide returned to
                    Haiti on October 15. 
Military planners had defined the conditions for hand-off to UNMIH as the
                    restoration of basic order, the return of Aristide, and the conduction of a
                    presidential election and subsequent peaceful transfer of power. The operation
                    ended with the transfer to UNMIH command on March 31, 1995, and a peaceful
                    election and transferal of power occurred on February 7, 1996. The operation
                    yielded important lessons about the complexities involved in managing complex
                    contingency operations, which were captured in PDD/NSC 56, &#8220;Managing Complex
                    Contingency Operations,&#8221; issued in May 1997.









Table of Contents


1993&#8211;2000: The Presidency of William J.
                    Clinton

The Evolution of NATO, 1988&#8211;2001

Somalia, 1992&#8211;1993

The War in Bosnia, 1992&#8211;1995

Bill Clinton, Boris Yeltsin, and U.S.-Russian Relations

Denuclearization and the Two Koreas, 1993&#8211;2001

The Oslo Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process

Intervention in Haiti, 1994&#8211;1995















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/haiti</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/oslo</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/evolution-of-nato</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/somalia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/bosnia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/clinton-yeltsin</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/two-koreas</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/oslo</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/haiti</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/haiti</id></item>