<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1989-1992

The Collapse of the Soviet Union






Milestones: 1989&#8211;1992








The Collapse of the Soviet Union
After his inauguration in January 1989, George H.W. Bush did
                    not automatically follow the policy of his predecessor, Ronald
                        Reagan, in dealing with Mikhail Gorbachev
                    and the Soviet Union. Instead, he ordered a strategic policy re-evaluation in
                    order to establish his own plan and methods for dealing with the Soviet Union
                    and arms control.

Boris Yeltsin makes a speech from atop a tank in front of the Russian
                        parliament building in Moscow, U.S.S.R., Monday, Aug. 19, 1991. (AP Photo)
                    

Conditions in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, however, changed rapidly.
                    Gorbachev&#8217;s decision to loosen the Soviet yoke on the countries of Eastern
                    Europe created an independent, democratic momentum that led to the collapse of
                    the Berlin Wall in November 1989, and then the overthrow of Communist rule
                    throughout Eastern Europe. While Bush supported these independence movements,
                    U.S. policy was reactive. Bush chose to let events unfold organically, careful
                    not to do anything to worsen Gorbachev&#8217;s position.
With the policy review complete, and taking into account unfolding events in
                    Europe, Bush met with Gorbachev at Malta in early December 1989. They laid the
                    groundwork for finalizing START negotiations, completing the Conventional Forces
                    in Europe treaty, and they discussed the rapid changes in Eastern Europe. Bush
                    encouraged Gorbachev&#8217;s reform efforts, hoping that the Soviet leader would
                    succeed in shifting the USSR toward a democratic system and a market oriented
                    economy.
Gorbachev&#8217;s decision to allow elections with a multi-party system and create a
                    presidency for the Soviet Union began a slow process of democratization that
                    eventually destabilized Communist control and contributed to the collapse of the
                    Soviet Union. Following the May 1990 elections, Gorbachev faced conflicting
                    internal political pressures: Boris Yeltsin and the pluralist movement advocated
                    democratization and rapid economic reforms while the hard-line Communist elite
                    wanted to thwart Gorbachev&#8217;s reform agenda.
Facing a growing schism between Yeltsin and Gorbachev, the Bush administration
                    opted to work primarily with Gorbachev because they viewed him as the more
                    reliable partner and because he made numerous concessions that promoted U.S.
                    interests. Plans proceeded to sign the START agreement. With the withdrawal of
                    Red Army troops from East Germany, Gorbachev agreed to German reunification and
                    acquiesced when a newly reunited Germany joined NATO. When Saddam Hussein
                    invaded Kuwait, the United States and the Soviet leadership worked together
                    diplomatically to repel this attack.
Yet for all of those positive steps on the international stage, Gorbachev&#8217;s
                    domestic problems continued to mount. Additional challenges to Moscow&#8217;s control
                    placed pressure on Gorbachev and the Communist party to retain power in order to
                    keep the Soviet Union intact. After the demise of Communist regimes in Eastern
                    Europe, the Baltic States and the Caucasus demanded independence from Moscow. In
                    January 1991, violence erupted in Lithuania and Latvia. Soviet tanks intervened
                    to halt the democratic uprisings, a move that Bush resolutely condemned.
By 1991, the Bush administration reconsidered policy options in light of the
                    growing level of turmoil within the Soviet Union. Three basic options presented
                    themselves. The administration could continue to support Gorbachev in hopes of
                    preventing Soviet disintegration. Alternately, the United States could shift
                    support to Yeltsin and the leaders of the Republics and provide support for a
                    controlled restructuring or possible breakup of the Soviet Union. The final
                    option consisted of lending conditional support to Gorbachev, leveraging aid and
                    assistance in return for more rapid and radical political and economic reforms. 
Unsure about how much political capital Gorbachev retained, Bush combined
                    elements of the second and third options. The Soviet nuclear arsenal was vast,
                    as were Soviet conventional forces, and further weakening of Gorbachev could
                    derail further arms control negotiations. To balance U.S. interests in relation
                    to events in the Soviet Union, and in order to demonstrate support for
                    Gorbachev, Bush signed the START treaty at the Moscow Summit in July 1991. Bush
                    administration officials also, however, increased contact with Yeltsin.
The unsuccessful August 1991 coup against Gorbachev sealed the fate of the Soviet
                    Union. Planned by hard-line Communists, the coup diminished Gorbachev&#8217;s power
                    and propelled Yeltsin and the democratic forces to the forefront of Soviet and
                    Russian politics. Bush publicly condemned the coup as &#8220;extra-constitutional,&#8221;
                    but Gorbachev&#8217;s weakened position became obvious to all. He resigned his
                    leadership as head of the Communist party shortly thereafter&#8212;separating the
                    power of the party from that of the presidency of the Soviet Union. The Central
                    Committee was dissolved and Yeltsin banned party activities. A few days after
                    the coup, Ukraine and Belarus declared their independence from the Soviet Union.
                    The Baltic States, which had earlier declared their independence, sought
                    international recognition.
Amidst quick, dramatic changes across the landscape of the Soviet Union, Bush
                    administration officials prioritized the prevention of nuclear catastrophe, the
                    curbing of ethnic violence, and the stable transition to new political orders.
                    On September 4, 1991, Secretary of State James Baker articulated five basic
                    principles that would guide U.S. policy toward the emerging republics:
                    self-determination consistent with democratic principles, recognition of
                    existing borders, support for democracy and rule of law, preservation of human
                    rights and rights of national minorities, and respect for international law and
                    obligations. The basic message was clear&#8212;if the new republics could follow these
                    principles, they could expect cooperation and assistance from the United States.
                    Baker met with Gorbachev and Yeltsin in an attempt to shore up the economic
                    situation and develop some formula for economic cooperation between the
                    republics and Russia, as well as to determine ways to allow political reforms to
                    occur in a regulated and peaceful manner. In early December, Yeltsin and the
                    leaders of Ukraine and Belarus met in Brest to form the Commonwealth of
                    Independent States (CIS), effectively declaring the demise of the Soviet
                    Union.
On December 25, 1991, the Soviet hammer and sickle flag lowered for the last time
                    over the Kremlin, thereafter replaced by the Russian tricolor. Earlier in the
                    day, Mikhail Gorbachev resigned his post as president of the Soviet Union,
                    leaving Boris Yeltsin as president of the newly independent Russian state.
                    People all over the world watched in amazement at this relatively peaceful
                    transition from former Communist monolith into multiple separate nations.
With the dissolution of Soviet Union, the main goal of the Bush administration
                    was economic and political stability and security for Russia, the Baltics, and
                    the states of the former Soviet Union. Bush recognized all 12 independent
                    republics and established diplomatic relations with Russia, Ukraine, Belarus,
                    Kazakhstan, Armenia and Kyrgyzstan. In February 1992, Baker visited the
                    remaining republics and diplomatic relations were established with Uzbekistan,
                    Moldova, Azerbaijan, Turkmenistan, and Tajikistan. Civil war in Georgia
                    prevented its recognition and the establishment of diplomatic relations with the
                    United States until May 1992. Yeltsin met with Bush at Camp David in February
                    1992, followed by a formal state visit to Washington in June. Leaders from
                    Kazakhstan and Ukraine visited Washington in May 1992.
During his visits to Washington, politics, economic reforms, and security issues
                    dominated the conversations between Yeltsin and Bush. Of paramount concern was
                    securing the nuclear arsenal of the former Soviet Union and making certain
                    nuclear weapons did not fall into the wrong hands. Baker made it clear that
                    funding was available from the United States to secure nuclear, chemical and
                    biological weapons in the former Soviet Union. The Nunn-Lugar Act established
                    the Cooperative Threat Reduction Program in November 1991 to fund the
                    dismantling of weapons in the former Soviet Union, in accordance with the START
                    and INF Treaties and other agreements. Bush and Baker also worked with Yeltsin
                    and international organizations like the World Bank and IMF to provide financial
                    assistance and hopefully prevent a humanitarian crisis in Russia.









Table of Contents


1989&#8211;1992: The Presidency of George H.W.
                    Bush

The End of Apartheid

Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC), 1989

Fall of Communism in Eastern Europe, 1989

The Collapse of the Soviet Union

The Breakup of Yugoslavia, 1990&#8211;1992

Tiananmen Square, 1989

The Gulf War, 1991

The Madrid Conference, 1991

Strategic Arms Reduction Treaties, 1991 and 1993















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/collapse-soviet-union</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/fall-of-communism</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/breakup-yugoslavia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apartheid</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apec</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/fall-of-communism</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/collapse-soviet-union</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/breakup-yugoslavia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/tiananmen-square</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/gulf-war</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/madrid-conference</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/strategic-arms-reduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/collapse-soviet-union</id></item>