<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1981-1988

The Reagan Administration and Lebanon, 1981&#8211;1984






Milestones: 1981&#8211;1988








The Reagan Administration and Lebanon, 1981&#8211;1984
From 1981 onward, the Reagan administration feared that conflict between Lebanese
                    factions backed by Syria and Israel, along with clashes between Israel and the
                    Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), could escalate into an Arab-Israeli
                    war. Yet American policymakers differed over how to prevent such a conflict,
                    especially over whether to commit troops for that purpose. Following Israel&#8217;s
                    1982 invasion of Lebanon, the advocates of military intervention won out. But by
                    1984, terrorist attacks, a lack of diplomatic progress, and congressional
                    opposition led President Ronald Reagan to withdraw U.S.
                    forces from Lebanon.

U.S. Marines on patrol in Beirut, April 1983. (Department of
                        Defense)

In April 1981, the Israeli Air Force attacked Syrian forces in Lebanon to prevent
                    them from seizing the strategic Sannin ridge. Syria responded by deploying
                    surface-to-air missiles into the Biqa&#8216; Valley, threatening Israel&#8217;s ability to
                    monitor PLO forces in Lebanon. To avert war, Reagan sent emissary
                        Philip Habib to the Middle East, but he failed to
                    persuade the Syrians to withdraw the missiles. When fighting escalated between
                    Israel and the PLO that July, the Reagan administration feared that Israel would
                    invade Lebanon. Ultimately, Habib managed to negotiate a de facto ceasefire
                    between Israel and the PLO.
The ceasefire, however, merely postponed a larger crisis. The Lebanese remained
                    at odds, Syria refused to withdraw its missiles, and Israel chafed under the
                    restrictions of the ceasefire, which allowed the PLO to strengthen itself and
                    did not prevent terrorist attacks from the West Bank and Gaza Strip or against
                    Israeli and Jewish targets in Europe. In London on June 3, 1982, Palestinian
                    assailants shot Shlomo Argov, Israel&#8217;s ambassador to the United Kingdom. The
                    Israel Defense Forces (IDF) invaded Lebanon on June 6.
The Reagan administration was divided over how to respond to Israel&#8217;s invasion.
                    Secretary of State Alexander Haig argued that the United
                    States should not pressure Israel to withdraw without demanding that the PLO and
                    Syria do likewise. Secretary of Defense Caspar Weinberger,
                    Vice President George Bush, and National Security Advisor
                        William Clark wanted the IDF to withdraw immediately
                    and to sanction Israel if they did not. The debate sharpened when the IDF
                    destroyed Syria&#8217;s missiles in the Biqa&#8216; on June 9, raising the specter of a
                    wider war. President Reagan sent Habib to Israel to demand a ceasefire. The IDF
                    halted its advance into the Biqa&#8216; but continued to the outskirts of
                    PLO-controlled West Beirut.
With the Israeli-Syrian confrontation defused, Reagan adopted Haig&#8217;s strategy of
                    helping the Lebanese Government take over West Beirut, then negotiating Israeli
                    and Syrian withdrawal. By July, the PLO informed Habib that they would leave
                    Beirut if an international force deployed to protect Palestinian civilians.
                    Against Weinberger&#8217;s advice, Reagan agreed to contribute Marines to a
                    multinational force (MNF), alongside French and Italian troops. However, the
                    Palestinian withdrawal did not begin until August 21. The United States could
                    not convince any Arab country to receive all PLO fighters from Beirut; they were
                    ultimately dispersed to several states. Initially, the Israelis refused to let
                    the MNF deploy until the PLO left, instead intensifying their attacks on Beirut.
                    The PLO completed its withdrawal by September 1. Though the MNF was supposed to
                    remain for thirty days, Weinberger announced that the Marines would leave on
                    September 10.
On September 14, Lebanese President-elect Bashir Gemayel,
                    whose election had been backed by the Israelis, was assassinated. Citing a need
                    to prevent civil disorder, the IDF entered West Beirut. By September 18, it
                    became clear that the Israelis had allowed Maronite militiamen to enter the
                    Sabra and Shatilla camps and massacre Palestinian civilians. An international
                    outcry ensued, and Reagan decided to commit Marines to a new MNF. On October 28,
                    Reagan signed National Security Decision Directive (NSDD) 64, calling for the
                    United States to work toward the withdrawal of foreign forces from Lebanon, help
                    rebuild the Lebanese Army, and contribute to an expanded MNF if necessary. In
                    April&#8211;May 1983, Secretary of State George Shultz helped Israel and Lebanon
                    negotiate an agreement that ended the hostilities between the two countries and
                    provided a basis for normal relations once Israel withdrew. For Israel to
                    withdraw, however, Syrian and Palestinian forces would also need to leave
                    Lebanon. 
The Israeli-Lebanese agreement was opposed by Syrian President Hafiz
                        al-Asad, who claimed that it would enable Israel to dominate
                    Lebanon. Asad refused to remove his troops and encouraged Lebanese opposition to
                    President Amin Gemayel. Meanwhile, the Israelis, facing
                    guerilla attacks in the Shuf, decided that they would unilaterally withdraw from
                    the area.
The Reagan administration feared that an Israeli pullback could lead to the
                    partition of Lebanon and expose the MNF to shelling from the Shuf. New emissary
                        Robert McFarlane attempted to soften Syria&#8217;s position,
                    delay Israeli withdrawal, and help Gemayel and his opponents reconcile, but
                    without success. The IDF pulled back on September 3, and fighting erupted
                    between Maronite Lebanese Forces and pro-Syrian militias led by Walid
                        Jumblatt&#8217;s Popular Socialist Party. To prevent Lebanese troops
                    from intervening, Jumblatt and his allies attacked them as well, leading
                    McFarlane to warn that they might reach Beirut and topple Gemayel&#8217;s
                    government.
Reagan responded by authorizing the Marines to engage in &#8220;aggressive
                    self-defense,&#8221; dispatching the battleship New Jerseyto
                    Lebanon, and authorizing naval gunfire and airstrikes to prevent hostile forces
                    from seizing Suq al-Gharb, which overlooked the Marine barracks. But by the time
                    a ceasefire took hold on September 25, the fighting had provoked significant
                    opposition to Reagan&#8217;s Lebanon policy. On September 29, Congress passed
                    legislation invoking the War Powers Act and authorizing the Marines to remain in
                    Lebanon for 18 months, the first time constraint placed on their presence.
                    Weinberger now proposed withdrawing U.S. forces offshore.
On October 23, suicide bombers attacked the barracks of the U.S. and French
                    contingents of the MNF, killing 241 American servicemen. The administration
                    believed that the bombings, like the attack on the U.S. Embassy in Beirut that
                    April, were perpetrated by Shi&#8216;i militants linked to Syria&#8217;s ally Iran. Reagan
                    responded by adopting a tough policy championed by Shultz and McFarlane, now
                    National Security Advisor. On October 28, he signed NSDD 111, which called for
                    broadening strategic cooperation with Israel and Arab opponents of Syria,
                    reducing Syrian influence over Lebanon&#8217;s Druze and Shi&#8216;a, and expanded rules of
                    engagement regarding naval and air support for the Lebanese Army.
The implementation of NSDD 111, however, was marred by disagreements between
                    Reagan&#8217;s advisors, Syrian intransigence, a lack of progress toward Lebanese
                    reconciliation, and major public relations setbacks. Though Reagan publicly
                    proclaimed that the perpetrators of the October 23 bombings &#8220;must be dealt
                    justice,&#8221; U.S. forces did not join their French counterparts in attacking an
                    Iranian Revolutionary Guards barrack in the Biqa&#8216; that November. McFarlane later
                    contended that Reagan had authorized U.S. participation in the strikes, but
                    Weinberger refused to follow through on his order. On December 4, the Syrians
                    shot down two U.S. planes, and held one of the pilots, Lt. Robert Goodman,
                    prisoner until releasing him to Democratic presidential candidate Jesse Jackson.
                    Even more damaging to the administration&#8217;s prestige were press leaks regarding
                    the Department of Defense&#8217;s Long Commission report, which harshly criticized the
                    Marines&#8217; deployment. On February 1, 1984, amidst mounting congressional
                    criticism, Reagan approved the idea of redeploying the Marines but did not set a
                    date for doing so. Almost immediately afterward, however, pro-Syrian militias
                    overran West Beirut, and on February 7, Reagan announced that the Marines would
                    withdraw offshore.
Reagan&#8217;s decision to withdraw the Marines remains controversial. Supporters argue
                    that it did not make sense to sacrifice American lives and resources to help
                    resolve a conflict where the parties involved showed little interest in working
                    toward U.S. goals. Critics, however, claim that Reagan failed to stand firm
                    against terrorism and demonstrated that the United States was an undependable
                    ally.









Table of Contents


1981&#8211;1988: The Presidency of Ronald W.
                    Reagan

U.S.-Soviet Relations, 1981&#8211;1991

Central America, 1981&#8211;1993

The Reagan Administration and Lebanon, 1981&#8211;1984

Crisis in the South Atlantic: The Reagan Administration and the
                    Anglo-Argentine War of 1982

The August 17, 1982 U.S.-China Communiqu&#233; on Arms Sales to Taiwan















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/lebanon</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/central-america</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/south-atlantic</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/u.s.-soviet-relations</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/central-america</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/lebanon</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/south-atlantic</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/china-communique</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/lebanon</id></item>