<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1981-1988

Central America, 1981&#8211;1993






Milestones: 1981&#8211;1988








Central America, 1981&#8211;1993
Following his electoral victory in November 1980, President Ronald
                        Reagan amplified the concerns expressed by President Carter and
                    Congress about foreign support of Central American leftist guerrilla forces. In
                    February 1981, a month after the leftist Farabundo Mart&#237;
                        National Liberation Front (FMLN) launched a major offensive against the
                    Salvadoran military, the Department of State issued a White Paper stating that
                    Cuba and other Communist countries had played a central role in the political
                    unification, military direction, and arming of the Salvadoran insurgents.
                    Secretary of State Alexander Haig accused the Sandinista
                    government of exporting terrorism to El Salvador and in April 1981, Reagan
                    terminated economic assistance to Nicaragua citing its involvement in supporting
                    Salvadoran rebels. After several failed diplomatic attempts to dissuade Managua
                    from supporting FMLN activities, Reagan opted to support a clandestine guerrilla
                    force to quash the Sandinista training and arming of Salvadoran guerillas. These
                    &#8220;Contras,&#8221; as in &#8220;counterrevolutionaries,&#8221; were primarily ex-Nicaraguan National
                    Guard members who had gathered in Honduran territory. The Contras launched their
                    first major attack against the Sandinistas in March 1982. In response, the
                    Sandinistas undertook a dramatic build-up of military manpower assisted by
                    Soviet and Cuban advisers and weaponry, mostly from the Soviet bloc.

Supporters of the Nicaraguan Contra rebels outside a protest against the
                        Contras at Hurlburt Field, Florida.(Department of Defense)

Reagan&#8217;s efforts to strengthen the Contras met with opposition from a divided
                    Congress and resistance in Nicaragua. Concerns about the ultimate goals of the
                    Contras and the possibility of direct U.S. military involvement prompted
                    Representative Edward Boland, Chairman of the House
                    Intelligence Committee, to sponsor legislation in December 1982 that prohibited
                    the use of U.S. funds for the purpose of overthrowing the Sandinista government.
                    The bill, signed into law by Reagan later that December, allowed assistance to
                    the Contras for other purposes. Reagan continued to advocate increases in
                    support for the Contras. He addressed a joint session of Congress in April 1983
                    asserting that the Sandinista government presented a threat to Central America
                    and U.S. national security. American military exercises off the Nicaraguan coast
                    and the invasion of Grenada in October 1983 demonstrated Reagan&#8217;s commitment to
                    countering Communist threats in the region. Consequently, the Sandinistas
                    decided to participate in the Contadora peace negotiations that had begun in
                    January 1983 at the initiative of Mexico, Venezuela, Colombia, and Panama.
                    Claiming success in rolling back Communism in Grenada, Reagan gained
                    congressional increases of up to $100 million in non-military aid to the
                    Contras. In October 1984, however, Congress ended the support after learning
                    about the mining of Nicaraguan harbors and the destruction of an oil facility.
                    In November 1984 Reagan&#8217;s re-election and Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega&#8217;s
                    elevation to president in a controversial national election set the tone for
                    additional confrontation.
Reagan redoubled his commitment to the Contras in his second term. In his 1985
                    State of the Union address he called them &#8220;freedom-fighters&#8221; who were risking
                    their lives to &#8220;defy Soviet-supported aggression.&#8221; In June 1985 Congress agreed
                    to $27 million in humanitarian aid for the Contras, but no military support.
                    Sandinista victories against the Contra fighters, heavy Presidential lobbying,
                    and an incursion into Honduran territory by Nicaraguan forces helped to sway
                    Congress into approving $100 million for the Contras, with seventy percent
                    allocated for military aid to be delivered in October 1986. However, the
                    Iran-Contra scandal broke the next month. The Tower Commission reported that
                    White House staff members had been using extralegal funds raised from arms sales
                    to Iran and foreign donors to arm the Contras prior to October 1986.
Following the deaths of hundreds of thousands and a decade of economic
                    devastation, peace initiatives eventually gained traction in Central America.
                    Numerous efforts to establish a peace plan by regional leaders, the United
                    Nations, and the Organization of American States had continued in the wake of
                    the 1983 Contadora initiative. In August 1987, Central American leaders signed a
                    peace accord at Esquipulas, Guatemala that had been shaped and promoted
                    primarily by Costa Rican President &#211;scar Arias. The plan focused on
                    democratization and regional security, backed with a system of verification.
                    Meeting in Costa Rica in January 1988, Central American leaders cemented their
                    commitment to implement the Guatemala peace accord. Nicaraguan President Ortega
                    entered into negotiations with the Contras and the United States began to shift
                    aid to humanitarian purposes. Nicaragua implemented the accord and held
                    internationally supervised elections in 1990. Violeta
                        Chamorro, former member of the revolutionary Provisional
                    Government and widow of Pedro Joaqu&#237;n Chamorro, the
                    journalist and hero of the opposition who had been slain in 1978, was elected
                    president and the Contras disbanded. The civil war in El Salvador lasted until
                    1991, when the FMLN reached a peace accord with the Salvadoran Government under
                    United Nations supervision. In Guatemala, fighting between leftist groups and
                    the military continued into the mid-1990s.
Washington continued to perceive threats in Central America after the end of the
                    Cold War. On December 20, 1989, President George H.W. Bush
                    dispatched over twenty thousand troops to invade Panama and arrest its head of
                    state, Manuel Noriega. Noriega had nullified a presidential
                    election won by opposition candidate Guillermo Endara that
                    May. In addition, Bush had become opposed to Noriega's continued leadership of
                    Panama due to Noriega&#8217;s connections with drug smuggling and money laundering, as
                    well as the declining security situation around the Panama Canal. In the months leading up to the
                    invasion, the Bush administration implemented economic sanctions and increased
                    local troop levels. The Panamanian legislature declared that a state of war
                    existed with the United States on December 15 due to the escalating tension
                    between the two countries. A U.S. serviceman was killed in Panama the following
                    day; this and other events, including the harassment of a U.S. officer and his
                    wife, precipitated U.S. action. Code-named Operation Just Cause, the fighting
                    lasted for five days. After taking refuge in the Vatican Embassy, Noriega
                    eventually surrendered to U.S. authorities and Endara regained his presidency.
                    Noriega was tried in a United States court and convicted on charges of drug
                    trafficking, money laundering, and racketeering.









Table of Contents


1981&#8211;1988: The Presidency of Ronald W.
                    Reagan

U.S.-Soviet Relations, 1981&#8211;1991

Central America, 1981&#8211;1993

The Reagan Administration and Lebanon, 1981&#8211;1984

Crisis in the South Atlantic: The Reagan Administration and the
                    Anglo-Argentine War of 1982

The August 17, 1982 U.S.-China Communiqu&#233; on Arms Sales to Taiwan















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/central-america</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/u.s.-soviet-relations</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/lebanon</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/u.s.-soviet-relations</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/central-america</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/lebanon</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/south-atlantic</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/china-communique</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/central-america</id></item>