<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1981-1988

1981&#8211;1988: The Presidency of Ronald W.
                    Reagan






Milestones: 1981&#8211;1988








1981&#8211;1988: The Presidency of Ronald W.
                    Reagan
The principal foreign policy framework for the Ronald Reagan
                    administration rejected acquiescence in the Cold War status quo that had emerged
                    during the Nixon, Ford, and Carter presidencies. Reagan objected to the implied
                    moral equivalency of d&#233;tente, insisting instead on the superiority of
                    representative government, free-market capitalism, and freedom of conscience
                    over what he viewed as godless, collectivist, Communism. This more
                    confrontational approach eventually came to be labeled the &#8220;Reagan Doctrine,&#8221;
                    which advocated opposition to Communist-supported regimes wherever they existed,
                    as well as a willingness to directly challenge the Soviet Union on a variety of
                    fronts.
Often referred to as &#8220;the great communicator,&#8221; Reagan utilized his rhetorical
                    skills to frame the Cold War contest as a fundamental clash between good and
                    evil. In his first inaugural address on January 20, 1981, the new President
                    contrasted the &#8220;enemies of freedom&#8221; as doomed to fail when faced with the &#8220;will
                    and moral courage of free men and women.&#8221; Later that year in an address at Notre
                    Dame University he stated that &#8220;the West won&#8217;t contain Communism, it will
                    transcend Communism.&#8221; In 1983, he famously characterized the Soviet Union as an
                    &#8220;evil empire.&#8221; In 1987, standing in front of the Berlin Wall constructed by the
                    East German communist regime a quarter-century earlier to stem the flow of East
                    Germans to the West, Reagan challenged the patron of the East German regime,
                    Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev, to &#8220;tear down this wall.&#8221; Reagan&#8217;s many
                    memorable public addresses served as an important tool to galvanize support for
                    policies that often sparked considerable controversy.

Arrival of General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev of the USSR for his first
                        meeting with President Reagan for the Geneva Summit at Fleur D&#8217;Eau in
                        Switzerland, November 19, 1985. (Ronald Reagan Presidential Library)

The Reagan administration advocated a wide array of initiatives that heightened
                    confrontation with the U.S.S.R. and its allies. Reagan engineered a significant
                    increase in U.S. defense spending designed to modernize existing forces and
                    achieve technological advances the Soviet Union could not match. For example,
                    the administration advocated building a much larger navy with enhanced technical
                    capabilities, deployment of intermediate-range nuclear missiles in Europe,
                    development of terrain-hugging cruise missiles difficult both to detect and to
                    shoot down, and the Strategic Defense Initiative, which held out the prospect of
                    seizing the ultimate &#8220;high ground&#8221;&#8212;outer space&#8212;by preventing intercontinental
                    nuclear missile warheads from reaching their targets. During his two terms in
                    office, Reagan successfully advocated increasing the Defense Department budget
                    by 35%. The United States supported Afghan resistance organizations opposing the
                    Soviet-backed regime in Kabul, anti-communist forces in Angola, and the Contras
                    in Nicaragua. In 1983 American forces invaded Grenada to forestall installation
                    of a Marxist regime. The administration also greatly increased spending on the
                    U.S. Information Agency, especially Voice of America and Radio Free Europe/Radio
                    Liberty, signaling the importance placed on challenging Soviet ideology
                    throughout the world.
Conversely, heightened tensions also led Reagan administration officials to
                    attempt conciliatory measures designed to reduce the threat of direct
                    confrontation, especially nuclear war. In 1982, Reagan broached the idea of
                    substantially decreasing nuclear weapon stockpiles, which eventually resulted in
                    the landmark Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty (START). The emergence of Mikhail
                    Gorbachev as the principal Soviet leader provided Reagan with a partner willing
                    to engage in substantive negotiations. A series of summit meetings ensued which
                    reduced tensions and produced concrete results, such as the 1987
                    Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty (INF) that eliminated the deployment of
                    theater-level nuclear missiles in Europe.
The Reagan administration dealt with many other foreign policy issues as well.
                    Affairs in and around Southwest Asia continued to present multiple challenges,
                    including a Lebanese civil war, strained relations with Iran, and increasing
                    tensions after the bombing of Libya in retaliation for a state-sanctioned
                    terrorist attack in Berlin. A (third) joint communiqu&#233; with the Peoples&#8217;
                    Republic of China reiterated both parties&#8217; commitment to improved relations,
                    while not resolving all issues related to Taiwan. Trade disputes with Japan
                    required constant attention. The United States had to determine what course to
                    steer amid hostilities between allies during the Falklands Crisis. A variety of
                    global issues also rose to prominence. After a decade of negotiation, the
                    administration opted not to support Senate ratification of a comprehensive Law
                    of the Sea treaty out of concerns about the potential for the internationalizing
                    of seabed mining operations and potential impingement on U.S. Navy prerogatives.
                    The United States increasingly promoted its enforcement preferences regarding
                    drug trafficking, resulting in a landmark 1988 treaty. It became apparent that
                    the AIDS crisis represented an international public health issue of consequence.
                    With the increasing rapidity of international communications, enhanced global
                    trade, and the rising world-wide movement of people, many issues previously
                    considered &#8220;domestic&#8221; became subject to diplomatic negotiation.
The Secretary of State occupied a prominent position in Reagan&#8217;s approach to
                    creating and implementing foreign policy. Alexander Haig
                    first occupied the chair, but an inability to exert as much influence as he
                    desired caused him to resign after only 18 months in office. George
                        Shultz served as Secretary for the remainder of Reagan&#8217;s two
                    terms, and is generally regarded as an effective bureaucratic manager and
                    influential policy leader. Caspar Weinberger served as
                    Secretary of Defense for almost seven years and William
                        Casey as Director of Central Intelligence for six years. Both
                    played key roles in the foreign policy arena. The position of National Security
                    Adviser was downgraded somewhat during the Reagan administration. The six
                    individuals who occupied the position exercised relatively less influence than
                    predecessors in the Carter, Ford, or Nixon White House.
Perhaps to an unusual degree, the accomplishments of this administration are
                    viewed in the light of events that occurred after Ronald Reagan left office in
                    January 1989. Within a year, the Berlin Wall fell, and by the end of 1991 the
                    Soviet Union had collapsed, signaling the end of the Cold War. Historians and
                    other analysts continue to debate the extent of their influence, but there is no
                    question that Ronald Reagan and his foreign policy advisers played key roles in
                    this remarkable turn of events.









Table of Contents


1981&#8211;1988: The Presidency of Ronald W.
                    Reagan

U.S.-Soviet Relations, 1981&#8211;1991

Central America, 1981&#8211;1993

The Reagan Administration and Lebanon, 1981&#8211;1984

Crisis in the South Atlantic: The Reagan Administration and the
                    Anglo-Argentine War of 1982

The August 17, 1982 U.S.-China Communiqu&#233; on Arms Sales to Taiwan















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov/#</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/u.s.-soviet-relations</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/u.s.-soviet-relations</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/central-america</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/lebanon</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/south-atlantic</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/china-communique</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988/foreword</id></item>