<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1989-1992

Fall of Communism in Eastern Europe, 1989






Milestones: 1989&#8211;1992








Fall of Communism in Eastern Europe, 1989

On November 9, 1989, thousands of jubilant Germans brought down the most visible
                    symbol of division at the heart of Europe&#8212;the Berlin Wall. For two generations,
                    the Wall was the physical representation of the Iron Curtain, and East German
                    border guards had standing shoot-to-kill orders against those who tried to
                    escape. But just as the Wall had come to represent the division of Europe, its
                    fall came to represent the end of the Cold War. In the White House, President
                    George H. W. Bush and his National Security Advisor, Brent Scowcroft, watched
                    the unfolding scene on a television in the study, aware of both the historical
                    significance of the moment and of the challenges for U.S. foreign policy that
                    lay ahead.

Germans celebrating the fall of the Berlin Wall on November 10, 1989. (AP
                        Photo/File) 

Not even the most optimistic observer of President&#8217;s Ronald Reagan&#8217;s 1987 Berlin
                    speech calling on Soviet General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev to &#8220;tear down this
                    wall&#8221; would have imagined that two years later the communist regimes of Eastern
                    Europe would collapse like dominoes. By 1990, the former communist leaders were
                    out of power, free elections were held, and Germany was whole again.
The peaceful collapse of the regimes was by no means pre-ordained. Soviet tanks
                    crushed demonstrators in East Berlin in June 1953, in Hungary in 1956, and again
                    in Czechoslovakia in 1968. Soviet military planners were intimately involved in
                    the Polish planning for martial law in 1980, and Soviet troops remained
                    stationed throughout Eastern Europe, as much a guarantee for Soviet security as
                    an ominous reminder to Eastern European peoples of Soviet dominance over their
                    countries. 
The Reagan administration&#8217;s strong rhetoric in support of the political
                    aspirations of Eastern European and Soviet citizens was met, following 1985,
                    with a new type of leader in the Soviet Union. Mikhail Gorbachev&#8217;s policies of
                        perestroika (restructuring) and glasnost (transparency) further legitimized popular calls for reform
                    from within. Gorbachev also made clear&#8212;at first secretly to the Eastern European
                    leaders, then increasingly more public&#8212;that the Soviet Union had abandoned the
                    policy of military intervention in support of communist regimes (the Brezhnev
                    Doctrine).
On February 6, 1989, negotiations between the Polish Government and members of
                    the underground labor union Solidarity opened officially in Warsaw. Solidarity
                    was formed in August 1980 following a series of strikes that paralyzed the
                    Polish economy. The 1981 Soviet-inspired imposition of martial law drove the
                    organization underground, where it survived due to support from Western labor
                    organizations and Polish &#233;migr&#233; groups. The results of the &#8220;Round Table Talks,&#8221;
                    signed by government and Solidarity representatives on April 4, included free
                    elections for 35% of the Parliament (Sejm), free
                    elections for the newly created Senate, a new office of the President, and the
                    recognition of Solidarity as a political party. On June 4, as Chinese tanks
                    crushed student-led protests in Beijing, Solidarity delivered a crushing
                    electoral victory. By August 24, ten years after Solidarity emerged on the
                    scene, Tadeusz Mazowiecki became the first non-communist Prime Minister in
                    Eastern Europe.
In Hungary, drastic changes were also under way. The government, already the most
                    liberal of the communist governments, allowed free association and assembly and
                    ordered opening of the country&#8217;s border with the West. In doing so, it provided
                    an avenue to escape for an ever-increasing number of East Germans. The Hungarian
                    Party removed its long-time leader, Janos Kadar, agreed to its own version of
                    the Round Table talks with the opposition, and, on June 16, ceremoniously
                    re-interred Imre Nagy, the reformist communist leader of the 1956 Hungarian
                    Revolution. By October 23, ten months after political reforms began, Hungary
                    adopted a new constitution allowing a multi-party system and competitive
                    elections.
The economic collapse of East Germany led increasing numbers of East Germans to
                    seek to emigrate to the West. Thousands sought refuge in West German embassies
                    in other communist countries, eventually forcing the government to allow them to
                    emigrate via special trains. Visiting Berlin in early October, Gorbachev
                    cautioned the East German leadership of the need to reform, and confided in his
                    advisors that East German leader Erich Honecker had to be replaced. Two weeks
                    later, Honecker was forced to resign, while hundreds of thousands marched in
                    protest throughout major East German cities. On November 9, as the world watched
                    on television, the East German Government announced the opening of all East
                    German borders. In a fluid situation, the Berlin Wall came down when an
                    obviously ill-prepared East German spokesman told reporters that the new travel
                    regulations also applied to Berlin. Before the end of the month, West German
                    Chancellor Helmut Kohl unveiled a plan for reunification of the two
                    Germanies.
As the Wall came down and the fears of a Soviet reaction receded, the dominoes
                    started falling at a quickened pace. In October, riot police arrested hundreds
                    in Prague after an unsanctioned demonstration; only weeks later, hundreds of
                    thousands gathered in Prague to protest the government. Alexander Dubcek, the
                    reformist communist who led the Prague Spring in 1968, made his first public
                    appearance in over two decades. A new, non-communist government took the
                    country&#8217;s reins on December 5, and on December 29, Vaclav Havel, the famed
                    playwright and dissident, was elected President. In Bulgaria, protests lead to
                    the removal of Todor Zhivkov, the long-time leader of the Bulgarian Communist
                    Party, and his replacement with reformist communist, Petar Mladenov. The new
                    government quickly announced that the government would hold free elections in
                    1990.
Only in Romania did the events turn violent. Nicolae Ceausescu, an increasingly
                    idiosyncratic relic of Stalinist times, refused any reforms. On December 17 in
                    Timisoara, the army and police fired into crowds protesting government policies,
                    killing dozens. Protests spread to other cities, with hundreds killed when
                    Ceausescu ordered the violent repression of demonstrations on December 21. By
                    the next day, Ceausescu was forced to flee Bucharest and was arrested by Army
                    units in the countryside. The interim government, led by a reformist communist
                    Ion Iliescu, held a quick mock trial and Ceausescu and his wife were executed on
                    December 25.
By the summer of 1990, all of the former communist regimes of Eastern Europe were
                    replaced by democratically elected governments. In Poland, Hungary, East Germany
                    and Czechoslovakia, newly formed center-right parties took power for the first
                    time since the end of World War II. In Bulgaria and Romania, reformed communists
                    retained control of the governments, but new center-right parties entered
                    Parliaments and became active on the political scene. The course was set for the
                    reintegration of Eastern Europe into Western economic, political, and security
                    frameworks. Writing in his journal on November 10, 1989, Anatoly Chernyaev,
                    foreign policy advisor to Gorbachev noted that the fall of the wall represented
                    &#8220;a shift in the world balance of forces&#8221; and the end of Yalta.
Meeting in Malta on December 2, Bush and Gorbachev &#8220;buried the Cold War at the
                    bottom of the Mediterranean&#8221; as one of Gorbachev&#8217;s staffers later described. In
                    his memoirs, Bush noted that the rapport he built with Gorbachev at that meeting
                    would prove beneficial later on. And while Scowcroft did not yet feel the Cold
                    War was over, he noted that U.S. policy at the time evolved, &#8220;from quietly
                    supporting the transformations to cultivating Soviet acquiescence, even
                    collaboration, in them.&#8221;









Table of Contents


1989&#8211;1992: The Presidency of George H.W.
                    Bush

The End of Apartheid

Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC), 1989

Fall of Communism in Eastern Europe, 1989

The Collapse of the Soviet Union

The Breakup of Yugoslavia, 1990&#8211;1992

Tiananmen Square, 1989

The Gulf War, 1991

The Madrid Conference, 1991

Strategic Arms Reduction Treaties, 1991 and 1993















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/fall-of-communism</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apec</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/collapse-soviet-union</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apartheid</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apec</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/fall-of-communism</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/collapse-soviet-union</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/breakup-yugoslavia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/tiananmen-square</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/gulf-war</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/madrid-conference</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/strategic-arms-reduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/fall-of-communism</id></item>