<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1989-1992

The End of Apartheid






Milestones: 1989&#8211;1992








The End of Apartheid
Apartheid, the Afrikaans name given by the white-ruled South
                        Africa&#8217;s Nationalist Party in 1948 to the country&#8217;s harsh,
                    institutionalized system of racial segregation, came to an end in the early
                    1990s in a series of steps that led to the formation of a democratic government
                    in 1994. Years of violent internal protest, weakening white commitment,
                    international economic and cultural sanctions, economic struggles, and the end
                    of the Cold War brought down white minority rule in Pretoria. U.S. policy toward
                    the regime underwent a gradual but complete transformation that played an
                    important conflicting role in Apartheid&#8217;s initial survival and eventual
                    downfall.

F.W. de Klerk shakes hands with Nelson Mandela at the end of the talks
                        between the Government and anti-apartheid groups to end white-minority rule.
                        (AP Photo/ John Parkin)

Although many of the segregationist policies dated back to the early decades of
                    the twentieth century, it was the election of the Nationalist Party in 1948 that
                    marked the beginning of legalized racism&#8217;s harshest features called Apartheid.
                    The Cold War then was in its early stages. U.S. President Harry Truman&#8217;s
                    foremost foreign policy goal was to limit Soviet expansion. Despite supporting a
                    domestic civil rights agenda to further the rights of black people in the United
                    States, the Truman Administration chose not to protest the anti-communist South
                    African government&#8217;s system of Apartheid in an effort to maintain an ally
                    against the Soviet Union in southern Africa. This set the stage for successive
                    administrations to quietly support the Apartheid regime as a stalwart ally
                    against the spread of communism.
Inside South Africa, riots, boycotts, and protests by black South Africans
                    against white rule had occurred since the inception of independent white rule in
                    1910. Opposition intensified when the Nationalist Party, assuming power in 1948,
                    effectively blocked all legal and non-violent means of political protest by
                    non-whites. The African National Congress (ANC) and its offshoot, the Pan
                    Africanist Congress (PAC), both of which envisioned a vastly different form of
                    government based on majority rule, were outlawed in 1960 and many of its leaders
                    imprisoned. The most famous prisoner was a leader of the ANC, Nelson
                        Mandela, who had become a symbol of the anti-Apartheid struggle.
                    While Mandela and many political prisoners remained incarcerated in South
                    Africa, other anti-Apartheid leaders fled South Africa and set up headquarters
                    in a succession of supportive, independent African countries, including Guinea,
                    Tanzania, Zambia, and neighboring Mozambique where they continued the fight to
                    end Apartheid. It was not until the 1980s, however, that this turmoil
                    effectively cost the South African state significant losses in revenue,
                    security, and international reputation.
The international community had begun to take notice of the brutality of the
                    Apartheid regime after white South African police opened fire on unarmed black
                    protesters in the town of Sharpeville in 1960, killing 69 people and wounding
                    186 others. The United Nations led the call for sanctions against the South
                    African Government. Fearful of losing friends in Africa as de-colonization
                    transformed the continent, powerful members of the Security Council, including
                    Great Britain, France, and the United States, succeeded in watering down the
                    proposals. However, by the late 1970s, grassroots movements in Europe and the
                    United States succeeded in pressuring their governments into imposing economic
                    and cultural sanctions on Pretoria. After the U.S. Congress passed the
                    Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act in 1986, many large multinational companies
                    withdrew from South Africa. By the late 1980s, the South African economy was
                    struggling with the effects of the internal and external boycotts as well as the
                    burden of its military commitment in occupying Namibia.
Defenders of the Apartheid regime, both inside and outside South Africa, had
                    promoted it as a bulwark against communism. However, the end of the Cold War
                    rendered this argument obsolete. South Africa had illegally occupied neighboring
                    Namibia at the end of World War II, and since the mid-1970s, Pretoria had used
                    it as a base to fight the communist party in Angola. The United States had even
                    supported the South African Defense Force&#8217;s efforts in Angola. In the 1980s,
                    hard-line anti-communists in Washington continued to promote relations with the
                    Apartheid government despite economic sanctions levied by the U.S. Congress.
                    However, the relaxation of Cold War tensions led to negotiations to settle the
                    Cold War conflict in Angola. Pretoria&#8217;s economic struggles gave the Apartheid
                    leaders strong incentive to participate. When South Africa reached a
                    multilateral agreement in 1988 to end its occupation of Namibia in return for a
                    Cuban withdrawal from Angola, even the most ardent anti-communists in the United
                    States lost their justification for support of the Apartheid regime.
The effects of the internal unrest and international condemnation led to dramatic
                    changes beginning in 1989. South African Prime Minister P.W.
                        Botha resigned after it became clear that he had lost the faith
                    of the ruling National Party (NP) for his failure to bring order to the country.
                    His successor, F W de Klerk, in a move that surprised
                    observers, announced in his opening address to Parliament in February 1990 that
                    he was lifting the ban on the ANC and other black liberation parties, allowing
                    freedom of the press, and releasing political prisoners. The country waited in
                    anticipation for the release of Nelson Mandela who walked out of prison after 27
                    years on February 11, 1990.
The impact of Mandela&#8217;s release reverberated throughout South Africa and the
                    world. After speaking to throngs of supporters in Cape Town where he pledged to
                    continue the struggle, but advocated peaceful change, Mandela took his message
                    to the international media. He embarked on a world tour culminating in a visit
                    to the United States where he spoke before a joint session of Congress.
After Prime Minister de Klerk agreed to democratic elections for the country, the
                    United States lifted sanctions and increased foreign aid, and many of the U.S.
                    companies who disinvested in the 1980s returned with new investments and joint
                    ventures. In April 1994, Nelson Mandela was elected as
                    South Africa&#8217;s first black president.









Table of Contents


1989&#8211;1992: The Presidency of George H.W.
                    Bush

The End of Apartheid

Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC), 1989

Fall of Communism in Eastern Europe, 1989

The Collapse of the Soviet Union

The Breakup of Yugoslavia, 1990&#8211;1992

Tiananmen Square, 1989

The Gulf War, 1991

The Madrid Conference, 1991

Strategic Arms Reduction Treaties, 1991 and 1993















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apartheid</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apec</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apartheid</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apec</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/fall-of-communism</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/collapse-soviet-union</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/breakup-yugoslavia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/tiananmen-square</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/gulf-war</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/madrid-conference</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/strategic-arms-reduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992/apartheid</id></item>