<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1993-2000

The Oslo Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process






Milestones: 1993&#8211;2000








The Oslo Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process
On September 13, 1993, Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin
                    and Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) Negotiator Mahmoud
                        Abbas signed a Declaration of Principles on Interim
                    Self-Government Arrangements, commonly referred to as the &#8220;Oslo Accord,&#8221; at the
                    White House. Israel accepted the PLO as the representative of the Palestinians,
                    and the PLO renounced terrorism and recognized Israel&#8217;s right to exist in peace.
                    Both sides agreed that a Palestinian Authority (PA) would be established and
                    assume governing responsibilities in the West Bank and Gaza Strip over a
                    five-year period. Then, permanent status talks on the issues of borders,
                    refugees, and Jerusalem would be held. While President Bill
                        Clinton&#8217;s administration played a limited role in bringing the Oslo
                    Accord into being, it would invest vast amounts of time and resources in order
                    to help Israel and the Palestinians implement the agreement. By the time Clinton
                    left office, however, the peace process had run aground, and a new round of
                    Israeli-Palestinian violence had begun. 

President Clinton, Yitzhak Rabin, and Yasir Arafat at the signing ceremony
                        for the Oslo Accord, September 13, 1993. (William J. Clinton Presidential
                        Library)

The Clinton Administration and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process,
                        1993&#8211;1996

The Clinton administration did not initially make Israeli-Palestinian peace a
                    priority. Clinton and his advisors believed that a diplomatic breakthrough on
                    the Israeli-Syrian track would be more likely, and that Israel&#8217;s leaders would
                    find it politically easier to pull back from the Golan Heights than to withdraw
                    from the West Bank. An Israeli-Syrian agreement, they reasoned, would also lead
                    to an Israeli-Lebanese agreement, and help isolate Iraq and Iran, the principal
                    regional opponents of the peace process. U.S. officials were briefed on secret
                    negotiations that the Israelis and Palestinians had begun in Oslo in December
                    1992, but made little effort to get involved in them.
The United States did not play a major role in the negotiations that led to the
                    Israeli-Jordanian peace treaty of October 1994, though Clinton lent his support
                    by hosting King Hussein and Rabin in Washington and urging Congress to forgive
                    Jordan&#8217;s debts. Nor did the United States play a critical part in the
                    negotiations leading up to the May 1994 Cairo Agreement, which finalized
                    Israel&#8217;s withdrawal from most of Gaza and Jericho, or the Taba (or "Oslo II")
                    Agreement of September 1995. The latter agreement divided the West Bank into
                    separate areas under Israeli control, Palestinian control, and Israeli military
                    responsibility with Palestinian civil administration, respectively. Oslo II aslo
                    spelled out provisions for elections, civil/legal affairs, and other bilateral
                    Israeli-Palestinian cooperation on various issues. Since the Oslo Accord did not
                    give the United States monitoring responsibilities, the Clinton administration
                    found itself largely confined to defusing crises and building up the Palestinian
                    Authority with economic aid and security assistance.
On the Israeli-Syrian track, the administration exerted itself more forcefully,
                    but with few results. Clinton, Secretary of State Warren
                        Christopher, and Special Middle East Coordinator Dennis
                        Ross tried to build on Rabin&#8217;s August 1993 promise to withdraw
                    fully from the Golan if Syria agreed to full peace and necessary security
                    arrangements. By 1994, these talks stalled over Israel and Syria&#8217;s different
                    definitions of &#8220;full withdrawal.&#8221; The Syrians insisted that the Israelis should
                    withdraw to the line of &#8220;June 4, 1967,&#8221; when they had controlled a pocket of
                    land on the northeastern shore of the Sea of Galilee, Israel&#8217;s principal source
                    of water. The Israelis wanted to pull back to the 1923 international border,
                    which would have left the Sea of Galilee under their sovereignty. That July,
                    Rabin indicated to Christopher that Israel would withdraw to the June 4 line if
                    Syria met its other needs, paving the way for talks between Israeli and Syrian
                    military officers. However, these negotiations eventually bogged down over
                    whether Israel could retain early warning stations on the Golan, and also became
                    politically controversial in Israel. Rabin thus chose to suspend them until
                    after Israel&#8217;s elections in 1996.
Oslo&#8217;s Collapse, 1996&#8211;2000

In November 1995, Rabin was assassinated by Yigal Amir, an
                    Israeli who opposed the Oslo Accords on religious grounds. Rabin&#8217;s murder was
                    followed by a string of terrorist attacks by Hamas, which undermined support for
                    the Labor Party in Israel&#8217;s May 1996 elections. New Prime Minister
                        Binyamin Netanyahu hailed from the Likud Party, which
                    had historically opposed Palestinian statehood and withdrawal from the occupied
                    territories.
Worried that the peace process might collapse, the Clinton administration
                    involved itself more actively in Israeli-Palestinian negotiations. In January
                    1997, following intensive U.S. mediation, Israel and the PA signed the Hebron
                    Protocol, which provided for the transfer of most of Hebron to Palestinian
                    control. In October 1998, Clinton hosted Netanyahu and Arafat at the Wye River
                    Plantation, where they negotiated an agreement calling for further Israeli
                    withdrawals from the West Bank. Infighting over the implementation of the Wye
                    Memorandum, however, brought down Netanyahu&#8217;s government in January 1999.
In Israel&#8217;s May 1999 elections, the Labor Party&#8217;s Ehud Barak
                    decisively defeated Netanyahu. Barak predicted that he could reach agreements
                    with both Syria and the Palestinians in 12 to 15 months, and pledged to withdraw
                    Israeli troops from southern Lebanon. In September, Barak signed the Sharm
                    al-Shaykh Memorandum with Arafat, which committed both sides to begin permanent
                    status negotiations. An initial round of meetings, however, achieved nothing,
                    and by December the Palestinians suspended talks over settlement-building in the
                    occupied territories. 
Barak then focused on Syria. In January 2000, Israeli, Syrian, and U.S.
                    delegations convened in West Virginia for peace talks. These negotiations
                    foundered when Barak refused to reaffirm Rabin&#8217;s pledge to withdraw to the June
                    4, 1967 line, arguing that none of the concessions offered by the Syrian
                    delegation in return could be considered final, since Syrian President
                        Hafiz al-Asad was not present. A subsequent meeting
                    between Clinton and Asad in Geneva failed to produce an Israeli-Syrian
                    accord.
Barak then withdrew Israeli forces unilaterally from Lebanon and returned to the
                    Palestinian track. At the prime minister&#8217;s insistence, Clinton convened a summit
                    at Camp David in July 2000, where he, Barak, and Arafat attempted to reach a
                    final agreement on the West Bank and the Gaza Strip. Accounts differ as to why
                    Camp David failed, but it is clear that despite additional concessions by Barak,
                    the Israelis and Palestinians remained strongly at odds over borders, Jerusalem,
                    and whether Israel would recognize Palestinian refugees&#8217; &#8220;right of return.&#8221; The
                    summit ended without a settlement; Clinton would blame Arafat for its
                    failure.
On September 28, riots erupted following a visit of Likud Party leader Ariel
                    Sharon to the Temple Mount, and soon escalated into a wave of
                    Israeli-Palestinian violence that became known as the al-Aqsa Intifada. In
                    December 2000, Clinton put forward his own proposals for an Israeli-Palestinian
                    agreement. By this point, however, the president was leaving office, Barak faced
                    electoral defeat, and Israeli-Palestinian violence continued unabated.
Thus, by the end of 2000, the prospect of ending the Arab-Israeli conflict looked
                    more distant than it had eight years earlier. The Clinton administration had
                    helped facilitate Israeli-Jordanian peace and lay the foundations for
                    Palestinian self-rule. More broadly, the negotiations of the 1990s helped
                    Israel, the Palestinians, and Syria break with numerous diplomatic taboos and
                    establish a basis for what a comprehensive Arab-Israeli peace might look like.
                    But a settlement of the Arab-Israeli conflict remained elusive.









Table of Contents


1993&#8211;2000: The Presidency of William J.
                    Clinton

The Evolution of NATO, 1988&#8211;2001

Somalia, 1992&#8211;1993

The War in Bosnia, 1992&#8211;1995

Bill Clinton, Boris Yeltsin, and U.S.-Russian Relations

Denuclearization and the Two Koreas, 1993&#8211;2001

The Oslo Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process

Intervention in Haiti, 1994&#8211;1995















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/oslo</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/two-koreas</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/haiti</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/evolution-of-nato</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/somalia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/bosnia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/clinton-yeltsin</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/two-koreas</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/oslo</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/haiti</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/oslo</id></item>