<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1993-2000

The War in Bosnia, 1992&#8211;1995






Milestones: 1993&#8211;2000








The War in Bosnia, 1992&#8211;1995
In 1991 and 1992, Yugoslavia disintegrated under the pressures of ethnic
                    conflict, economic issues, and the demagoguery of Serbian President Slobodan
                    Milosevic. The secessions of Slovenia and Croatia triggered warfare in both new
                    nations, with the United Nations inserting a peacekeeping force, the U.N.
                    Protective Force (UNPROFOR), in mid-1992 to stabilize the situation. The U.N.
                    further imposed an arms embargo on the region, seeking to dry up the flow of
                    arms to the combatants. Serbian forces executed widespread &#8220;ethnic cleansing&#8221; in
                    occupied areas, creating horrific scenes of refugees and concentration camps
                    that seemed unthinkable in modern Europe.

Bosnia and Herzegovina. (Central Intelligence Agency)

Bosnia&#8217;s declaration of independence from Yugoslavia in 1992 raised the violence
                    to a new level, triggering a war that lasted over three years and exemplified
                    the complexities of the &#8220;post-Cold War&#8221; strategic environment. The population of
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina was comprised of three ethnic groups: Serbian, Croatian, and
                    Muslim. Initially, Croats and Serbs expanded their territorial control at the
                    expense of the Bosnian state, with the Serbs, supported by Serbia and the
                    Yugoslav National Army (JNA), eventually controlling about 70% of
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina. Shifts in territorial control were accompanied by widespread
                    ethnic cleansing.
While the situation in Yugoslavia was a constant subject of discussion at the
                    highest levels of the Bush Administration, President George H. W. Bush and his
                    advisors considered the situation in the Balkans to be primarily a European
                    issue, to be addressed by the European Union. The lack of U.S. response became
                    an issue in the 1992 presidential campaign, as candidate Bill Clinton advocated
                    a &#8220;lift and strike&#8221; policy&#8212;lifting the arms embargo, which was operating at the
                    disadvantage of the Bosnian Muslims and Croats, and conducting airstrikes
                    against Bosnian Serb forces.
Following Clinton&#8217;s electoral victory, the new administration set to work quickly
                    with Ambassador to the United Nations Madeleine Albright to shape a more active
                    U.N. role in the conflict. In early January 1993, during the final days of the
                    Bush Administration, the United Nations and the European Union had agreed upon
                    the Vance-Owen Peace Plan (VOPP) for Bosnia. A month later, the U.N. Security
                    Council established a war crimes tribunal for the former Yugoslavia and the
                    United States initiated night airdrops of food to the Muslim enclaves. By March
                    the U.N. authorized enforcement of a no-fly zone in Bosnia, implemented by the
                    United States Air Force in Operation Deny Flight, the first armed engagement of
                    U.S. forces in the former Yugoslavia. Following the Bosnian Serbs&#8217; rejection of
                    VOPP, the U.N. declared the Muslim enclaves of Sarajevo, Bihac, Tusla,
                    Srebrenica, Zepa, and Gorazde to be &#8220;safe areas.&#8221; The Security Council did not,
                    however, provide for the defense of these areas.
On May 1 President Clinton sent Secretary of State Warren Christopher to consult
                    with the major NATO allies and with Russia in order to gain support for the
                    &#8220;lift and strike&#8221; strategy. This effort failed, exposing issues that would
                    hamstring NATO&#8217;s actions in the conflict for another two years. Alliance members
                    participating in UNPROFOR were concerned that their troops, lightly armed and
                    widely dispersed, were likely to be taken as hostages and did not share
                    Washington&#8217;s enthusiasm for an air campaign. Wide divergence between the
                    alliance&#8217;s national perspectives on the conflict and very little European
                    domestic support for armed intervention added to the Administration&#8217;s problems.
                    NATO&#8217;s inability to reach consensus on an effective response to the atrocities
                    called into question the future of the alliance in post-Cold War Europe.
Gridlock in the alliance was mirrored by gridlock in the U.S. interagency policy
                    process. The Department of Defense was very reluctant to commit to a role in the
                    Balkans, concerned as it was about a protracted occupation or guerrilla warfare.
                    Ambassador Albright was active in promoting a western response but she had
                    little influence on the overall administration policy. There was also little
                    domestic support in the United States for intervention in the Balkans, though
                    the violence, documented by cable television news, kept the issue in the public
                    eye.
In June 1993, Serb attacks on the Srebrenica &#8220;safe area&#8221; led the U.N. Security
                    Council to authorize the use of air power &#8220;to support UNPROFOR in the
                    performance of its mandate.&#8221; The resolution established a &#8220;dual key&#8221; arrangement
                    between the U.N. and NATO in control of tactical air power responding to Serbian
                    attacks. This arrangement proved difficult for Washington, as the U.N. was
                    extremely reluctant to authorize any effective combat action on the part of
                    NATO.
On February 5, 1994, a mortar shell exploded in the Markala marketplace in
                    Sarajevo, killing 69 civilians. The attack led to the declaration of a
                    20-kilometer weapons exclusion zone around Sarajevo. A confrontation with the
                    Bosnian Serb forces was averted through Russian mediation.
In early April, Bosnian Serb forces launched an offensive against Gorazde.
                    Following the killing of a UNPROFOR soldier by Serbian artillery, NATO launched
                    an air strike. In turn, Bosnian Serbs surrounded a contingent of UNPROFOR
                    soldiers, and their commander, Ratko Mladic, threatened that none would survive
                    if NATO repeated the air attacks. In the immediate aftermath, the United States
                    led the formation of a Contact Group to spearhead policy toward the conflict.
                    The group agreed on a set of principles for any peace settlement: Bosnia would
                    remain a single state, comprised of the Muslim-Croat federation and a Serb
                    entity, and these entities would be linked by constitutionally-agreed
                    principles. The group further agreed to a map of Bosnia-Herzegovina where the
                    Muslim-Croat federation controlled 51 percent of the territory and the Serbian
                    entity controlled 49 percent. While the Bosnian Croats and Muslim groups signed
                    a cease fire between their forces under the terms of the 1994 Washington
                    Agreement, the Bosnian Serbs rejected the plan. The military balance also began
                    to equalize, as Serbia cut off support to Bosnian-Serb forces while Croatia and
                    Bosnian-Muslim forces built up via an increasingly porous arms embargo. The year
                    closed with a four-month truce negotiated by former President Jimmy Carter.
The spring of 1995 brought renewed combat, with Muslim and Croatian forces now on
                    the offensive in western Bosnia-Herzegovina. Without logistical support from
                    Serbia, Bosnian Serb forces retook U.N.-secured weapons, brushing aside UNPROFOR
                    guards. When NATO responded with air strikes, the Serbs took UNPROFOR troops
                    hostage, using them as human shields. NATO deployed a combat-ready Rapid
                    Reaction Force to Bosnia to reduce the vulnerability of the widely scattered
                    UNPROFOR units.
In July, the Bosnian Serb commanders launched an offensive against the eastern
                    enclaves of Srebrenica and Zepa; they massacred over 7,000 men in Srebrenica.
                    The mass killing served as a tipping point to western resolve to bring a
                    decisive end to the conflict. Convening in London on July 21, NATO agreed on the
                    effective end of the &#8220;dual key&#8221; policy for controlling air strikes, with
                    authority for strikes delegated to UNPROFOR and NATO commanders in the field.
                    The alliance further agreed that any future attacks on safe areas would result
                    in a sustained air offensive.
On August 1, Croatian and Bosnian forces launched a powerful offensive, Operation
                    Storm, against Bosnian Serb-held territory in western Bosnia. The offensive
                    rolled eastward, displacing many thousands of Serb refugees and steadily moving
                    the territorial balance toward the 51/49 balance called for by the Contact
                    Group. The new Assistant Secretary of State for Western Europe, Richard
                    Holbrooke, had seized a major role in policy toward the Balkans, and sought to
                    orchestrate a cease-fire and negotiated settlement. When a mortar shell exploded
                    in the Markala marketplace in Sarajevo on August 25, NATO executed Operation
                    Deliberate Force, an intense two-week series of attacks on Serb military
                    positions.
The combination of the ground offensive, NATO&#8217;s air campaign, and Holbrooke&#8217;s
                    tireless diplomacy yielded a cease-fire by the end of September. On November 1,
                    negotiations among the three parties opened at Dayton AFB, OH. The parties
                    reached a hard-fought agreement on November 21 and the Dayton Accords, formally
                    the General Framework Agreement for Peace in Bosnia and Herzegovina, were signed
                    in Paris on December 14. The NATO-led Implementation Force (IFOR) deployed into
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina on December 20.









Table of Contents


1993&#8211;2000: The Presidency of William J.
                    Clinton

The Evolution of NATO, 1988&#8211;2001

Somalia, 1992&#8211;1993

The War in Bosnia, 1992&#8211;1995

Bill Clinton, Boris Yeltsin, and U.S.-Russian Relations

Denuclearization and the Two Koreas, 1993&#8211;2001

The Oslo Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process

Intervention in Haiti, 1994&#8211;1995















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/bosnia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/somalia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/clinton-yeltsin</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/evolution-of-nato</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/somalia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/bosnia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/clinton-yeltsin</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/two-koreas</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/oslo</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/haiti</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/bosnia</id></item>