<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Milestones

1993-2000

The Evolution of NATO, 1988&#8211;2001






Milestones: 1993&#8211;2000








The Evolution of NATO, 1988&#8211;2001
The North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) was born at the outset of the Cold
                    War, designed to meet three complementary objectives: deter Soviet expansionism,
                    prevent the revival of nationalist militarism in Europe through a strong North
                    American presence on the continent, and encourage European political
                    integration. Its core function lay in the collective defense of Central and
                    Western Europe against a Soviet attack. The end of the Cold War and the
                    disintegration of the Soviet Union forced the organization and its member states
                    to adapt to a new security environment. This evolution has played out over a
                    protracted series of decisions addressing a series of complex and interrelated
                    issues: the Alliance&#8217;s mission in the post-Cold War setting, and the related
                    questions of its force structure, command structure, and decision making
                    processes; NATO&#8217;s composition; and its role in the complex system of
                    interlocking European institutions.

U.S. Army forces cross the Sava River during their deployment into
                        Bosnia-Herzegovina as part of Operation Joint Endeavor, 31 December 1995.
                        (Department of Defense/Senior Airman Edward Littlejohn)

This process began in the late 1980s, as Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev
                    instituted a sweeping series of reforms in the Soviet Union. Gorbachev
                    considered it imperative to reduce the proportion of the Soviet economy devoted
                    to defense spending. That objective quickly manifested itself in a new openness
                    toward arms control, and eventually led to a dramatic reduction of Soviet forces
                    in Eastern Europe and abandonment of the Brezhnev Doctrine. The subsequent
                    collapse of the Warsaw Pact and the reunification of Germany ended the threat of
                    Soviet-led invasion that had been the centerpiece of NATO&#8217;s defense posture
                    since its foundation.
Wary of Soviet intentions and aware of the possibility of a reversal of these
                    reforms, policymakers in the West responded cautiously to Gorbachev and his
                    calls for a &#8220;common European home.&#8221; NATO&#8217;s first formal response to the changes
                    in the security environment came in July 1990, with the &#8220;London Declaration on a
                    Transformed North Atlantic Alliance.&#8221; Acknowledging the changes in the Soviet
                    Union, NATO&#8217;s heads of state agreed on changes to force structure and nuclear
                    posture, directed the Alliance to prepare a new strategic concept and an
                    accompanying defense strategy, and emphasized the importance of the Conference
                    on Security and Cooperation in Europe (CSCE)&#8217;s role in the emerging European
                    security architecture. The London Declaration closed, &#8220;Today, our Alliance
                    begins a major transformation. Working with all the countries of Europe, we are
                    determined to create enduring peace on this continent.&#8221;
Alliance leaders meeting at the Rome Summit in November 1991 approved a new
                    Strategic Concept outlining NATO&#8217;s purpose and missions in the new Europe. The
                    &#8220;Rome Declaration on Peace and Cooperation&#8221; emphasized the importance of NATO&#8217;s
                    traditional collective defense mission, calling for &#8220;smaller and more flexible&#8221;
                    forces. The Concept outlined NATO&#8217;s purpose in providing a &#8220;stable security
                    environment in Europe,&#8221; a decision that committed the Alliance to sustaining the
                    stability within NATO and areas on its periphery. The Strategic Concept
                    projected NATO&#8217;s place in the emerging strategic architecture in Europe, with
                    the maturation of the European Union, an expanded role for the CSCE, and
                    construction of the North Atlantic Cooperation Council as a consultative
                    mechanism for NATO and its former adversaries. The Rome Declaration &#8220;welcomed
                    the development of a European security and defence role, reflected in the
                    further strengthening of the European pillar within the Alliance.&#8221;
This program for transformation and new capacity was tested immediately. NATO
                    faced instability on its doorstep with the disintegration of Yugoslavia. The
                    conflict in Bosnia-Herzegovina placed severe stress on the Alliance, as its
                    members struggled to reach a common perspective and an effective response to
                    this complex and vicious war. The Alliance committed forces toward limiting the
                    war, enforcing the arms embargo in Operation Sharp Guard and the no-fly zone
                    through Operation Deny Flight. The Alliance&#8217;s involvement increased gradually
                    until September 1995, when NATO air attacks against Bosnian Serb forces in
                    Operation Deliberate Force were among the key factors in enabling the peace
                    talks at Dayton that yielded a negotiated settlement to the war. NATO forces
                    then executed the postwar peacekeeping and stabilization mission in Operation
                    Joint Endeavor.
The Brussels Summit in January 1994 continued the progressive elaboration of the
                    Alliance&#8217;s role in the new Europe, strongly supporting the maturation of the
                    European Security and Defence Identity and confirming the willingness of NATO to
                    &#8220;make collective assets of the Alliance available in operations of the Western
                    European Union.&#8221; The Brussels Declaration called for the adaptation of the
                    Alliance&#8217;s command and control structures to provide for Combined Joint Task
                    Forces, as a flexible &#8220;means to facilitate contingency operations, including
                    operations with participating nations outside the Alliance.&#8221; Most significantly,
                    the Brussels Summit addressed the issue of enlargement&#8212;reconfirming that the
                    Alliance remained open to NATO expansion, and establishing the Partnership for
                    Peace (PfP) to strengthen practical working relations between the Alliance and
                    participating nations from across the CSCE. The Partnership, expected to &#8220;play
                    an important role in the evolutionary process of the expansion of NATO,&#8221; began
                    operations that same year.
NATO enlargement was widely debated through the mid-1990s, as policymakers and
                    analysts explored its implications, costs, and likely results. NATO conducted a
                    study of enlargement and established general criteria for new members in
                    September 1995. In December 1996, the Alliance announced its decision to invite
                    new members the following July in a summit to be held in Madrid. The major
                    concern was the effect of enlargement on Russia, with fear that an expansion of
                    NATO to the east would threaten its fragile democracy and any prospects of
                    future cooperation between Russia and the Western democracies. President Bill
                    Clinton addressed that issue with Russia&#8217;s President Boris Yeltsin in a March
                    1997 summit conducted in Helsinki. There the leaders agreed to disagree on
                    NATO&#8217;s enlargement, but pledged stronger consultation and, where possible, joint
                    decision making in security issues between NATO and Russia. Two months later
                    Yeltsin signed the &#8220;Founding Act on Mutual Relations, Cooperation, and Security
                    between NATO and the Russian Federation,&#8221; which established the NATO-Russia
                    Permanent Joint Council. With Russia&#8217;s concerns somewhat mollified, NATO invited
                    the Czech Republic, Poland, and Hungary to join the Alliance, projecting an
                    accession date in 1999.
Much work remained, both within the Alliance and across the broader landscape of
                    European security, but this first decade of post-Cold War adaptation established
                    the broad scope of adaptation for NATO. The Alliance had begun its internal
                    transformation, accepted and executed its new missions, recast its relationship
                    with its former adversaries, and begun its enlargement. In doing so, NATO
                    confirmed its utility in the new security environment and its capacity for
                    further change as considered necessary by its member states.









Table of Contents


1993&#8211;2000: The Presidency of William J.
                    Clinton

The Evolution of NATO, 1988&#8211;2001

Somalia, 1992&#8211;1993

The War in Bosnia, 1992&#8211;1995

Bill Clinton, Boris Yeltsin, and U.S.-Russian Relations

Denuclearization and the Two Koreas, 1993&#8211;2001

The Oslo Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process

Intervention in Haiti, 1994&#8211;1995















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov//about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about</value><value>https://history.state.gov//tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov//conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov//developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov//education</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//open</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/evolution-of-nato</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/somalia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/foreword</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/evolution-of-nato</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/somalia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/bosnia</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/clinton-yeltsin</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/two-koreas</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/oslo</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/haiti</value><value>https://history.state.gov//</value><value>https://history.state.gov//search</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov//about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.gov/http://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/mailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//milestones/1993-2000/evolution-of-nato</id></item>