<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
b"<item><bodyText>\n\n\n\n\n\nForeign Relations of the United States\n\n\nHome\nSearch\nBrowse\nCopyright\nHelp\nUWDC\n\n\n\n\nDisplay:\n\nGallery view\nPage image\nPDF of section (565.5 MB) \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Contents&#160;\n&#160;Section&#160;\n&#160;Page&#160;\n&#160;\n\n\n\n\nPage View\nUnited States Department of State / Foreign relations of the United States : diplomatic papers, 1945. General : the United Nations\n\t\t\t(1945)\n\n The United Nations conference on international organization, San Francisco, California, April 25-June 26, 1945,&#160;&#160; pp. 1-1432\n\t\t\t\n PDF (565.5 MB) \n\n\n\nPage 88\n\n\nFOREIGN RELATIONS, 1945, VOLUME I\nheld with the Government of China and the Provisional Government\nof France with respect to (a) the text of the proposals on voting pro-\ncedure in the Security Council of the general international organiza-\ntion proposed at the Dumbarton Oaks Conference, and (b) their\njoining the Governments of the United States, Great Britain, and\nthe Soviet Union in sponsoring invitations to a conference of United\nNations to be called to meet in San Francisco on April 25, 1945. While\nthe Government of China has accepted the text of the voting procedure\nand has agreed to join in sponsoring invitations to the San Francisco\nConference the Provisional Government of France, despite earnest\nand repeated representations from this Government on behalf of all\nthree Governments participating in the Crimea Conference, has so\nfar not indicated its agreement.\n  2. The Government of the United States believes that while the\nProvisional Government of France should be allowed some further\ntime to consider the invitation to act as a joint sponsor at the San\nFrancisco Conference and to concur in the proposals on voting pro-\ncedure, there is, however, urgent need for making the text of the voting\nproposals public and for giving the United Nations as much time as\npossible to prepare for the Conference. Furthermore, in view of the\nfact that the French Provisional Government has had since February\n12 to consider this matter, it would seem that the procedure regarding\nconsultation agreed on at the Crimea Conference has in fact been\ncarried out. Therefore, this Government proposes for the concur-\nrence of the Governments of Great Britain, Soviet Union and China\nthat it issue the invitations to the Conference on behalf of itself and\nthe other three governments on March 1 at 12 o'clock noon, Washing-\nton time, the text of the invitations to be made public at that time\nsimultaneously by the four governments in Washington, London, Mos-\ncow and Chungking. Representatives of the Government of the\nUnited States will be instructed to present the invitations formally\nt o the Foreign Ministers of each of the United Nations in their re-\nspective capitals at that time. This date is selected since it was agreed\nat the Crimea Conference that invitations are to be issued to those\nnations which were signatories to the United Nations Declaration on\nFebruary 8, 1945 and those associated nations, including Turkey,\nwhich will have declared war by March 1.\n  3. In the event that the Provisional Government of France agrees\n(a) with the proposals on voting procedure in the Security Council,\nand (b) to join in sponsoring the invitations to the San Francisco\nConference by February 28 at 12 o'clock noon, Washington time, the\nProvisional Government of France would be included as one of the\nfive governments sponsoring the invitations and would join in the\nsimultaneous release on March 1 referred to in the preceding para-\ngraph. On the other hand, if the Provisional Government does not\nindicate its agreement by February 28 at 12 o'clock noon, Washington\ntime, then an invitation to the Conference will, of course, be issued\nto it as one of the United Nations.\n  4. The agreed text of the invitations to be issued is contained in\nthe telegram immediately following along with the list of the United\nNations to which it will subsequently be issued. In the event that\nthe Governments of Egypt, Iceland, Uruguay, and Turkey declare\nwar by March 1, invitations will also be issued to them. The same con-\n88\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Top of Page\n\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Contents&#160;\n&#160;Section&#160;\n&#160;Page&#160;\n&#160;\n\n\nAs a work of the United States government, this material is in the public domain.| For information on re-use see: http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/Copyright\n\n\nContent/Navigation Questions\nTechnical Assistance\nUniversity of Wisconsin Digital Collections\nAccessibility Information\n\n\n \n&#169; This compilation (including design, introductory text, organization, and descriptive material) is copyrighted by University of Wisconsin System Board of Regents.\nThis </bodyText><pdf><value>http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1945v01/reference/frus.frus1945v01.i0008.pdf</value><value>http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1945v01/reference/frus.frus1945v01.i0008.pdf</value></pdf><name /><urls><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Search.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Browse.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Copyright.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Help.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;isize=S</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;isize=M</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;isize=L</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;isize=XL</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=gallery&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;posn=curr&amp;curr=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;isize=M</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1945v01/reference/frus.frus1945v01.i0008.pdf</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.i0007&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.i0009&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0063&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0149&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0151&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1945v01/reference/frus.frus1945v01.i0008.pdf</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.i0007&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.i0009&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0063&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0149&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0151&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</value></urls><id>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1945v01.p0150&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1945v01&amp;isize=text</id></item>"