<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
b'<item><bodyText>\n\n\n\n\n\nForeign Relations of the United States\n\n\nHome\nSearch\nBrowse\nCopyright\nHelp\nUWDC\n\n\n\n\nDisplay:\n\nGallery view\nPage image\nPDF of section (86.4 MB) \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Contents&#160;\n&#160;Section&#160;\n&#160;Page&#160;\n&#160;\n\n\n\n\nPage View\nUnited States Department of State / Foreign relations of the United States. Conference at Quebec, 1944\n\t\t\t(1944)\n\n Substantive preparatory papers,&#160;&#160; pp. 48-278\n\t\t\t\n PDF (86.4 MB) \n\n\n\nPage 116\n\n\nTHE SECOND QUEBEC CONFERENCE\nfinancial data required for the determination of expenditures arising\nout of operations or activities involving participation of Allied Mili-\ntary forces.\n  a. Insofar as operations relate to the provision of currencies for the\npay and other cash requirements of military components of the Allied\nforces, the Financial Division will supply Allied Military marks from\ncurrency on hand and will record the debit against the military force\nconcerned at the rate of exchange prescribed in paragraph 4 above.\n  b. Insofar as operations relate to the provision of currencies for\ncivil administration, the Finance Division will supply Allied Military\nmarks from currency on hand and will record the debit against the\nAllied Military (overnment.\n  C. If found practicable and desirable, you will designate, under\ndirect military control and supervision, the Reichsbank, or any branch\nthereof, or any other bank satisfactory to you, as agent for the Finan-\ncial Division of the Civil Affairs Section. When satisfied that the\nReichsbank, or any branch thereof, or other designated bank, is under\nadequate military control and supervision, you may use that bank for\nofficial business, and, if necessary, by making credits available, place\nsuch bank or banks in a position to finance other banks and branches\nthereof, for the conduct of their business as approved by the Allied\nMilitary authorities.\n  d. The records of the Financial Division of the Civil Affairs Section\nestablished within the area will indicate in all cases in what currency\nreceipts were obtained or disbursements male rby the Financial\nDivision.\n  i6. You will take the following steps and will put into effect only\nsuch further financial measures as you may deem to be necessary from\na strictly military standpoint:\n  a. You will declare a general or limited moratorium if you deem\nsuch measure to be necessary. In particular, it may prove desirable to\nprevent foreclosures of mortgages and the exercise of similar remedies\nby creditors against individclllls and small business enterprises.\n  b. Banks should be placed under such control as deemed necessary\nby you in order that adequate facilities for military needs may be pro-\nvided and to insure that instructions and regulations issued by mili-\ntary authorities will be fully complied with. Banks should be closed\nonly long enough to introduce satisfactory control, to remove Nazi\nelements and other objectionable personnel, and to issue instructions\nfor the determination of accounts to be blocked under paragraph e\nbelow. As soon as practicable, banks should be required to file reports\nlisting assets, liabilities, and all accounts in excess of 25,000 narks.\n  c. You will issue regulations prescribing the purposes for which\ncredit may be extended and the terms and conditions governing the\nextension of credit. If banking facilities are not available you may\nestablish such credits or make such loans as you deem necessary for\nessential economic activities. These will be restricted to mark credits\nand loans.\n  d. You will close all stock exchanges and similar financial institu-\ntions for such period as you deem desirable.\n  e. Pending determination of future disposition, all gold, foreign\ncurrencies, foreign securities, accounts in financial institutions, credits,\n116\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Top of Page\n\n\n\n\n\n&#160;Contents&#160;\n&#160;Section&#160;\n&#160;Page&#160;\n&#160;\n\n\nAs a work of the United States government, this material is in the public domain.| For information on re-use see: http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/Copyright\n\n\nContent/Navigation Questions\nTechnical Assistance\nUniversity of Wisconsin Digital Collections\nAccessibility Information\n\n\n \n&#169; This compilation (including design, introductory text, organization, and descriptive material) is copyrighted by University of Wisconsin System Board of Regents.\nThis </bodyText><pdf><value>http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value><value>http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value></pdf><name /><urls><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Search.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Browse.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Copyright.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Help.html</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;isize=S</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;isize=M</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;isize=L</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;isize=XL</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=gallery&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;posn=curr&amp;curr=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;isize=M</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0009&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0011&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0102&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0171&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0173&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduhttp://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1944/reference/frus.frus1944.i0010.pdf</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0009&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=div&amp;did=FRUS.FRUS1944.i0011&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0102&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0171&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0173&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</value></urls><id>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1944.p0172&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944&amp;isize=text</id></item>'