<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic Papers,
                    1945, General: The United Nations, Volume I

Introductory note






Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic Papers,
                    1945, General: The United Nations, Volume I








Introductory note
AMERICAN FOREIGN POLICY: SELECTED PUBLIC DOCUMENTS
Beginning with the year 1950, American Foreign Policy, a
                    companion series to Foreign Relations of the United
                        States, provides systematic coverage of the principal messages,
                    addresses, statements, reports, and of certain of the diplomatic notes exchanged
                    and treaties made in a given period that indicate the scope, goals, and
                    implementation of the foreign policy of the United States. For the immediately
                    preceding years, 1945&#8211;1949 inclusive, the present series, Foreign Relations, will provide under this heading a brief indication
                    of certain major documents in these categories. This listing does not purport to
                    be complete, of course, and as a rule items dealing primarily with United States
                    relations with particular countries will be noted in the compilations for those
                    countries. Many of the items cited below are also referred to in appropriate
                    compilations in the various volumes for the year.
I. Major Public Statements of American Foreign
                        Policy

The State of the Union: Annual Message of the President
                        (Roosevelt) to the Congress, January 6, 1945. The
                    portions of the address dealing with foreign affairs are printed in the
                    Department of State Bulletin (hereinafter cited as Bulletin), January 7, 1945, pp. 22&#8211;28. The complete text
                    is printed as House Document 1, 79th Congress.
America&#8217;s Place in World Affairs: Address by the Under Secretary
                    of State (Grew) at the New York Times
                    Hall, New York, January 17, 1945. Bulletin, January 21,
                    1945, pp. 87&#8211;90.
Report on the Crimean (Yalta) Conference: Message delivered by
                    the President (Roosevelt) before a joint session of the
                    Congress, March 1, 1945. Bulletin, March 4, 1945, pp.
                    321&#8211;326, 361.
Statement by the Secretary of State (Stettinius) Upon Return From Conferences in
                    the Crimea and at Mexico City, March 10, 1945. Bulletin,
                    March 11, 1945, pp. 393&#8211;394.
United Nations Will Write Charter for a World Organization:
                    Address by the Secretary of State (Stettinius) before the Council on Foreign Relations at New York,
                    April 6, 1945. Ibid., April 8, 1945, pp. 605&#8211;607.
The Economic Basis for Lasting Peace: Address by the Secretary
                    of State (Stettinius), April 4, 1945.
                        Ibid., pp. 598&#8211;599.
Address by the President (Truman) before a
                    joint session of the Congress, April 16, 1945. Address delivered on the day
                    following the funeral of President Roosevelt. Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                            Harry S. Truman, April 12 to December 81, 1945
                    (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1961), pp. 1&#8211;6. For text of a
                    Proclamation by President [Page VIII]Truman, and for other statements relating to the
                    death of President Roosevelt, see Bulletin, issue of April 15, 1945.
Address by the President (Truman) to the
                    United Nations Conference in San Francisco, April 25, 1945. Delivered from the
                    White House by direct wire. Public Papers of the Presidents of
                        the United States: Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp.
                    20&#8211;23.
Unconditional Surrender of Germany: Radio Address by the
                    President (Truman), May 8, 1945, with related statements
                    and a Proclamation. Bulletin, May 13, 1945, pp.
                    885&#8211;889.
Report on the San Francisco Conference: Address by the Secretary
                    of State (Stettinius), broadcast May 28,
                    1945. Ibid., June 3, 1945, pp. 1007&#8211;1013.
Special Message of the President (Truman)
                    to the Congress on Winning the War With Japan: Message read before the Senate
                    and the House of Representatives on June 1, 1945. Ibid.,
                    pp. 999&#8211;1006.
Letter from the President (Truman) to the
                    Speaker of the House of Representatives on the Defense Aid Program, June 4,
                    1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                            Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp. 102&#8211;103.
Statement by Cordell Hull,
                    Senior Adviser to the United States Delegation to the United Nations Conference.
                    Issued to the press on June 26, 1945, at Bethesda, Maryland. Bulletin, July 1, 1945, pp. 13&#8211;14.
Address by the President (Truman) in San
                    Francisco at the Closing Session of the United Nations Conference, June 26,
                    1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                            Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp. 138&#8211;144.
Address by the President (Truman) Before
                    the Senate Urging Ratification of the Charter of the United Nations, July 2,
                    1945. Ibid., pp. 153&#8211;155.
Statement by the President (Truman)
                    Announcing the Use of the Atomic Bomb at Hiroshima, August 6, 1945. Ibid., pp. 197&#8211;200.
Radio Report by the President (Truman) to
                    the American People on the Potsdam Conference, August 9, 1945. Delivered from
                    the White House. Ibid., pp. 205&#8211;214.
Radio Address by the President (Truman) to
                    the American People After the Signing of the Terms of Unconditional Surrender by
                    Japan, September 1, 1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of
                        the United States: Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp.
                    254&#8211;257.
Special Message of the President (Truman)
                    to the Congress on Atomic Energy, October 3, 1945. Ibid.,
                    pp. 362&#8211;366.
Report on First Session of the Council of Foreign Ministers:
                    Address by the Secretary of State (Byrnes), October 5,
                    1945. Radio broadcast from Washington. Bulletin, October
                    7, 1945, pp. 507&#8211;512. Statement by the Secretary of State
                        (Byrnes) on the Meetings of the Council of Foreign
                    Ministers, London, October 2, 1945. Released to the press on October 3. Ibid., p. 513.
Restatement of Foreign Policy of the United States: Address by
                    the President (Truman), October 27, 1945. Delivered in
                    Central Park, New York, in connection with the celebration of Navy Day. Bulletin, October 28, 1945, pp. 653&#8211;656.
Neighboring Nations in One World: Address by the Secretary of
                    State (Byrnes), New York, October 31, 1945. Ibid., November 4, 1945, pp. 709&#8211;711.
World Cooperation: Address by the Secretary of State
                        (Byrnes), Charleston, South Carolina, November 18,
                    1945. Ibid., November 18, 1945, pp. 783&#8211;786.
America&#8217;s Policy in China: Statement by the Secretary of State
                        (Byrnes) on December 7, 1945, before the Senate
                    Committee on Foreign Relations, answering charges made by Patrick J.
                        Hurley, former Ambassador to China, against the Department of
                    State and the Foreign Service. Ibid., December 9, [Page IX]1945, pp. 930&#8211;933. See also Mr.
                        Byrnes&#8217; statement at a news conference on November 28,
                        ibid., December 2, 1945, pp. 882&#8211;883.
United States Policy Toward China: Statement by the President
                        (Truman), released to the press by the White House on
                    December 16, 1945. Bulletin, December 16, 1945, pp.
                    945&#8211;946.
Special Message of the President (Truman)
                    to the Congress Recommending the Establishment of a Department of National
                    Defense, December 19, 1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of
                        the United States: Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp.
                    546&#8211;560.
Statement and Directive by the President
                        (Truman) on Immigration to the United States of Certain
                    Displaced Persons and Refugees in Europe, December 22, 1945. Ibid., pp. 572&#8211;578.
II. The Implementation of American Foreign
                        Policy

a. the organization and activities of the
                        department of state

A chart showing the organization of the Department as of May 1, 1945, is printed
                    in the Bulletin, May 13, 1945, pp. 898&#8211;899.
The resignation of Edward R. Stettinius,
                        Jr., as Secretary of State was accepted by President
                        Truman on June 27; for texts of a letter by the
                    President and a statement by Mr. Stettinius on accepting appointment as Representative of the
                    United States to the United Nations, both dated June 27, 1945, see ibid., July 1, 1945, pp. 15&#8211;16.
Arrangements for recruitment of commissioned Foreign Service officers from among
                    men and women of the armed forces were announced by the Department on June 29;
                        ibid., pp. 38&#8211;39.
James F. Byrnes, of South Carolina, was commissioned as
                    Secretary of State on July 2 and entered upon duties July 3. For text of remarks
                    by Mr. Byrnes on taking the oath of office at the White
                    House, see ibid., July 8, 1945, p. 45.
For information concerning the representation by the United States of foreign
                    interests, as of July 28, with tables arranged according to countries
                    represented and according to United States diplomatic and consular offices, see
                        ibid., July 29, 1945, pp. 144&#8211;149. For additional
                    information, see William M. Franklin, Protection of Foreign Interests: A Study in Diplomatic and Consular
                        Practice (Department of State publication 2693; 1947).
The resignation of Joseph C. Grew as Under
                    Secretary of State was accepted by President Truman on
                    August 16; for texts of letters by the President, Secretary of State
                        Byrnes, and Mr. Grew, see the Bulletin, August 19, 1945,
                    p. 271.
Dean G. Acheson, of Connecticut, was
                    commissioned Under Secretary of State on August 16 and entered upon duties the
                    same day.
Patrick J. Hurley resigned as Ambassador to China on
                    November 27.
On November 27 the White House announced that the President had appointed General
                    of the Army George C. Marshall as his personal envoy to
                    China with personal rank of Ambassador.[Page X]
The former Secretary of State, Cordell
                    Hull, was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in Oslo on December 10. A
                    message from Mr. Hull, read by
                        Lithgow Osborne, American Ambassador in Norway, to the
                    president and members of the Nobel Committee of the Storting, was issued to the
                    press by the Department of State on December 10, 1945.
For a general discussion of the situation of the Department and the Foreign
                    Service in the immediate postwar period, see &#8220;The Future of the Foreign
                    Service&#8221;, a radio broadcast of December 29, Bulletin,
                    December 30, 1945, pp. 1048&#8211;1054.
b. assignment of additional duties to the
                        department of state

1. International Information.
By Executive Order 9608 (10 Federal Register 11223),
                    August 31, 1945, President Truman provided for the
                    termination of the Office of War Information and the transfer to the Department
                    of State of its international information functions as well as the foreign
                    information functions of the Office of Inter-American Affairs. In a statement
                    released to the press on that date the President noted that &#8220;the nature of
                    present-day foreign relations makes it essential for the United States to
                    maintain informational activities abroad as an integral part of the conduct of
                    our foreign affairs&#8221; (Bulletin, September 2, 1945, pp.
                    306&#8211;307).
For statements on the role of an international information service in the conduct
                    of foreign relations, by William Benton, Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Public Affairs, before the House Committee on Foreign
                    Affairs (on October 16) and the House Appropriations Committee (on October 17),
                    see ibid., October 21, 1945, pp. 589&#8211;595. For text of a
                    radio broadcast by Mr. Benton and others on &#8220;Our
                    International Information Policy&#8221;, December 15, see ibid., December 16, 1945, pp. 947&#8211;954, and for a statement by Mr.
                        Benton, &#8220;Plans for International Information Service&#8221;,
                    released to the press on December 28, see ibid., December
                    30, 1945, pp. 1045&#8211;1047.
On December 31 Secretary of State Byrnes addressed to
                    President Truman a letter describing certain proposals for
                    an overseas information service; for text, see ibid.,
                    January 20, 1946, pp. 57&#8211;58.
2. Research and Intelligence.
President Truman wrote on September 20, 1945, to Secretary
                    of State Byrnes that he had that day signed an Executive
                    Order (No. 9621; 10 Federal Register 12033) transferring
                    to the Department of State the activities of the Research and Analysis Branch
                    and the Presentation Branch of the Office of Strategic Services. The order,
                    effective October 1, abolished the O.S.S. and transferred its remaining
                    activities to the War Department. The President added that the transfer [Page XI]would provide the Secretary of State
                    &#8220;with the resources which we have agreed you will need to aid in the development
                    of our foreign policy, and will assure that pertinent experience accumulated
                    during the war will be preserved and used in meeting the problems of the peace.&#8221;
                    The President further stated that he particularly desired the Secretary of State
                    &#8220;to take the lead in developing a comprehensive and coordinated foreign
                    intelligence program for all Federal agencies concerned with that type of
                    activity &#8230; through the creation of an interdepartmental group, heading up under
                    the State Department, which would formulate plans for my approval.&#8221; For texts of
                    the Executive Order and of the President&#8217;s letters of September 20 to the
                    Secretary of State and to Major General William J. Donovan,
                    Director of the Office of Strategic Services, see the Bulletin, September 22, 1945, pp. 449&#8211;450.
The appointment of Colonel Alfred McCormack as Special
                    Assistant to the Secretary of State in Charge of Research and Intelligence was
                    announced on September 27, 1945 (ibid., September 30,
                    1945, p. 499).
For additional information, see &#8220;A National Intelligence Program&#8221;, a radio
                    broadcast of December 22, ibid., December 23, 1945, pp.
                    987 ff.
3. Foreign Economic Functions, and Functions
                        with Respect to Surplus Property in Foreign Areas.
By Part I of Executive Order 9630, September 27, 1945, President
                        Truman terminated the Foreign Economic Administration
                    (established by Executive Order 9380 of September 25, 1943) and transferred to
                    the Department of State all functions of the F.E.A. and its agencies with
                    respect to: 

&#8220;(a) The administration of the Act of March
                                11, 1941, as amended, entitled &#8216;An Act further to promote the
                                defense of the United States and for other purposes.&#8217;
&#8220;(b) The participation of the United States
                                in the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, as
                                defined in Executive Order No. 9453 of July 6, 1944.
&#8220;(c) Activities in liberated areas with
                                respect to supplying the requirements of and procuring materials in
                                such areas under paragraph 4 of the said Executive Order No.
                                9380.
&#8220;(d) The gathering, analysis, and reporting
                                of economic and commercial information, insofar as such functions
                                are performed abroad.
&#8220;(e) The planning of measures for the
                                control of occupied territories.
&#8220;(f) The administration of Allocation No.
                                42/398 of February 1, 1943 from the appropriation, &#8216;Emergency Fund
                                for the President, National Defense, 1942 and 1943.&#8217;&#8221;


The remaining functions of the F.E.A. were transferred to the Reconstruction
                    Finance Corporation, the Department of Commerce, and the Department of
                    Agriculture.[Page XII]
Part II of Executive Order 9630 assigned to the Department of State additional
                    functions as a disposal agency for all surplus property in foreign areas,
                    excepting certain vessels.
For text of the Executive Order, see 10 Federal Register
                    12245, or Bulletin, September 30, 1945, pp. 491&#8211;492.
c. foreign economic policy&#8212;trade and
                        tariffs

1. Lend-Lease.
Documents relating to Lend-Lease operations in connection with particular
                    countries are printed in the compilations for those countries. On the program as
                    a whole, see:
Proposed Extension of the Lend-Lease Act: Statement by the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional Relations and International
                    Conferences (Acheson), February 8, 1945,
                    before the Committee on Foreign Relations of the House of Representatives. Bulletin, February 11, 1945, p. 189.
Signing of the Third Lend-Lease Act: Statement by the President
                        (Truman), April 17, 1945. Ibid.,
                    April 22, 1945, p. 773.
Current Lend-Lease Problems: Statements by the Acting Secretary
                    of State (Grew), May 14, and the
                    Secretary of State (Stettinius), May 15,
                    1945. Ibid., May 20, 1945, pp. 940&#8211;941.
The President&#8217;s News Conference of May 23, 1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States;
                            Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp. 67&#8211;68.
Lend-Lease Matters: Defense-Aid Appropriation Estimate: Letter
                    from the President (Truman) to the Speaker of the House of
                    Representatives, June 4, transmitting letter of June 1 from the Director of the
                    Bureau of the Budget to the President. Bulletin, June 10,
                    1945, pp. 1061&#8211;1063.
Discontinuance of Lend-Lease Operations: White House press
                    release, August 21, 1945. Ibid., August 26, 1945, p.
                    284.
Statement by the Secretary of State
                    (Byrnes), August 31, 1945. Ibid.,
                    September 2, 1945, pp. 332&#8211;333.
The President&#8217;s News Conference of August 23, 1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                            Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp. 234&#8211;235.
Lend-Lease and Postwar Reconstruction. Section 18 of Special
                    Message of the President (Truman) to the Congress
                    Presenting a 21-Point Program for the Reconversion Period, September 6, 1945.
                        Ibid., pp. 305&#8211;307.
The 19th, 20th, 21st, and 22nd quarterly reports of operations
                    under the Lend-Lease Act transmitted by the President to the Congress, covering
                    the year 1945. House documents 189, 279, 432, and 663, 79th Congress.
2. International Finance.
The Bretton Woods Proposals: International Monetary Fund and
                    International Bank for Reconstruction and Development. Message of the President
                        (Roosevelt) to the Congress, February 12, 1945. Bulletin, February 18, 1945, pp. 220&#8211;222.
International Monetary Fund and International Bank for
                    Reconstruction and Development: Statement by the Assistant Secretary of State
                    for Congressional Relations and International Conferences (Acheson) before the Committee on Banking and
                    Currency of the House of Representatives, March 7, 1945. Bulletin, March 11, 1945, pp. 409&#8211;410.
Bretton Woods: A Monetary Basis for Trade: Address by Mr.
                        Acheson, April 16, 1945. Ibid., April 23, 1945, pp. 738&#8211;742.[Page XIII]
General Policy Statement of the Export-Import Bank of
                    Washington. Released to the press September 11, 1945. Ibid., September 23, 1945, pp. 441&#8211;446.
The Necessity for Foreign Investment: Address by
                        Willard L. Thorp, Deputy to the Assistant Secretary of
                    State for Economic Affairs, at New York, November 20, 1945. Ibid., November 25, 1945, pp. 829&#8211;832.
On December 27 there were signed in the Department of State the Articles of
                    Agreement of the International Monetary Fund and the Articles of Agreement of
                    the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development. Fred M.
                        Vinson, Secretary of the Treasury, signed the two agreements on
                    behalf of the United States. For a description of the ceremony and for text of a
                    statement by Mr. Vinson, see ibid.,
                    December 30, 1945, pp. 1058&#8211;1059.
3. International Trade.
Recommendation for Renewal of Trade Agreements Act: Message of
                    the President (Roosevelt) to the Congress, March 26, 1945.
                        Bulletin, April 1, 1945, pp. 531&#8211;533.
United States Policy Regarding Commodity Agreements: Address by
                    the Director of the Office of International Trade Policy
                        (Haley), at New York, April 5, 1945. Ibid., April 8, 1945, pp. 638&#8211;642.
Renewal of Trade Agreements: Statements by the Secretary of
                    State (Stettinius) and the Assistant
                    Secretaries of State for Economic Affairs (Clayton) and for
                    American Republic Affairs (Rockefeller)
                    before the Ways and Means Committee of the House of Representatives, April 18,
                    1945. Ibid., April 22, 1945, pp. 748&#8211;759. Testimony of
                        Charles P. Taft, Director of the
                    Office of Transport and Communications Policy, May 12, 1945. Ibid., May 13, 1945, pp. 905&#8211;910.
Private Barriers to International Trade: Statement by the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs (Clayton)
                    before a joint session of the Senate special committee investigating petroleum
                    resources and the subcommittee of the Senate Judiciary Committee on S. 11, 79th
                    Congress, May 17, 1945. Ibid., May 20, 1945, pp.
                    933&#8211;938.
Statements by the Acting Secretary of State (Grew) on May 26 and June 20 concerning the
                    approval of the trade-agreements bill by the House of Representatives and the
                    Senate. Ibid., May 27, 1945, p. 955, and June 24, 1945,
                    p. 1149.
Renewal of Trade Agreements Act: Statement by the Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Economic Affairs (Clayton) before
                    the Finance Committee of the Senate, May 30, 1945. Ibid.,
                    June 3, 1945, pp. 1024 ff.
Relaxation of Export Controls: Statement released to the press
                    by the Foreign Economic Administration, September 10, 1945. Ibid., September 16, 1945, pp. 397&#8211;400.
The Future of International Economic Relations: Address by
                        Clair Wilcox, Director of the Office of International
                    Trade Policy, at Milwaukee Wisconsin, November 22, 1945. Ibid., November 25, 1945, pp. 833&#8211;836.
4. Foreign Oil Policies.
Formulation and Implementation of Foreign Oil Policies:
                    Assignment of Petroleum Officers on a Global Basis. Letters exchanged between
                    the Petroleum Administrator for War (Ickes) and the Secretary of State (Byrnes);
                    letters dated September 10 and November 21, respectively. Ibid., December 2, 1945, pp. 894&#8211;895.[Page XIV]
d. foreign war relief activities

Letter from the President (Truman) to the
                    President of the Senate and to the Speaker of the House of Representatives
                    Transmitting Reports on Foreign War Relief Activities, July 17, 1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                            Harry S. Truman 1945, pp. 173&#8211;174. The reports
                    of the American Red Cross and the War Refugee Board and the report on status of
                    appropriations and allocations are printed in House Document 262, 79th
                    Congress.
The Repatriation Program: Statement by the Acting Secretary of
                    State (Grew), August 5, 1945. Bulletin, August 5, 1945, pp. 162&#8211;164.
Letter from the President (Truman) to the
                    Commanding General, United States Forces, European Theater
                        (Eisenhower), Transmitting Report of Earl G.
                        Harrison on Displaced Persons in Europe, Especially in Germany
                    and Austria, August 31, 1945. Ibid., September 30, 1945,
                    pp. 455&#8211;463. Reply by General Eisenhower, October 8, 1945.
                        Ibid., October 21, 1945, pp. 607&#8211;609.
Statement by the President (Truman) on the
                    European Relief and Rehabilitation Program, September 17, 1945. Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                            Harry S. Truman, 1945, pp. 321&#8211;324.
Special Message of the President (Truman)
                    to the Congress on United States Participation in the United Nations Relief and
                    Rehabilitation Administration, November 13, 1945. Ibid.,
                    pp. 464&#8211;467.
Statement by the President (Truman) on the
                    Problem of Jewish Refugees in Europe, November 13, 1945. Ibid., pp. 467&#8211;469.
Letter from the President (Truman) to the
                    British Prime Minister (Attlee)
                    Concerning the Need for Resettlement of Jewish Refugees in Palestine, November
                    13, 1945. Ibid., pp. 469&#8211;470.
Immigration to the United States of Certain Displaced Persons
                    and Refugees in Europe: Statement by the President
                    (Truman), with attached Directive by the President.
                    Released to the press by the White House on December 22. Bulletin, December 23, 1945, pp. 981&#8211;984.
e. report on atrocities and war
                    crimes

Report from Justice Robert H. Jackson,
                    Chief of Counsel for the United States in the Prosecution of Axis War Criminals,
                    to the President (Truman). Released to the press by the
                    White House on June 7, 1945. Bulletin, June 10, 1945, pp.
                    1071&#8211;1078. For additional information, see Report of
                            Robert H. Jackson, United States Representative to
                        the International Conference on Military Trials, London, 1945
                    (Department of State publication 3080; 1949).
f. report on the status of countries in
                        relation to the war

Status of Countries in Relation to the War, August 12, 1945.
                    Compiled by Katherine Elizabeth Crane, Division of Research
                    and Publication. Bulletin, August 12, 1945, pp. 230&#8211;241.
                    Lists countries at war; signatories of the Declaration by United Nations,
                    January 1, 1942, and adherents to the Declaration; signatories to the Charter of
                    the United Nations; and countries in a state of armistice relations and in a
                    state of surrender.











General: The United Nations


Preface

Introductory note

List of papers

Guide to discussions of Dumbarton Oaks proposals and corresponding articles of
                    the Charter of the United Nations, 1944&#8211;1945

The United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco,
                    California, April 25&#8211;June 26, 1945


Efforts of the United States in the Preparatory Commission of the United
                    Nations to effect an early establishment of the United Nations Organization;
                    selection of the United States as the permanent location for the seat of the
                        Organization (Documents 321-359)
Participation by the United States in the establishment of the United Nations
                    Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (Documents 360-374)
Participation by the United States in the sessions of the International Labor
                    Conference and Governing Body (Documents 375-387)
Sponsorship by the Department of State of legislation resulting in the
                    International Organizations Immunities Act of 1945 (Documents 388-393)
Index








Persons

Acheson, Dean
                                    G.Attlee,
                                    Clement R.Grew, Joseph
                                    C.Hull,
                                    CordellIckes, Harold
                                    L.Rockefeller,
                                    Nelson A.Stettinius,
                                    Edward R., Jr.Taft, Charles
                                    P.




Abbreviations &amp; Terms















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov/about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about</value><value>https://history.state.gov/tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov/conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov/education</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov/open</value><value>https://history.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov../frus1945v01</value><value>https://history.state.govintroduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/preface</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/papers</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_VIII</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_IX</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_X</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XI</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XII</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XIII</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XIV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/preface</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/introduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/papers</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/guide</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp3</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp4</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp5</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/index</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_ADG1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_ACR1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_GJC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_HC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_IHL1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_RNA1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_SERJ1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_TCP1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/search</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.govmailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/introduction</id></item>