<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic Papers,
                    1945, General: The United Nations, Volume I

List of papers






Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic Papers,
                    1945, General: The United Nations, Volume I







.document_top {
   vertical-align: top;
}



List of papers
THE UNITED NATIONS CONFERENCE ON INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION, SAN
                    FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA, APRIL 25&#8211;JUNE 26, 1945
Chapter I: January 1&#8211;March 8, 1945


Date
Paper
Page



Introductory Note by the EditorHistorical
                            note; information on Conference structure and documentation; purpose and
                            scope of compilation; List of Persons.
1



1945 Jan. 2
The Secretary of State to Diplomatic Officers in
                                Certain American RepublicsSummary of December 29 meeting
                            of Secretary of State Stettinius
                            with Heads of Mission of American Republics to continue discussions
                            concerning international organization: Dumbarton Oaks Proposals Chapter
                            I, respect for international treaties, juridical equality of nations,
                            respect of territorial integrity.
10



Jan. 7&#8211;23
Extracts From the Diary of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.,
                                Secretary of State, December 1, 1944&#8211;July 3, 1945Notes on
                            Secretary&#8217;s anxiety lest six Latin American &#8220;associated nations&#8221; be
                            excluded from initial participation in the forthcoming UN Conference
                            unless they qualified as United Nations; preparation of policy papers
                            for the President to take to Yalta Conference; and problem of clearing
                            up unsettled issues from the Dumbarton Oaks Conversations, such as the
                            proposed compromise voting formula.
12



Jan. 13
Memorandum of Conversation? by Mr. Leo Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to
                                the Secretary of StateSecond conversation with Ambassador
                                Gromyko on subjects related
                            to the Dumbarton Oaks proposals: Regional arrangements; the ICJ;
                            trusteeships; League of Nations; initial membership; site for UN
                            headquarters; views of Latin American governments; and voting in the
                            Security Council.
14



Jan. 13
Memorandum by Mr. Leo
                                    Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to the Secretary of
                                StateMemorandum for the President regarding forthcoming
                            conversations with Colonel Stanley, British
                            Secretary of State for the Colonies; outline of US and British views on
                            dependent areas; annex, a memorandum on background of recent
                            Departmental work regarding dependent areas.
18



Jan. 17
Mr. Leo
                                    Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to the Secretary of
                                State, to the Counselor of the British Embassy (Wright)Acknowledgement of
                            note informing of British acceptance of the President&#8217;s proposal on
                            voting in the Security Council.
22



Jan. 23
Memorandum by the Secretary of War
                                    (Stimson) to the Secretary of StateViews on
                            international trusteeship.
23



[Page XVI]Jan. 26
Record of Informal Meeting With Diplomatic
                                Representatives of Certain American Republics, Held at Washington,
                                January 26, 1945, 3 p.m.Summary of address by Under
                            Secretary Grew; discussion of
                            Dumbarton Oaks Proposals: II(5), Principles: use of armed forces;
                            VIII,C, Regional Arrangements; III(1), Membership; IV, Principal Organs;
                            V, B, General Assembly: functions and powers and the question of
                            withdrawal of members from the UN.
27



Jan. 27
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)Department&#8217;s comments on points
                            of view expressed in an article by H. Malinin in
                                War and the Working Class on creation of an
                            international security organization.
34



Jan. 30
Policy Papers for President
                                    RooseveltYalta Briefing Book
                            papers: (a) World Security (Mexico City Conference, and discussions with
                            Latin American Ambassadors in Washington); (b) International Court of
                            Justice (provisions of the Proposals and proposed meeting of a UN
                            Committee of Jurists to prepare a draft statute of the court); and (c)
                            Liquidation of the League of Nations (recommendation to leave the
                            question for consideration at the UN Conference).
35



Jan. 31
Record of Informal Meeting With Diplomatic
                                Representatives of Certain American Republics, Held at Washington,
                                January 31, 1945, 3 p.m.Preamble: respect for treaties;
                            VI, A and B, Security Council; VII, ICJ.
39



Feb. 5
Record of Informal Meeting With Diplomatic
                                Representatives of Certain American Republics, Held at Washington,
                                February 5, 1945, 3 p.m.VIII, A, Pacific Settlement of
                            Disputes; VIII, B, Threats to the Peace: enforcement procedures &#8212;
                            diplomatic, economic measures, or action by air, naval or land forces,
                            provision of armed forces to the Council by the UN members, Military
                            Staff Committee; VIII,C, Regional Arrangements; IX, Economic and Social
                            Cooperation.
46



Feb. 5
The Chief of the Division of Eastern European
                                Affairs (Durbrow)
                                to the Chief of the Division of International
                                Organization Affairs (Sandifer)Transmittal of
                            memorandum outlining the Polish Government&#8217;s preliminary views on the
                            Dumbarton Oaks Proposals.
58



Feb. 9
Record of Informal Meeting With Diplomatic
                                Representatives of Certain American Republics, Held at Washington,
                                February 9, 1945, 3 p.m.X, Secretariat; XI, Amendments to
                            the Charter; XII, Transitional Arrangements.
60



Feb. 11
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)Substance of communiqu&#233; to be issued at
                            termination of Yalta Conference announcing (a) agreements on the voting
                            procedure in the Security Council (b) the convening of the UN Conference
                            on April 25, 1945; (c) authorization of the US, the UK, and the USSR to
                            consult on behalf of all three governments the Republic of China and the
                            Provisional Government of France regarding the proposed issuance of [Page XVII]invitations to the Conference
                            on behalf of the UK, the USSR, China, and France; proposed consultation
                            of the five inviting Governments, prior to the conference, on
                            trusteeship.
67



Feb. 11
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary
                                of StateTelegram no. 546 read to the French Ambassador
                                (Bonnet) setting forth plans
                            for the UN Conference; an early reply requested of his
                            Government.
68



Feb. 12
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)Message for Secretary Stettinius concerning the question of
                            Department&#8217;s making public the fact that the voting procedure accepted
                            at Yalta Conference was a US proposal.
69



Feb. 13
Statement Released to the Press by the White House,
                                February 13, 1945List of names of US Delegation to the UN
                            Conference.
70



Feb. 13
Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State
                                (MacLeish)Publicity policy of the Department of
                            State regarding the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals.
70



Feb. 13
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateQuestion of
                            publicizing United States authorship of voting proposal.
71



Feb. 13
Mr. Harry L. Hopkins, Special
                                Assistant to President Roosevelt, to the
                                Director of the Office of War Mobilization and Reconversion
                                    (Byrnes)Question of possible United States request
                            for additional votes in the Assembly to achieve parity for the United
                            States; satisfactory replies received by President
                                Roosevelt from Prime Minister
                                Churchill and Marshal
                                Stalin.
72



Feb. 15
The Minister in Egypt (Tuck) to the
                                Acting Secretary of StateFrance being given 3-day time
                            limit to decide to join as sponsoring power prior to issuance of
                            invitations.
72



Feb. 16
The Acting Secretary of State to the Charge in
                                Brazil (Daniels)Inadvisability of sending invitations
                            before March 1.
73



Feb. 17
The Charg&#233; in Brazil (Daniels) to the
                                Acting Secretary of StateMessage from Secretary Stettinius commenting on a reference
                            to the agreed voting provisions as &#8220;the compromise&#8221; which had been made
                            in the Acting Secretary&#8217;s telegram of February 17.
73



Feb. 19
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                Mexico (Messersmith)Pressure on French Ambassador to
                            hasten response regarding sponsorship.
74



Feb. 20
The Ambassador in Guatemala (Long) to the
                                Acting Secretary of StateDesire of Secretary Stettinius to issue invitations
                            February 21 from the White House and to include invitation in his
                            opening remarks at Mexico City Conference.
75



Feb. 20
The Acting Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltProposed procedure
                            regarding issuance of invitations on March 1.
76



[Page XVIII]Feb. 20
Memorandum of Telephone Conversations, by the Acting
                                Secretary of StateInvitations for UN Conference,
                            announcement of voting procedure; Secretary Stettinius agrees to leave matter to Acting Secretary
                                Grew.
77



Feb. 20
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)Reassurance to France that trusteeship
                            consultations would not deal with specific territories.
80



Feb. 21
The Acting Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltProposed public
                            statement regarding voting procedure
81



Feb. 21
The Ambassador in Mexico (Messersmith) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateSecretary Stettinius&#8217; eagerness to have French
                            response on sponsorship before delivery of his address on February
                            22.
82



Feb. 21
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Acting Secretary of StateExpectation of France to attend
                            United Nations Conference; inquiry concerning relation of Franco-Soviet
                            treaty to the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals.
83



Feb. 22
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                Mexico (Messersmith)Proposed press statement on the
                            question of issuing an invitation to Poland to attend the UN
                            Conference.
83



Feb. 22
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)United States concurrence in
                            British proposal regarding issuance of invitation to Saudi Arabia to
                            attend the UN Conference.
84



Feb. 22
Memorandum by George M. Elsey
                                of the White House Map Room to the Acting Secretary of
                            StatePresident Roosevelt&#8217;s message of
                            February 21 authorizing Acting Secretary Grew to make final decision regarding invitations and
                            release text of voting agreement.
85



Feb. 23
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)Question of Soviet concurrence in
                            proposal regarding Saudi Arabia&#8217;s adherence to United Nations
                            Declaration.
86



Feb. 23
The Acting Secretary of State to the Minister in
                                Iceland (Dreyfus)Iceland required to qualify in same manner
                            as members of United Nations in order to attend the Conference.
86



Feb. 23
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Proposed procedure for issuance of
                            invitations on March 1.
87



Feb. 23
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Text of proposed invitation.
89



Feb. 24
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary
                                of StateFrance willing to act as sponsor with one
                            reservation&#8212;the right to present amendments to the Dumbarton Oaks
                            Proposals for consideration at the Conference.
90



[Page XIX]Feb. 25
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)United States attitude toward French
                            acceptance of invitation to act as sponsor with reservation.
91



Feb. 26
Memorandum by the Chairman of the State&#8211;War&#8211;Navy
                                Coordinating Committee (Dunn) to the
                                Secretary of StateJoint Chiefs of Staff express no
                            objection to proposed discussion of international trusteeships under
                            certain specified conditions.
93



Feb. 26
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateBritish proposal
                            for changed wording of invitation to meet French reservation.
95



Feb. 27
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Text of message from Secretary
                                Stettinius to Mr. Eden insisting on issuance of
                            invitations on March 1 and urging France to join in sponsorship.
96



Feb. 27
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateThird proposal
                            submitted to the French Embassy by the British Foreign Office regarding
                            possibility of issuance by French Government of unilateral statement
                            reserving right to offer amendments to the Dumbarton Oaks
                            Proposals.
97



Feb. 27
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateSoviet approval for
                            issuance of invitations on March 1 in names of United States, United
                            Kingdom, China, and the Soviet Union only.
98



Feb. 28
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateProposed formulae regarding change in
                            text of invitation.
99



Feb. 28
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Postponement of issuance of invitations
                            until completion of consultations with France.
100



Feb. 28
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateApproval by French
                            Cabinet of modification of invitation text and issuance of separate
                            declaration by French Government regarding right to propose amendments
                            to the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals.
100



Feb. 28
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateProposed press statement by Mr.
                                Bidault at time of
                            announcement of French participation in Conference.
101



Feb. 28
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateText of reply from
                            Mr. Eden to Mr. Stettinius&#8217; message of February
                            27.
102



Mar. 2
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateSoviet refusal to
                            agree to proposed modification of text of paragraph 2 of invitation to
                            the Conference.
103



[Page XX]Mar. 2
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)Postponement of issuance of
                            invitations to allow France to present its case directly to the Soviet
                            Government; final plan to issue invitations on March 5 at noon.
103



Mar. 3
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateFrench endeavor to persuade Soviets to
                            change their point of view.
104



Mar. 4
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Plan to deliver invitations March 5
                            without France as a sponsoring Government.
105



Mar. 4
The Acting Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic
                                RepresentativesAnnouncement of anticipated issuance of
                            invitations to the United Nations Conference, for information of nations
                            not invited to attend the Conference.
106



Mar. 5
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateSoviet support of
                            invitation-form worked out in Yalta Conference.
106



Mar. 5
Memorandum of the Acting Secretary&#8217;s Press and Radio
                                News ConferenceBackground statement regarding question of
                            extending invitation to either the London Polish Government or the
                            provisional government functioning in Poland.
108



Mar. 6
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateCommuniqu&#233; released to the press
                            concerning anticipated role of the French in the Conference.
109



Mar. 8
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)Background statement to press regarding
                            France as a sponsoring nation.
110



Mar. 8
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)Background statement to press regarding
                            France as a sponsoring nation.
111



Mar. 8
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Emphasis on the point that no conflict
                            exists between the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals and such regional security
                            arrangements as the Act of Chapultepec and the Soviet-French
                            alliance.
111



Chapter II: March 9&#8211;April 9, 1945


Date
Paper
Page


1945 Mar. 9
The Soviet Embassy to the Department of
                            StateQuestion of inviting to the Conference representatives of
                            the Polish Provisional Government acting in Warsaw.
113



[Page XXI]Mar. 11
The Polish Ambassador (Ciechanowski) to
                                the Secretary of StateAssertion of the Polish Government&#8217;s
                            right to participate in the Conference.
114



Mar. 13
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Proposal to hold pre-Conference meeting
                            of the Committee of Jurists.
119



Mar. 13
Minutes of the First Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Tuesday, March 13, 1945, 11
                                a.m.Conference problems: administration, organization,
                            publicity, trusteeship, League of Nations liquidation, Committee of
                            Jurists.
116



Mar. 14
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltChinese Communist
                            representation on Chinese Delegation.
120



Mar. 15
The Secretary of State to the Charge in China
                                    (Atcheson)President
                            Roosevelt&#8217;s message to President Chiang
                                Kai-shek regarding Chinese Delegation.
121



Mar. 15
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on
                                Caribbean Affairs (Taussig)Conversation with
                            President. Roosevelt regarding trusteeship, Arabia,
                            Caribbean bases, East Asian peoples, Indo-China, and New
                            Caledonia.
121



Mar. 15
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Polish representation at the
                            Conference.
124



Mar. 16
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltSenator Vandenberg&#8217;s proposed amendments to the
                            Dumbarton Oaks Proposals.
125



Mar. 16
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                Soviet Union (Harriman)Text of United States note to
                            Soviet Embassy regarding three-point proposal submitted by the Chinese
                            at Dumbarton Oaks for inclusion in the Charter.
126



Mar. 16
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltCongressional
                            consultations oh international-organization problems.
127



Mar. 16
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Proposed pre-Conference Five-Power
                            consultation on trusteeship questions.
128



Mar. 16
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Director
                                of the Office of Special Political Affairs (Hiss)Conversation of Secretary Stettinius with British and Soviet
                            Ambassadors regarding arrangements for Conference.
128



Mar. 16
Memorandum Prepared in the Department of
                            StateConference arrangements; memorandum handed to British,
                            Soviet, and Chinese Ambassadors.
131



Mar. 17
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant
                                Secretary of State (Dunn)Members of Soviet
                            Delegation; participation of Soviet Republics in Conference.
132



[Page XXII]Mar. 17
Memorandum by the Interdepartmental Committee on
                                Dependent AreasDraft statement on international
                            trusteeship, submitted to the Secretary of State&#8217;s Staff
                            Committee.
134



Mar. 17
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateBritish Foreign
                            Office official&#8217;s views on questions of Syria and Lebanon, International
                            Court of Justice, Polish participation, and trusteeship.
138



Mar. 18&#8211;Apr. 7
Extracts From the Diary of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.,
                                Secretary of State, December 1, 1944&#8211;July 3, 1945Dependent
                            peoples.
140



Mar. 19
The Latvian Minister (Bilmanis) to the
                                Secretary of StateProposed Latvian participation in
                            Conference.
141



Mar. 21
The British Secretary of State for Foreign
                                Affairs (Eden) to the British Ambassador
                                in the United States (Halifax)Participation of
                            Soviet Republics in the Conference.
142



Mar. 22
Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State to
                                President RooseveltParticipation of
                            two Soviet Republics in the Conference.
144



Mar. 22
The Secretary of State to the Polish Ambassador
                                    (Ciechanowski)Polish representation at the
                            Conference.
145



Mar. 22
The Charge in China (Atcheson) to the
                                Secretary of StateReference to the three proposals made by
                            the Chinese delegation at Dumbarton Oaks and request that the United
                            States transmit the proposals to all governments invited to
                            UNCIO.
146



Mar. 22
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman) Pre-Conference meeting of Committee
                            of Jurists; proposed procedure approved by British and Chinese
                            Governments.
146



Mar. 22
The Soviet Embassy to the Department of
                            StateQuestion of inviting Poland to the Conference.
147



Mar. 23
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary
                                of StateSoviet request that Poland be invited to the
                            Conference.
148



Mar. 23
Minutes of the Second Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at Washington, Friday, March 23,
                                1945, 10 a.m.Proposal to invite various private national
                            organizations to the Conference.
148



Mar. 23
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Participation of Soviet Republics in
                            the Conference.
150



Mar. 23
Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State to
                                President RooseveltList of names of
                            Soviet Delegation.
151



Mar. 23
Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State to
                                President RooseveltAuthorization
                            requested for statement regarding representation of two Soviet Republics
                            in the UN.
152



[Page XXIII]Mar. 23
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Requests from five inter-Governmental
                            organizations for invitations.
153



Mar. 23
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateSoviet agreement on
                            procedure regarding meeting of Committee of Jurists.
154



Mar. 24
The Acting Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic
                                RepresentativesInvitation to meeting of the Committee of
                            Jurists.
154



Mar. 24
President Roosevelt to the
                                Chairman of the Council of People&#8217;s Commissars of the Soviet
                                Union (Stalin)Disappointment that Mr. Molotov was not to attend the
                            Conference.
156



Mar. 24
The Acting Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic
                                RepresentativesProposals on questions of Conference
                            organization and procedures.
156



Mar. 25
The Soviet Ambassador (Gromyko) to the Secretary of StateSoviet insistence
                            on participation of the Soviet Ukraine and the Soviet White Russia in
                            UNCIO as charter members.
158



Mar. 26
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StatePolish
                            representation at the Conference.
159



Mar. 27
The Chinese Ambassador (Wei) to the
                                Secretary of StateCommunist Party represented in Chinese
                            Delegation.
160



Mar. 27
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)French participation in preliminary
                            conversations on trusteeship.
160



Mar. 28
Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Leo Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to
                                the Secretary of StateLiquidation of the League of
                            Nations.
161



Mar. 28
The Department of State to the British
                            EmbassyProposal for prior consultation among the sponsoring
                            nations on any proposed amendments submitted to the Conference by them
                            individually or severally.
162



Mar. 29
The Secretary of State to the Soviet Ambassador
                                (Gromyko)Representation of Soviet
                            Republics.
163



Mar. 29
The Department of State to the Soviet
                            EmbassyPolish representation.
164



Mar. 29
President Roosevelt to the
                                British Prime Minister (Churchill)Quoted telegram of March 27 from
                            Marshal Stalin regarding Mr. Molotov&#8217;s inability to attend
                            Conference.
165



Mar. 29
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateDecision of the
                            Soviet Union not to send Mr. Molotov to the Conference.
165



[Page XXIV]Mar. 29
Memorandum by Mr. Charles E. Bohlen, Assistant to the Secretary of
                                State for White House Liaison, of a Meeting at the White House,
                                Thursday, March 29, 1945, 11:45 a.m.Proposed press
                            statement regarding two Soviet Republics, President
                                Roosevelt&#8217;s plans to attend Conference, and
                            role of consultants in the Conference.
166



Mar. 30
Minutes of the Third Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Friday, March 30, 1945, 11
                            a.m.Discussion of the White House press statement on
                            representation of Soviet Republics in the UN, and Secretary Stettinius&#8217; press statement on this
                            subject.
168



Mar. 30
The Secretary of State to the Soviet Ambassador
                                (Gromyko)United States views on structure of
                            the Conference.
174



Mar. 30
The British Ambassador (Halifax) to the Secretary of StateSummary of report
                            by the League Supervisory Committee on question of liquidation of the
                            League of Nations.
175



Mar. 31
The Soviet Embassy to the Department of
                            StateSoviet agreement with United States proposal regarding
                            consultation of the four inviting Powers before submitting their
                            proposals to the Conference.
179



Apr. 2
The Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltRequest for Presidential
                            views on draft press statement on United States request for two
                            additional votes in the General Assembly; statement to be made April
                            3.
179



Apr. 2
The Counselor of the British Embassy
                                    (Makins) to Mr. Leo
                                    Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to the Secretary of
                                StateLiquidation of the League of Nations.
180



Apr. 3
The Department of State to the British
                            EmbassySuggestions concerning allocation of Commission and
                            Committee positions at the Conference.
181



Apr. 3
Minutes of the Fourth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Tuesday, April 3, 1945, 10
                            a.m.Proposed press statement on participation of the two
                            Soviet Republics in the UN; administrative matters.
183



Apr. 3
Minutes of the First Meeting of the Informal
                                Organizing Group on Arrangements for the San Francisco Conference,
                                Held at Washington, Tuesday, April 3, 1945, 2:45
                            p.m.Conference organization, allocation of positions, official
                            languages, press policy, denial of requests of the Italian and the
                            Korean Governments for representation by observers, unofficial
                            representation of five international organizations, consultation of
                            sponsoring states on amendments of Dumbarton Oaks Proposals.
189



Apr. 3
Memorandum Prepared in the Department of
                            StateOfficial languages to be used at the Conference.
192



Apr. 3
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateBritish promise of
                            support for the three Chinese Proposals suggested for inclusion in the
                            Charter.
193



Apr. 3
The Secretary of State to the Legal Adviser
                                (Hackworth)Designation of Mr. Hackworth as United States
                            Representative on the UN Committee of Jurists.
193



[Page XXV]Apr. 3
The Secretary of State to Mr. Leo Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to
                                the Secretary of StateDesignation of Mr. Pasvolsky as United States
                            Representative in preliminary consultations on international
                            trusteeship.
194



Apr. 3
The Lithuanian Minister (Zadeikis) to the
                                Secretary of StateRequest for Lithuanian representation at
                            the Conference.
195



Apr. 5
Extracts From President
                                    Roosevelt&#8217;s Press and Radio Conference at
                                the Little White House, Warm Springs, Georgia, April 5, 1945, 2
                                p.m.President Roosevelt&#8217;s description
                            of the &#8220;quiet way&#8221; in which Marshal Stalin made his
                            plea for representation of the Soviet Republics in the UN.
196



Apr. 5
The Secretary of the Interior (Ickes) to the Secretary of StateInternational
                            trusteeship problem.
198



Apr. 5
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Question of the resumption of normal
                            diplomatic relations with Argentina.
199



Apr. 5
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)Proposal that France join in sponsoring
                            the Conference.
201



Apr. 6
The Acting Consul General of Estonia in Charge of
                                Legation (Kaiv) to the Secretary of StateRequest for
                            Estonian representation at the Conference.
203



Apr. 7
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the
                                Division of, Dependent Areas (Gerig)Review of draft
                            memorandum on trusteeship; differing views of the Navy Department, the
                            War Department, the Interior Department, and the State
                            Department.
204



Apr. 7
The Secretary of State to the Italian
                                Ambassador (Tarchiani)Denial of Italian request to send an
                            observer to the Conference.
206



Apr. 7
The Secretary of State to Mr. Alexander C.
                                    Kirk, United States Political Adviser to the Supreme
                                Allied Commander, Mediterranean TheatreDenial of Albanian
                            request for participation in the Conference.
207



Apr. 8
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the
                                Office of Special Political Affairs (Hiss)Question of
                            presidency of the Conference.
208



Apr. 8&#8211;14
Extract From the Diary of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.,
                                Secretary of State, December 1, 1944&#8211;July 3,
                            1945International trusteeship problems.
209



Apr. 9
The Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltInternational
                            trusteeship problems.
211



Apr. 9
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltPaper on international
                            trusteeship.
214



Apr. 9
Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Leo Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to
                                the Secretary of StateChairmanship of the Committee of
                            Jurists.
214



[Page XXVI]Apr. 9
Minutes of the Fifth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Monday, April 9, 1945, 3:15
                                p.m.Discussion of Dumbarton Oaks Proposals and statements
                            of changes suggested for discussion by the various delegations: Name and
                            Preamble, I (Purposes), and II (Principles).
215



Apr. 9
Memorandum Prepared in the Department of
                            StateAllocation of Commission and Committee positions at the
                            Conference.
225



Apr. 9
Memorandum Prepared in the Department of
                            StateRecords to be made of proceedings of the
                            Conference.
226



Chapter III: April 10&#8211;April 24, 1945


Date
Paper
Page


1945 Apr. 10
Minutes of the Sixth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Tuesday, April 10, 1945, 10:15
                                a.m.Press policy; developments in the Committee of
                            Jurists; II, Principles; III, Membership; and IV, Principle
                            Organs.
227



Apr. 10
Minutes of the Second Meeting of the Informal
                                Organizing Group on Arrangements for the San Francisco Conference,
                                Held at Washington, Tuesday, April 10, 1945, 3
                            p.m.Organization of the Conference, allocation of Conference
                            positions, official languages, unofficial representation of five
                            international organizations, consultation of sponsoring powers on
                            amendment proposals, Conference documentation, languages.
235



Apr. 10
The Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltRequest received by the
                            Department that World Trade Union Conference be represented as advisers
                            to the Conference.
240



Apr. 10
The Secretary of State to President
                                    RooseveltSoviet proposal for four
                            Chairmen representing each of sponsoring nations at the
                            Conference.
240



Apr. 11
Minutes of the Seventh Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Wednesday, April 11, 1945, 9
                                a.m.V, General Assembly.
241



Apr. 11
Minutes of the Eighth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Wednesday, April 11, 1945, 11
                                a.m.IX, Economic and Social Cooperation.
259



Apr. 11
The Soviet Ambassador (Gromyko) to the Secretary of StateSoviet protest
                            regarding failure of Committee of Jurists to accept Soviet porposal for
                            four chairmen representing the four sponsoring nations.
269



Apr. 12
Minutes of the Ninth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Thursday, April 12, 1945, 9
                                a.m.Four problems arising from discussions in the
                            Committee of Jurists: election of judges to the Court, compulsory
                            jurisdiction, advisory opinions, and right of an international
                            organization like the ILO to request advisory opinions; review of
                            Proposals and suggestions for consideration: VI, Security Council; VIII,
                            A and B, Arrangements for the Maintenance of International Peace and
                            Security, Pacific Settlement of Disputes, and Determination of Threats
                            to the Peace.
269



[Page XXVII]Apr. 12
Minutes of the Ninth Meeting (Executive Session) of the United States
                                Delegation (A), Held
                                at Washington, Thursday, April 12, 1945Chairmanship of the
                            Conference; question of admission of the Soviet Republics as initial
                            members of the UN.
278



Apr. 13
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to President
                                    TrumanReport on preparations for
                            UNCIO: activities of the United States Delegation, presidency of
                            Conference, trusteeships, and question of initial membership of the
                            Soviet Republics.
281



Apr. 13
Minutes of the Third Meeting of the Informal
                                Organizing Group on Arrangements for the San Francisco Conference,
                                Held at Washington, Friday, April 13, 1945, noonAllocation
                            of Conference positions, chairmanship of Conference, languages,
                            nationality of unofficial observers from inter-governmental
                            organizations (reference to representatives of ILO and League of
                            Nations), initial membership of the Soviet Republics in the UN;
                            permanent adjournment of the Informal Organizing Group.
283



Apr. 13
Memorandum by Mr. Leo
                                    Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to the Secretary of
                                StateStatus of the trusteeship problem.
288



Apr. 13
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StatePremier
                                Stalin&#8217;s agreement to send Mr. Molotov to Washington and then to San
                            Francisco as head of Soviet Delegation.
289



Apr. 14
Memorandum by the Secretary of
                            StateTrusteeship issue.
290



Apr. 14
The Secretary of State to the Soviet Ambassador
                                (Gromyko)Chairmanship of the Jurists&#8217; Committee
                            and the Conference.
291



Apr. 14
Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Cabot Coville of the Office of
                                Special Political AffairsSoviet views on various aspects
                            of Conference arrangements.
291



Apr. 15&#8211;23
Extracts From the Diary of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.,
                                Secretary of State, December 1, 1944&#8211;July 3, 1945Polish
                            representation; initial membership of Soviet Republics.
292



Apr. 16
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant
                                Secretary of State (Dunn)Plans for preliminary
                            conversations on trusteeship.
295



Apr. 16
Minutes of the Tenth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Monday, April 16, 1945, 9
                            a.m.Allocation of Conference assignments for other countries;
                            general discussion on the character of changes to be proposed by United
                            States Delegation; V,B(6), General Assembly: Vandenberg proposal on adjustment of treaties; VIII,C,
                            Regional Arrangements, XII, Transitional Arrangements; and VIII, A(7),
                            Pacific Settlement of Disputes.
296



Apr. 17
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateFrance declines invitation to act as
                            fifth sponsoring nation.
310



[Page XXVIII]Apr. 17
Minutes of the Eleventh Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at Washington, Tuesday, April 17,
                                1945, 9 a.m.Meeting of Secretaries of War and Navy with
                            the Delegation to discuss trusteeship; language of report of Jurists&#8217;
                            Committee.



Apr. 17
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                StateDiscussion between Mr. Stettinius and Mr. Eden on various plans for the Conference: Chairmanships
                            Committee memberships, languages, Steering Committee procedure, Poland,
                            and Argentina.



Apr. 17
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                Soviet Union (Harriman)Soviet proposal regarding
                            nationality of unofficial observers representing inter-Governmental
                            organizations.



Apr. 17
The Soviet Embassy to the Department of
                            StateSoviet insistence on inviting to the Conference the
                            Polish Provisional Government functioning in Poland.



Apr. 18
Minutes of the Twelfth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at Washington, Wednesday, April 18, 1945, 9:10
                                a.m.VIII, A(7), Pacific Settlement of Disputes: domestic
                            jurisdiction; XI, Amendments; III Membership: withdrawal; IX, A(1),
                            Economic and Social Cooperation; review of decisions tentatively reached
                            for suggestions on the Proposals: Preamble, Chapters I through VI, VIII,
                            A(5, 7) and B(1), and XII; text of draft proposal on trusteeship.



Apr. 18
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to the Under
                                Secretary of State (Grew)Meeting of the
                            Secretaries of State, War, and Navy with President
                                Truman on trusteeship.



Apr. 18
Memorandum by the Secretaries of State, War, and
                                Navy to President TrumanPolicy
                            directive on trusteeship, approved by President
                                Truman.



Apr. 18
The Charg&#233; in the Soviet Union (Kennan) to the
                                Secretary of StateText of Mr. Molotov&#8217;s note of March 31 approving invitations to
                            non-official representatives of five inter-Governmental
                            organizations.



Apr. 18
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                StateSoviet attitude on questions of chairmanship,
                            nationality of representatives of international organizations, and
                            submission of proposed amendments through the various delegations rather
                            than individuals.



Apr. 19
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to President
                                    TrumanConclusion of review by the
                            American Delegation of the Proposals; tentative U.S. revisions of the
                            Proposals with respect to Purposes, Principles, General Assembly,
                            Security Council, Maintenance of Peace and Security, and Amendments;
                            questions deferred: Preamble, definition of the right of self-defense,
                            the chapter on economic and social cooperation, and a possible
                            withdrawal provision.



[Page XXIX]Apr. 21
Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Leo Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to
                                the Secretary of StateViews of the Mexican Delegation on
                            proposed modifications of the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals, and Mr.
                                Pasyolsky&#8217;s comments on their
                            four major points.
355



Apr. 23
Minutes of the Thirteenth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, April 23, 1945, 11
                                a.m.Summary statement on administrative and procedural
                            subjects discussed.
360



Apr. 23
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Denial of Danish request to be
                            represented by an observer at the Conference.
361



Apr. 23
Memorandum by the Secretary of State to President
                                    TrumanReport on recommendations
                            of the Committee of Jurists concerning the statute of the new
                            Court.
362



Apr. 23
Minutes of the First Four-Power Preliminary Meeting
                                on Questions of Organization and Admission, Held at Washington,
                                Monday, April 23, 1945, 9:35 p.m.Questions of organization
                            and admission of States to the Conference: Soviet Republics,
                            chairmanship, commissions and committees, languages, nationality of
                            observers or advisers to the Conference, Soviet promise of support of
                            Chinese proposals to be discussed with other proposed changes in the
                            Dumbarton Oaks Proposals.
363



Apr. 24
Minutes of the Fourteenth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, April 24, 1945,
                                9:30 a.m.Principal proposals by other Governments and
                            arguments against them: II, Principles, III, Membership, V, B, General
                            Assembly, VI, Security Council; press policy.
374



Apr. 24
Minutes of the Fifteenth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, April 24, 1945,
                                3:35 p.m.Summary statement on subjects discussed.
379



Apr. 24
The Department of State to the Embassy of the Soviet
                                UnionReiteration of United States position that it could
                            not agree to extension of an invitation to the Provisional Government
                            functioning in Warsaw.
379



Apr. 24
Memorandum by Mr. Charles E. Bohlen, Assistant to the Secretary of
                                State, of a Conversation Held at San Francisco, April 24, 1945, 5:45
                                p.m.Discussion of Secretary Stettinius with Soviet Foreign Minister Molotov and Ambassador Gromyko on problems of chairmanship,
                            admission of the Soviet Republics, and invitation to Poland.
380



Chapter IV: April 25&#8211;May 7, 1945


Date
Paper
Page


1945 Apr. 25
Minutes of the Sixteenth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation (A), Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, April 25, 1945, 8:35
                            a.m.Miscellaneous announcements.
385



[Page XXX]Apr. 25
Minutes of the Sixteenth Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation (B), Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, April 25, 1945, 9:30
                                a.m.US relations with the USSR on question of Poland and
                            on the problem of votes for the two additional Soviet Republics;
                            Argentina.
386



Apr. 25
Minutes of the Second Four-Power Preliminary Meeting
                                on Questions of Organization and Admission, Held at San Francisco,
                                April 25, 1945, 11 a.m.Plans for opening session of the
                            Conference.
402



Apr. 25
Minutes of the Seventeenth Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, April
                                25, 1945, 8:40 p.m.Questions of presidency of the
                            Conference, Argentina, and admission of Soviet Republics.
407



Apr. 26
Minutes of the Eighteenth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, April 26, 1945, 9:30
                                a.m.Discussion on Argentina and admission of two Soviet
                            Republics; proposed revisions II(4,8, and unnumbered paragraph),
                            Principles; III(1), Membership; V,B(1), General Assembly; VIII,B(1),
                            Threats to the Peace; X(1&#8211;6), Secretariat; and XI(2, and new paragraph),
                            Amendments: withdrawal provision.
414



Apr. 26
Memorandum by Mr. Charles E. Bohlen, Member of the United States
                                Delegation, of a Conversation Held at San Francisco, April 26, 1945,
                                10:20 a.m.Secretary Stettinius informs Mr. Molotov of his optimism on question of Steering
                            Committee approval of admission of Soviet Republics as initial members
                            of the proposed UN.
444



Apr. 26
Minutes of the Nineteenth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation (A), Held at San Francisco, Thursday, April 26, 1945, 8:40
                            p.m.Charter XII and XIII, Trusteeship system: United States
                            proposed draft approved by the Delegation as a basis for discussion in
                            the Conference.
445



Apr. 26
Minutes of the Nineteenth Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation (B), Held at San Francisco, Thursday, April 26, 1945, 9:05
                                p.m.Presidency of the Conference.
452



Apr. 26
Draft United States Proposals for
                            TrusteeshipCharter, XII and XIII, Text of draft
                            proposals.
459



Apr. 27
Minutes of the Twentieth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation (A), Held at San Francisco, April 27, 1945, 9:30 a.m.IX,
                            Economic and Social Cooperation.
460



Apr. 27
Minutes of the Third Four-Power Preliminary Meeting
                                on Questions of Organization and Admission, Held at San Francisco,
                                April 27, 1945, 10 a.m.Chairmanship of the
                            Conference.
472



Apr. 27
Minutes of the Twenty-First Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, April 27, 1945,
                                8:30 p.m.IX, Economic and Social Cooperation; VIII,B(1&#8211;3),
                            Threats to the Peace; Preamble; VIII,C(1&#8211;3), Regional Arrangements;
                            Charter XVI (102, 103), Registration of Treaties, and Inconsistent
                            Obligations; III, Membership: withdrawal.
473



[Page XXXI]Apr. 27
Minutes of the Twenty-First Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, April 27,
                                1945, 8:55 p.m.Secretary Stettinius&#8217; report on meeting of the Conference Steering
                            Committee and conversations with the President and Mr. Hull; Dumbarton Oaks Proposals
                            constituted the agenda of the Conference and proposed amendments to
                            these Proposals to be submitted by midnight May 4; Soviet Republics,
                            Poland, and Argentina.
481



Apr. 28
Minutes of the Twenty-Second Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, April 28, 1945,
                                9:30 a.m.List of subjects discussed.
485



Apr. 28
Minutes of the Fourth Four-Power Preliminary Meeting
                                on Questions of Organization and Admission, Held at San Francisco,
                                Saturday, April 28, 1945, 6:45 p.m.Soviet Republics,
                            Poland, Argentina.
486



Apr. 28
The Soviet Embassy to the Department of
                            StateSoviet insistence on inviting the Warsaw Government of
                            Poland.
488



Apr. 30
Minutes of the Twenty-Third Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, April 30, 1945,
                                9:30 a.m.Proposed statement of press policy for the
                            American Delegation; Charter XII, Trusteeship; S.36/2, Compulsory
                            Jurisdiction, S.2&#8211;7, Nomination of Judges of the Court, S.1, Continuity
                            of the Court.
488



Apr. 30
The Acting Secretary of State to the Chairman of the
                                United States Delegation at San Francisco (Stettinius)Recommendation that the question of
                            Italy&#8217;s participation in UNCIO be reopened.
499



Apr. 30
Minutes of the Twenty-Fourth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, April 30, 1945,
                                6:20 p.m.Admission of the two Soviet Republics and
                            Argentina approved by the Steering Committee and the Conference in
                            Plenary session; assignment of positions on Commissions and
                            Committees.
500



Apr. 30
Minutes of the Fifth Four-Power Preliminary Meeting
                                on Questions of Organization and Admission, Held at San Francisco,
                                April 30, 1945Approval of a list (not printed) of
                            officerships of the commissions and committees.
505



May 1
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateReport to President
                                Truman on alterations in the Dumbarton Oaks
                            Proposals which the Delegation had agreed should be proposed and certain
                            other alterations proposed by other governments which should be
                            supported.
506



May 1
Minutes of the Sixth Four-Power Preliminary Meeting
                                on Questions of Organization and Admission, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 1, 1945, 7:15 p.m.VIII,C, Enforcement action under
                            regional arrangements.
509



[Page XXXII]May 2
Minutes of the Twenty-Fifth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 2, 1945, 9
                                a.m.S.1, Continuity of the Court, S.4&#8211;7, Nomination of
                            Judges of the Court, VIII,A(6), reference of justiciable disputes to the
                            Court; VIII,A(1), application of veto power to the investigation
                            procedure of the Security Council; VIII,A(6) and Charter Article 96/1
                            and 2; Advisory Opinions; comments by U.K., U.S.S.R., China, and France
                            on U.S. Proposals; IX,A(1), Economic and social cooperation and Charter
                            article 8, Organs: equal opportunity for men and women; XI, Amendments:
                            revisionary conference and withdrawal from membership.
511



May 2
Minutes of the Twenty-Sixth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 2, 1945,
                                5:30 p.m.Voting procedure in public meetings of the
                            Conference; statements by Consultants; review of U.S. proposals in light
                            of consultation developments: I (1&#8211;3), Purposes; II (1,5,6, and unn.
                            par.), Principles; V, B (1,2,5, and 6), General Assembly; VI, D(2),
                            Security Council; VIII, A(5 and 7), Pacific Settlement of Disputes;
                            VIII,B (1&#8211;4), Threats to the Peace and Action with Respect Thereto; IX,
                            A(1) and D(1), Economic and Social Cooperation; X, Secretariat (new
                            par.); XI (new par.), Amendments; Preamble; III and XI, provisions on
                            withdrawal charter article 102, registration of treaties; Review of
                            Amendments to Dumbarton Oaks Proposals as suggested by the United
                            Kingdom Delegation: IX,C(1,d), Functions of the Economic and Social
                            Council; V,B(7), new par., Functions of the General Assembly; VI,A,
                            Composition of the Security Council; VIII,A (1 and 7), Pacific
                            Settlement of Disputes; Review of amendments to Dumbarton Oaks Proposals
                            as suggested by the Soviet Delegation: I(1&#8211;3), Purposes; V,B (6),
                            Functions of the General Assembly; VIII,C (2), Regional Arrangements;
                            IX,A (1), Economic and Social Cooperation, Purpose and Relationships; X
                            (1) Secretariat; XII (new par. after 1), Transitional
                            Arrangements.
528



May 2
Minutes of the First Four-Power Consultative Meeting
                                on Charter Proposals, Held at San Francisco, May 2, 1945, 9
                                p.m.VIII, B (2, 3), Threats to the peace; VII(6),
                            International Court of Justice; VI, A, and D(5), Security Council; VIII,
                            A(2), Pacific Settlement of Disputes; I (1&#8211;3), Purposes; II (1&#8211;5),
                            Principles: members; V,B(1,2,5,6), General Assembly.
548



May 3
Minutes of the Twenty-Seventh Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 3, 1945, 9
                                a.m.I(3), Purposes: equal rights for all people; V,B(6),
                            General Assembly&#8217;s functions: proposal on revision of treaties.
558



May 3
Minutes of the Second Four-Power Consultative
                                Meeting on Charter Proposals, Held at San Francisco, May 3, 1945, 10
                                a.m.VI,D (2,5), Security Council: Procedure; VIII, A(1,
                            new par., 2, 4, 7), Pacific Settlement of Disputes, B (1&#8211;2, new par.),
                            Threats to the Peace; C (2), Regional Arrangements; VII(6), Enforcement
                            of Judgments of the Court; IX A(1), D(1), Economic and Social
                            Cooperation, Purpose, and Organization; X (1, new par. 4), Secretariat;
                            XI (1, 2), Amendments; and V, B (7, new par.), General Assembly,
                            functions.
562



[Page XXXIII]May 3
Minutes of the Twenty-Eighth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 3, 1945,
                                6:20 p.m.Draft covering statement for joint submission to
                            the Conference of amendments agreed upon by the four sponsoring nations;
                            amendments which had been deferred for further study: VI,A, Security
                            Council, proposal of the UK, VII, ICJ, Chinese Proposal, VIII,A(2), and
                            VIII,A(4), Pacific settlement of disputes, Chinese and British
                            Proposals, respectively, VIII,B and VIII,B(9), Threats to the Peace,
                            Chinese Proposal, IX, Economic and Social Cooperation, British Proposal,
                            and X, Secretariat, Soviet Proposal; Interim Economic Commission.
                            Reports on subcommittees: VIII,A(1), Charter article 2(7), V,B(6),
                            VIII,C(2), XII(2), and IX,D.
574



May 3
Minutes of the Third Four-Power Consultative Meeting
                                on Charter Proposals, Held at San Francisco, May 3, 1945, 9:40
                                p.m.Question of France&#8217;s participation in discussions of
                            sponsoring Powers; discussion of subcommittee reports on domestic
                            jurisdiction, revision of treaties; IX,A(1) and C(1), Economic and
                            Social Council; VI,A, Security Council, election of nonpermanent
                            members; VIII,A(2) rights of non-member states; VIII,A(4), Security
                            Council recommendations of terms of settlement; VIII,B(1), and B(2), new
                            paragraph, and B(9), Threats to the Peace; specific reference to the
                            ILO; X, Secretary General.
581



May 4
Minutes of the Twenty-Ninth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 4, 1945, 9:05
                                a.m.Consideration of deferred questions: VIII,A(4) and
                            B(1), Pacific Settlement of Disputes, and Threats to the Peace; VIII,C,
                            Regional Arrangements; XII (2), Transitional Arrangements; Charter XII,
                            trusteeship.
588



May 4
Minutes of the Fourth Four-Power Consultative
                                Meeting on Charter Proposals, Held at San Francisco, May 4, 1945,
                                12:15 p.m.II(7), Principles: Domestic jurisdiction;
                            V,B(6), General Assembly, Functions; VIII,A(4), Pacific Settlement of
                            Disputes; VIII, B(1), Threats to the Peace; VII, International Court of
                            Justice; International trusteeship; draft press release to cover
                            presentation of the joint Four-Power amendments; Preamble.
598



May 4
Minutes of the Fifth Four-Power Consultative Meeting
                                on Charter Proposals (Part I), Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 4, 1945, 6:30
                                p.m.VB (6), General Assembly; VIII,C(2), Regional
                            Arrangements; XII (2), Transitional Arrangements.
603



May 4
Minutes of the Thirtieth Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 4,
                                1945, 7:10 p.m.VIII,C(2), Regional Arrangements.
607



May 4
Minutes of the Fifth Four-Power Consultative Meeting
                                on Charter Proposals (Part II), Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 4, 1945, 10
                                p.m.VIII,C(2), Regional Arrangements; separate and
                            individual submission to the Conference by each of the Sponsoring Powers
                            of those amendments upon which they had found themselves in
                            disagreement, citation to UNCIO Documents for texts.
610



[Page XXXIV]May 6
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateMessage to the President, Mr. Hull and the Acting Secretary of State:
                            Press conference, three statements given out, one describing the joint
                            amendments submitted to the Conference by the four Sponsoring Powers,
                            second, quoting amendments submitted by the United States alone (V,B(6),
                            VIII,C(2), and trusteeship arrangements), and third, dealing with arrest
                            of the Polish underground leaders; projected attempts to reconcile
                            remaining differences among the four Sponsoring Powers, to whose
                            consultations France would be added; Latin American attitudes regarding
                            regional pacts.
612



May 7
Minutes of the Thirty-First Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, May 7, 1945, 9
                                a.m.Question of unofficial representatives of official
                            organizations; VIII,C(2), Regional Arrangements (charter art.
                            53/1).
615



May 7
Minutes of the First Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 7, 1945, 3 p.m.Procedure to be followed in review of
                            proposed amendments to the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals submitted by other
                            nations represented at the Conference; Soviet action on two proposed
                            amendments to V,B(6) and VIII,C(2) (charter articles 13/1 and
                            53/1).
628



May 7
Minutes of the Thirty-Second Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, May 7, 1945, 6:18
                                p.m.VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements (charter art.
                            53/1).
631



May 7
The Acting Secretary of State to the Minister in
                                Iceland (Dreyfus)Question of Iceland&#8217;s membership in the
                            UN.
640



Chapter V: May
                        8&#8211;May 31, 1945


Date
Paper
Page


1945 May 8
Minutes of the Thirty-Third Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, May 8, 1945, 5
                                p.m.VIII,C, Regional Arrangements.
641



May 8
Memorandum by Mr. Charles E. Bohlen, Member of the United States
                                Delegation, of a Conversation Held at San Francisco, May 8, 1945,
                                8:30 p.m.Conversation of Secretary Stettinius with Mr. Molotov before his departure
                            (Ambassador Gromyko to remain as
                            his deputy); Soviet views on dealing with amendments proposed by other
                            countries.
650



May 8
The Acting Secretary of State to the Chairman of the
                                United States Delegation (Stettinius)Molotov&#8217;s press statement on
                            self-government for dependent peoples.
652



[Page XXXV]May 9
Minutes of the Second Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 9, 1945, 3:05 p.m.Suggested procedure for drafting
                            final Charter.
652



May 9
Minutes of the Thirty-Fourth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 9, 1945,
                                5:30 p.m.VI, A, Security Council, Composition; Charter
                            XII, Commander Stassen&#8217;s
                            progress report on trusteeship.
654



May 10
Minutes of the Thirty-Fifth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 10, 1945,
                                6:30 p.m.VIII, C, Regional problem; decision to await
                            recommendations by the Preparatory Commission on questions of location
                            of the UN and place of first meeting of the General Assembly; V, B (2
                            and 3), and III (1), Membership.
657



May 11
Minutes of the Thirty-Sixth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Firday, May 11, 1945, 2:30
                                p.m.VIII,C, Regional Arrangements; Charter article 51:
                            Right of self defense, draft new par. to be added to VIII, B, as par.
                            12; departure of Mr. Eden from the
                            Conference: voting procedure in Committees.
663



May 12
Minutes of the Thirty-Seventh Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, May 12, 1945, 9
                                a.m.VIII,C, Regional Arrangements; Navy views; VIII, B
                            (12), Right of self defense, Charter article 51, British reaction; Mr.
                                Hull&#8217;s views; agreement of
                            Delegation on 11:20 draft on regional arrangements; Charter XII, draft
                            proposed Working Paper on trusteeship discussed; IX, Economic and Social
                            Cooperation.
674



May 12
Minutes of the Third Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments (Part I), Held at San Francisco, Saturday,
                                May 12, 1945, 2:30 p.m.VIII,B(12), Right of self defense;
                            and VIII,C(2), Regional Arrangements; draft texts of VIII,B, new par.
                            12, and VIII, C(1).
691



May 12
Minutes of the Third Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments (Part II), Held at San Francisco, Saturday,
                                May 12, 1945, 6 p.m.VIII,B(12), Right of self defense; and
                            VIII,C(2), Regional Arrangements.
706



May 14
Minutes of the Thirty-Eighth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, May 14, 1945, 9:05
                                a.m.VIII,B(12), Right of self defense; VIII,C(1), Regional
                            Arrangements; X(1), Secretariat; V,B, role of General Assembly in
                            enforcement action.
707



May 14
Record of First Informal Consultative Meeting With
                                Chairmen of Delegations of Certain American Republics, Held at San
                                Francisco, May 14, 1945, 2:30 p.m.VIII,C(1), Regional
                            Arrangements; VIII,B(12), Right of self-defense.
712



[Page XXXVI]May 15
Minutes of the Thirty-Ninth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, May 15, 1945, 9
                                a.m.VIII,B, Enforcement Arrangements; VIII,C, Regional
                            Arrangements; III, Membership (withdrawal); V,B(1), security powers of
                            the General Assembly: Charter article 2(4), Purposes and Principles:
                            territorial integrity.
719



May 15
Notes on Second Informal Consultative Meeting With
                                Chairmen of Delegations of Certain American Republics, Held at San
                                Francisco, May 15, 1945, 2:45 p.m.VIII, A(3), Pacific
                            Settlement of Disputes; VIII,B(12), Right of self-defense; VIII,C,
                            Regional Arrangements.
730



May 15
Minutes of the Fourth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 15, 1945, 5 p.m.VIII,A(3), Pacific Settlement of
                            Disputes: Regional Arrangements; VIII,C(1), Regional Arrangements;
                            VIII,B(12), Right of self-defense.
737



May 15
Minutes of the Fortieth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at San Francisco, May 15, 1945, 6
                            p.m.X(1), Secretary General and Deputy Secretaries General;
                            Preamble, &#8220;due respect for treaties&#8221;; I, Purposes; Charter article 2(4)
                            Purposes and Principles: territorial integrity; press statement on
                            regional areas.
740



May 15
Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary
                                of StateRelation of Switzerland to the proposed UN.
749



May 16
Minutes of the Forty-First Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 16, 1945, 9
                                a.m.Consideration of amendments proposed by other
                            countries: Preamble; I, Purposes; and II, Principles: human rights;
                            recommendations on III, Membership (withdrawal, expulsion, and
                            suspension); XI, Charter amendments; X, Secretariat; VII, New Court vs.
                            Old Court; VI A, Security Council, Composition: election of
                            non-permanent members to the Security Council; Charter XII, the
                            Delegation&#8217;s working paper accepted by the Committee on Trusteeship as
                            basis for its discussions.
749



May 16
Minutes of the Fifth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 16, 1945, 3 p.m.Completion of Five-Power consultation
                            on regional formula awaiting Soviet approval before submission to the
                            Conference Commission III/4.
758



May 16
Minutes of the Forty-Second Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 16, 1945, 6
                                p.m.Consideration of recommendations to American
                            Delegation on basic issues: V,B,C,D, General Assembly: structure,
                            voting, procedures, political and security functions; IX, Economic and,
                            Social Cooperation.
761



May 17
Minutes of the Forty-Third Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 17, 1945,
                                8:30 a.m.V,B(4), Election of Secretary General; Procedural
                            questions; VI, Security Council; VIII,B, Voting procedure on enforcement
                            action; VIII,A, Pacific Settlement of Disputes.
768



[Page XXXVII]May 17
Minutes of the Forty-Third Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation (B), Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 17, 1945, 10:20
                                a.m.X(1), Deputies, Secretary General; VIII,C, Regional
                            Arrangements; II, Principles: Atlantic Charter, freedom of information
                            and communication.
774



May 17
Minutes of the Forty-Fourth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 17, 1945, 6
                                p.m.VI, Security Council: Yalta voting agreement; VIII,
                            B(12), Enforcement arrangements: Collective measures in selfdefense;
                            Decisions reached by the Committee of Five: Preamble, I and II, Purposes
                            and Principles; III Membership, X, Secretariat; V,B(3), and B,C(1&#8211;2),
                            General Assembly: suspension of voting rights as penalty of non-payment
                            of contribution; Charter articles 8, Organs and 101(3), Secretariat:
                            Participation of men and women on an equal basis in UN; VII,
                            International Court of Justice: Judges&#8212;nomination and election; V, B(1),
                            General Assembly: functions and powers; IX, Economic and Social
                            Cooperation: IX, A(2), ILO, IX, A(1), Right to work; Charter article
                            55(a), Full employment; IX, A, new paragraphs (Australian pledge); IX, B
                            and C, Economic and Social Council, composition and functions; Charter
                            article 76(b), International Trusteeship System, &#8220;independence&#8221; as a
                            goal.
778



May 18
Minutes of the Forty-Fifth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 18, 1945, 9
                                a.m.Recommendations to U.S. Delegation on basic issues;
                            Legal problems: Charter article 105(1&#8211;2), privileges and immunities
                            (UN); Charter article 102(1&#8211;2), registration and publication of
                            treaties; Charter article 103, conflict of international agreements with
                            Charter; Charter article 13(1a), General Assembly: development of
                            international law, General Assembly role; dissolution of League of
                            Nations; Charter article 76(b), Trusteeship: &#8220;independence&#8221; for
                            dependent peoples as a goal; Charter article 62(1), Economic and Social
                            Council: reference to &#8220;education&#8221;.
790



May 18
Minutes of the Forty-Sixth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 18, 1945, 6
                                p.m.VIII, B, Enforcement arrangements; XII, Transitional
                            Arrangements; IX,A(1), Economic and Social Cooperation: reference to
                            &#8220;education&#8221;.
799



May 19
Minutes of the Forty-Seventh Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, May 19, 1945, 9
                                a.m.IXC, Economic and Social Council, functions and
                            powers; IX,A(1), full employment; VI,D(5), and Charter article 44,
                            Security Council, ad hoc voting membership;
                            VIII,C, Regional Arrangements: mention of &#8220;Act of Chapultepec&#8221;;
                            VIII,C(2), Charter article 53, exception for action against enemy
                            states; VIII,B, Enforcement arrangements: definition of aggression, and
                            agreements for supply of forces and facilities; XII(2), Transitional
                            Arrangements; and VIII,A(2), Pacific Settlement of Disputes: Right of
                            enemy states to appeal to the Security Council or the General Assembly;
                            I(1), Purposes and III(1), Membership: Neutrality.
803



[Page XXXVIII]May 19
Minutes of the Sixth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 19, 1945VIII,A(3), Pacific Settlement of Disputes:
                            Regional Arrangements; VIII,B(12), Enforcement arrangements: right to
                            self-defense; VIII,C, Regional Arrangements: reply of the USSR to
                            revisions proposed by the other four Governments on the paragraphs
                            dealing with regional arrangements in relation to the UN.
812



May 20
Minutes of the Forty-Eighth Meeting (Executive Session), of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Sunday, May 20,
                                1945, 12 NoonDiscussion of Soviet regional drafts
                            (VIII,B(12), VIII,C); May 19 draft text of VIII, B(12); VI, Security
                            Council: voting procedure.
813



May 20
Minutes of the Seventh Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                Sunday, May 20, 1945, 6 p.m.Consideration of report of
                            Subcommittee of Five on Soviet proposals regarding the three drafts on
                            regional arrangements (VIII,B(12), VIII,C(1), VIII,A(3)).
823



May 20
Record of Third Informal Consultative Meeting With
                                Ambassadors of Certain American Republics, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 20, 1945, 9 p.m.Presentation to the Ambassadors of
                            three drafts to the Regional Committee the following day (VIII, A(3),
                            VIII, B(12), and VIII, C(1); no dissent from the drafts
                            expressed.
825



May 21
Minutes of the Forty-Ninth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, May 21, 1945, 9
                                a.m.VI,C(1&#8211;3), Voting procedure in the Security Council:
                            Yalta voting formula interpreted by Mr. Hiss; Charter article 71, relations of Economic and
                            Social Council with non-governmental organizations; Charter article
                            62(4), calling of international conference by the Economic and Social
                            Council; IX,A(1a), Full employment as an objective of UN.
826



May 21
The Acting Secretary of State to Diplomatic
                                Representatives in the American RepublicsBackground
                            information on the regional arrangements issue (VIII,C, XII(2),
                            VIII,B(12), VIII,A(3)).
831



May 22
Minutes of the Fiftieth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation (A), Held
                                at San Francisco, Tuesday, May 22, 1945, 9:05
                            a.m.IX,A(1a), &#8220;full employment&#8221;; Charter article 56,
                            cooperation of members on economic and social matters; UNCIO:
                            establishment and composition of Advisory Committee of Jurists (US, UK,
                            USSR, China, France, and Mexico); VII, International Court of Justice;
                            Charter XII, Trusteeship; review proposal on a Preparatory Commission;
                            Charter Preamble: provision on respect for treaties.
837



May 22
Minutes of the Fiftieth Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, May 22,
                                1945, 10:50 a.m.Charter article 108, Amendments:
                            Withdrawal from membership.
847



[Page XXXIX]May 23
Minutes of the Fifty-First Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 23, 1945, 9
                                a.m.Charter article 108, Withdrawal provision; IX,A,
                            Economic and Social Cooperation: Purpose and relationships; full
                            employment; V,B(6), General Assembly, objectives; VIII,C(2), Regional
                            Arrangements: French draft amendment; Charter Preamble; respect for
                            treaties; Charter XII, 77(2), Trusteeship System: future arrangements
                            concerning individual territories, Arab League proposal freezing status
                            of Palestine.
849



May 24
Minutes of the Fifty-Second Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 24, 1945,
                                9:05 a.m.VIII, B(5), Enforcement arrangements: conclusion
                            of military agreements, registration of military agreements; VIII,C(2),
                            Regional arrangements, enforcement action-proposed change in Sponsoring
                            Governments&#8217; amendments; XI, Amendments; II(7), Principles: Domestic
                            jurisdiction; V,B(3) membership; expulsion, suspension; IX,A(1),
                            Economic and social cooperation: full employment.
862



May 25
Minutes of the Fifty-Third Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 26, 1945, 9:05
                                a.m.VI,C (Charter art. 27(3)), Security Council, voting
                            (Yalta voting formula); IX,A(1), Economic and Social Cooperation; full
                            employment, and Australian amendment; Charter article 103, compatibility
                            of treaties with Charter; Charter XII, Trusteeship: Arab League&#8217;s
                            amendments, Palestinian situation.
873



May 25
Minutes of the Eighth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 25, 1945, 11 a.m.IX,A(2), Economic and Social
                            Cooperation: specialized agencies (ILO, etc.) brought into relationship
                            with UN; VIII,C(2), Regional Arrangements, French amendment.
889



May 26
Minutes of the Fifty-Fourth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, May 26, 1945,
                                9:03 a.m.IX, A(1), Economic and Social Cooperation:
                            Australian amendment; VI,C, Security Council, voting: proposed statement
                            on USDEL interpretation of Yalta formula; VIII,A, Pacific settlement of
                            disputes: rearrangement order of paragraphs in Charter language as
                            altered by Four Power amendments; Charter Preamble; respect for
                            treaties; VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements: French treaty
                            question.
892



May 26
Minutes of the Fifty-Fifth Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, May 26,
                                1945, 2:30 p.m.VI,C, Security Council: Yalta voting
                            formula; VIII,B (5,6,9), Determination of threats to the peace: French
                            amendments, armed forces and national air force contingents made
                            available to the Secuirty Council, and Military Staff Committee; V,B(3),
                            V,C(2) General Assembly: Membership, expulsion; X, Secretariat: deputy
                            secretary general; V,B General Assembly: functions and powers,
                            Australian porposal; Charter XI, XII, XIII, Trusteeship, Iraqi,
                            Egyptian, and Arab League proposals involving Amandates,
                            Palestine.
911



[Page XL]May 26
Minutes of the Ninth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                Saturday, May 26, 1945, 9:15 p.m.VI,C, Security Council:
                            Voting procedure.
926



May 28
Minutes of the Fifty-Sixth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, May 28, 1945, 9
                                a.m.VI,C, Security Council: voting; VIII,B(7),
                            Determination of threats to the peace, Charter article 4(1), membership:
                            French amendment on neutrality; VIII, B(5), Threats to the peace:
                            procedure on agreements for supply of forces; IX, Economic and Social
                            Cooperation, Charter article 56, Australian &#8220;pledge&#8221; agreement; VIII, B
                            (5,6,9), French amendments regarding military agreements; Charter XII,
                            Trusteeship: amendments proposed by Arab League and by Iraq involving
                            Palestine.
935



May 29
Minutes of the Fifty-Seventh Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, May 29, 1945, 9
                                a.m.Proposed invitation to Denmark to participate in
                            Conference; VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements: French treaty question;
                            question of acceptance of Italy into the UN; Preamble; Charter XII,
                            Trusteeship; S36, Statute of the International Court of Justice:
                            Compulsory jurisdiction; VIII,B (new par. between pars. 5 and 6),
                            enforcement measures: representation in Security Council of non-member
                            states contributing armed forces, Canadian amendment; VIII,B(5)
                            Enforcement measures: Participation of Security Council in conclusion of
                            agreements for supply of forces to the UN: XII, Transitional
                            arrangements: French participation in interim arrangements.
954



May 29
Minutes of the Tenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                May 29, 1945, 11 a.m.VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements:
                            utilization regional agencies for enforcement action; VI,C, Security
                            Council: voting; Conference procedures: time schedule.
968



May 30
Minutes of the Fifty-Eighth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 30, 1945,
                                9:05 a.m.Problems of inviting Denmark, Korea, Iceland,
                            Poland, Albania, Palestine, Italy; IX,A(1), Economic and Social
                            Cooperation: raw materials; S36, Statute of the ICJ: compulsory
                            jurisdiction; VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements and XII(2), action with
                            respect to enemy states: French treaty amendment; VIII,B(5),
                            Determination of threats to peace: procedure on agreements for supply of
                            forces, Australian amendment; XI, Amendment procedure; X, Secretariat:
                            election Secretary General.
974



May 31
Minutes of the Fifty-Ninth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 31, 1945,
                                9:02 a.m.U.S. note on Syria and Lebanon to France; XI,
                            Charter amendment procedure; Charter article 109, revisionary
                            conference; invitation of Denmark; X, Secretariat; S4&#8211;15, ICJ: election
                            of judges; V,B(3), V,C(2), Membership: expulsion; VIII,B(5),
                            Determination of threats to peace: supply of forces; IX, Economic and
                            Social Council; VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements: French treaty
                            amendment; Preamble.
989



[Page XLI]May 31
Memorandum by the Chairman of the American
                                Delegation (Stettinius) of a Conversation
                                With the Acting Chairman of the Soviet Delegation (Gromyko), Held at San Francisco, Thursday, May 31, 1945, 12:25
                                p.m.Discussion of major issues requiring decisions;
                            interpretation of voting procedure; election of judges; election of
                            secretary general and deputies; amendment process; expulsion; agreements
                            for armed forces; French amendment on regional arrangements; preparatory
                            commission; trusteeship; transitional arrangements (XIII); powers of the
                            General Assembly; position of the Soviet Delegation; proposed Big Five
                            meeting.
1011



Chapter VI: June 1&#8211;June 26, 1945


Date
Paper
Page


1945 June 1
Minutes of the Sixtieth Meeting of the United States
                                Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, June 1, 1945, 9
                            a.m.XII, transtional arrangements; Charter article 56,
                            Economic and Social Cooperation: Australian pledge amendment and
                            IX,A(1(b)), Purpose: raw materials amendment; Preamble; X, Secretariat:
                            Secretary General and Deputy Secretaries General; procedural voting
                            arrangements applicable to VI,D; VIII,A; XI, revisionary conference; and
                            S4&#8211;15, ICJ: election of judges of the World Court; VIII,C(2), Regional
                            arrangements: French treaty amendment; XII(2), Enforcement action
                            against enemies of Charter signatories; V,B(8), General Assembly,
                            functions and powers: annual reports from UN bodies; Charter XII,
                            Trusteeship.
1022



June 1
Minutes of the Sixty-First Meeting of the United
                                States Delegagation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, June 1, 1945,
                                6:04 p.m.Discussion of a paper, position on open
                            questions: VI,C, Security Council, voting; XI, Charter amendments; X(1),
                            Secretariat: election of the Secretary General and the Deputy
                            Secretaries General; ICJ, S4&#8211;15: election of judges; V,B(3) Membership:
                            expulsion; VIII,B(5), provision of armed forces; Charter article 56,
                            Economic and Social Cooperation: Australian pledge amendment; IX,A(1),
                            raw materials; IX, reconstruction; VIII,C(2), and XII, Enforcement
                            arrangements; revised draft; V,B(8), action by the General Assembly on
                            reports of the Security Council; V,B(1), right of the General Assembly
                            to discuss any matter within the sphere of international relations;
                            V,B(6), revision of treaties; Charter article 96(1) ICJ, advisory
                            opinions; Charter XII, trusteeship; Charter article 69, ECOSOC:
                            participation of non-members.
1056



June 1
Minutes of the Eleventh Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 1, 1945, 9 p.m.VI,C, Security Council: voting, new
                            draft Four-Power statement; VIII,B(5), provision of armed forces;
                            VIII,C(2), enforcement arrangements, and enforcement measures against
                            enemy states under XII(2); XI, convocation of a general conference for
                            review of the Charter; report on progress of the Conference; question of
                            inviting Denmark to the Conference; X(1), Secretariat; V,B(3),
                            membership: expulsion.
1071



[Page XLII]June 2
Minutes of the Sixty-Second Meeting (Executive Session) of the
                                United States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, June 2,
                                1945, 9 a.m.VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements: French
                            treaty amendment; XI, Charter amendment procedure; VI, C, Yalta voting
                            formula.
1087



June 2
Minutes of the Twelfth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 2, 1945, 10 a.m.VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements:
                            French proposal; VI,C, and VIII, A, Voting in the Security Council;
                            XII(1), Transitional arrangements; XI, Amendments: Conference for review
                            of Charter; S4&#8211;15, ICJ: election of judges; X(1) Secretary
                            General.
1094



June 2
Minutes of the Thirteenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 2, 1945, 5:30 p.m.X(1) Secretariat: election of
                            Deputy Secretaries-General; Charter article 96(1) and VIII, A(6), ICJ,
                            advisory opinion; IX, Economic cooperation: Australian pledge, raw
                            materials, and reconstruction; Charter articles 76(b), 80, 86, and 91,
                            Trusteeship questions: objectives, the &#8220;conservatory clause&#8221;, and
                            Council composition and procedure; V, B(8), General Assembly action on
                            Security Council reports.
1106



June 2
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)VI,C, Security Council: Soviet
                            opinion on the Yalta agreement on voting procedure.
1117



June 3
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)Yalta voting formula.
1119



June 3
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Acting Secretary of StateQuestions on
                            Soviet position on voting in the Security Council.
1119



June 3
Minutes of the Fourteenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 3, 1945, 4 p.m.VIII,C(2), Regional arrangements:
                            French proposal; XI, Charter amending procedure; X, Secretariat:
                            election of Deputy Secretaries General; V,B(8), General Assembly action
                            on Security Council reports; V,B(6), General Assembly right to revise
                            treaties; V,B (1,2) Right of General Assembly to discuss any matter
                            within the sphere of international relations; IX,A(1), Australian pledge
                            for separate action.
1120



June 3
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateDraft text of statement, by the
                            Sponsors&#8217; subcommittee, on voting procedure in the Security Council,
                            together with Soviet-proposed substitution of certain paragraphs.
1131



June 3
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateSecretary Stettinius&#8217; reply to Ambassador Harriman&#8217;s telegram 1882 of June 3 on
                            voting procedure in the Security Council.
1136



[Page XLIII]June 4
Minutes of the Sixty-Third Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, June 4, 1945, 9
                                a.m.XII, Transitional arrangements; VIII,A(7), Charter
                            article 2(7), domestic jurisdiction, and VIII,B, enforcement measures;
                            V,B(1), Right of the General Assembly to discuss any matter within the
                            sphere of international relations; Preparatory Commission.
1137



June 4
Minutes of the Fifteenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 4, 1945, 12 noonVIII,C(2), Regional arrangements:
                            French proposal; XI, Amendments: Conference for revision of Charter;
                            V,B(1), Powers of General Assembly; IX, Economic cooperation: raw
                            materials; Interim arrangements: Preparatory Commission; VIII,B(9),
                            Regional subcommittees of the Military Staff Committee.
1145



June 4
Memorandum by Mr. Robert
                                    W. Hartley of the United States Delegation, of a
                                Conversation Held at San Francisco, Monday, June 4, 1945, 3:30
                                p.m.Exchange of views between members of delegations of
                            the United States and the Soviet Union on Charter article 27, voting in
                            the Security Council.
1152



June 4
Mr. Hugh S. Gumming, Jr.,
                                Political and Liaison Officer for Europe, to Mr. G. Hayden Raynor, Special Assistant
                                to the Chairman of the American Delegation (Stettinius)Question of Danish participation in the
                            UN.
1159



June 5
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateUS-Soviet views on possible locations of
                            permanent seat of the UN.
1159



June 5
Minutes of the Sixty-Fourth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, June 5, 1945,
                                9:01 a.m.XII, Transitional arrangements; II(3 and 4),
                            Principles; X, Secretariat; ICJ Statute, authority: proposed amendment
                            to allow the Court to settle disputes among international agencies;
                            VIII,B(9), Military Staff Committee; Charter XII, trusteeship: art.
                            76(b), objctives, art. 80(1), the &#8220;conservatory clause&#8221;; VIII,C(2),
                            French treaty amendment.
1160



June 5
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the Soviet Union (Harriman)VI,C, Voting procedure in the
                            Security Council.
1170



June 6
Minutes of the Sixty-Fifth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, June 6, 1945,
                                9:03 a.m.Invitation to Denmark to participate in UNCIO;
                            press leak on the veto question; V,B(5), power of the General Assembly
                            to apportion UN expenses among UN members; VIII,C(2), French treaty
                            amendment for the purpose of safeguarding French bilateral regional
                            arrangements&#8217;, VIII,B and II(7), domestic jurisdiction.
1171



[Page XLIV]June 6
Minutes of the Sixteenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 6, 1945, 4:40 p.m.VIII, C (2) and XII (2), Regional
                            arrangements: agreement reached on text; XI Amendments, Charter article
                            109(3), the calling of a conference for review of the Charter; II(7) and
                            VIII, B, domestic jurisdiction; III, Membership: withdrawal.
1176



June 7
Minutes of the Seventeenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 7, 1945, 3 p.m.VI, C and D, VIII, A, Voting in the
                            Security Council, and draft text of Four-Power interpretive statement on
                            voting; proposed seat of the Preparatory Commission.
1189



June 8
Minutes of the Sixty-Sixth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, June 8, 1945, 9:02
                                a.m.V, B(8), General Assembly&#8217;s power to consider reports
                            by the Security Council; XI, Amendments, calling of a special conference
                            to revise the Charter; VI, C, Yalta formula controversy and text of
                            statement of the Soviet Delegation on the veto question; UNCIO:
                            procedure for signing the Charter; Preamble: title of the organization;
                            III, and V, B(3), Membership: expulsion and withdrawal; Charter XII,
                            Trusteeship, articles 76(b), 80, and 86(1), and text of statement of
                            views by Secretary Ickes; UNCIO:
                            Delegation&#8217;s report to President Truman.
1197



June 8
Minutes of the Eighteenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 8, 1945, 9:30 p.m.XI, Amendments: calling a general
                            conference to review the Charter, and the rights of withdrawal.
1211



June 9
Minutes of the Sixty-Seventh Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, June 9, 1945,
                                9:02 a.m.Charter article 86, Trusteeship Council:
                            membership; Charter articles 1(2), 76(b), and 55, use of the language of
                            the Atlantic Charter with respect to self-determination; Preamble; XI,
                            Amendments: Soviet proposal for a withdrawal provision.
1222



June 9
Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. O. Benjamin Gerig, Member of the
                                United States DelegationCharter article 80(2),
                            Trusteeship: delay or postponement of agreements, and Soviet eligibility
                            as a potential administering authority.
1235



June 11
Minutes of the Sixty-Eighth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, June 11, 1945,
                                12:06 p.m.Italy: question of admission to UNCIO; VI, C,
                            Voting; XI, Amendments: withdrawal from the UN, draft statement on
                            withdrawal presented by Mr. Dulles; UNCIO: abstention from any vote; VIII,C,
                            Regional arrangements: the Rapporteur&#8217;s report.
1236



June 11
Minutes of the Nineteenth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 11, 1945, 3 p.m.Interim Arrangements (Preparatory
                            Commission); VI, C, voting procedure; abstention from voting in the
                            Security Council; abstention from voting under VIII, A, Pacific
                            settlement of disputes; XI, Amendments: questions of withdrawal and
                            special conference to review the Charter.
1256



[Page XLV]June 12
Minutes of the Sixty-Ninth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, June 12, 1945,
                                9:05 a.m.XI, Amendments: withdrawal.
1266



June 12
Minutes of the Twentieth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 12, 1945, 6 p.m.UNCIO: procedure for preparation and
                            signing of five-language texts of the Charter; VIII, B and Charter 2(7),
                            Domestic Jurisdiction.
1269



June 13
Minutes of the Seventieth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, June 13, 1945, 9
                            a.m.XI, Amendments: withdrawal; XII (1), transitional
                            arrangements; VIII,B and Charter article 2(7), Domestic Jurisdiction;
                            Charter article 47(4), Military Staff Committee consultations with
                            regional agencies; Charter XII, Trusteeship.
1273



June 13
Minutes of the Twenty-First Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 13, 1945, 2:30 p.m.UNCIO: Procedure for signing
                            language texts of the Charter; XII(1) Transitional arrangements;
                            VI,D(2), and Charter article 47(4), Threats to the peace: Military Staff
                            Committee; V,B(1), General Assembly rights to discuss any matter within
                            sphere of international relations; XI, Amendments: withdrawal, draft
                            statement of views.
1280



June 14
Minutes of the Seventy-First Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Thursday, June 14,
                                1945XI, Charter amendments; withdrawal; X, Secretariat:
                            Secretary General; Charter article 2(7), Domestic jurisdiction; Charter
                            article 6, Membership: Expulsion; Charter XII, Trusteeship; tentative
                            Conference schedule.
1288



June 15
Minutes of the Seventy-Second Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, June 15, 1945, 9
                                a.m.XI, Amendment procedure; Preamble; Charter XII,
                            Trusteeship: Egyptian amendment on termination and transfer of trust
                            areas.
1302



June 16
Minutes of the Seventy-Third Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, June 16, 1945,
                                9:04 a.m.XI, Amendments: Re visionary conference; V, B,
                            General Assembly: Right to discuss any matter within sphere of
                            international relations; Interim arrangements.
1304



June 16
Minutes of the Twenty-Second Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 16, 1945, 9:45 a.m.XI, Amendments: re visionary
                            conference; Interim arrangements; V, B, General Assembly right to
                            discuss any matter within sphere of international relations; XII(1),
                            Transitional arrangements.
1313



June 16
Minutes of the Seventy-Fourth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, June 16, 1945,
                                7:30 p.m.V,B(1), General Assembly, right to discuss any
                            matter within sphere of international relations.
1328



[Page XLVI]June 17
Minutes of the Twenty-Third Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 17, 1945, 6 p.m.XII, Transitional arrangements; X(1),
                            Secretariat: election of deputy secretaries general; VIII,B, VI,D(2),
                            and Charter article 47(4), Threats to the peace: Peruvian amendment
                            concerning consultation by the Military Staff Committee with regional
                            agencies; V,B(1), right of discussion in the General Assembly; VI,C(3),
                            Charter article 27(3), Security Council, voting.
1331



June 18
Minutes of the Seventy-Fifth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Monday, June 18, 1945, 9
                                a.m.Charter XII, Trusteeship; IX, Economic and social
                            cooperation: opium traffic, International Labor Organization; V,B (1),
                            General Assembly, powers of discussion; V,B(3), and Charter article 108,
                            Membership: expulsion, and withdrawal; XI, Amendments: re visionary
                            conference; X, Secretariat: term of Secretary-General; VII,
                            International Court of Justice; VIII,A(7), Domestic jurisdiction.
1339



June 18
Minutes of the Twenty-Fourth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 18, 1945, 12 noonV,B, General Assembly&#8217;s right of
                            discussion.
1348



June 18
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateText of telegram from Secretary
                                Stettinius to be transmitted
                            to the Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) requesting that he discuss with Mr. Molotov the status of the problem
                            concerning V,B(1), the General Assembly&#8217;s right of discussion.
1353



June 19
Minutes of the Seventy-Sixth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Tuesday, June 19, 1945,
                                9:03 a.m.UNCIO: Military endorsement of the Charter in its
                            military aspects; V,B(1), Discussion by the General Assembly; Charter
                            XII, Trusteeship; Spain: question of participation in the UN;
                            representation of Poland at the Conference; VIII,A(2), Pacific
                            Settlement of Disputes; and XII(2), Transitional Arrangements: recourse
                            of enemy states to the General Assembly or the Security Council;
                            Preamble.
1355



June 19
Minutes of the Twenty-Fifth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 19, 1945, 7:30 a.m.XII(2), Transitional arrangements
                            and VIII,A(2), Pacific settlement of disputes: Greek amendment
                            concerning right of enemy states to have recourse to the General
                            Assembly and the Security Council; XI, Amendments: withdrawal from
                            membership; VI,B(2), Security Council: Functions.
1367



June 19
Minutes of the Twenty-Sixth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 19, 1945, 5 p.m.V,B(1), General Assembly, right of
                            discussion; VIII,B, and VI,B(2), functions of Security Council; IX,
                            Functions of Economic and Social Council.
1377



[Page XLVII]June 19
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateDraft text on V,B,
                            General Assembly, right of discussion, by Mr. Molotov.
1382



June 19
Minutes of the Twenty-Seventh Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 19, 1945, 8:45 p.m.V,B(1), General Assembly, right of
                            discussion.
1382



June 19
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateV,B, General Assembly, right of
                            discussion: proposed change in Soviet text, to be transmitted to Mr.
                                Molotov.
1387



June 20
Minutes of the Seventy-Seventh Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, June 20,
                                1945Status of the UNCIO Committees (General Assembly&#8217;s
                            powers; Preamble; right of recourse by enemy states to General Assembly;
                            peaceful settlement of disputes; expulsion from membership); Charter
                            XII, Trusteeship; IX,A(1) opium traffic; V,B(1) General Assembly&#8217;s
                            discussion right.
1388



June 20
Minutes of the Twenty-Eighth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 20, 1945, 12:30 p.m.V,B(1), General Assembly right of
                            discussion: Soviet agreement on text of paragraph one.
1397



June 20
The Acting Chairman of the Soviet Delegation
                                (Gromyko) to the Chairman of the
                                United States Delegation (Stettinius)Charter XII,
                            Soviet interest in territories under trusteeship.
1398



June 21
Minutes of the Twenty-Ninth Five-Power Informal
                                Consultative Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco,
                                June 21, 1945, 12:35 p.m.Preparatory Commission; London
                            the proposed seat of Commission.
1399



June 23
Minutes of the Seventy-Eighth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, June 23, 1945,
                                10:36 a.m.Situation in Poland; UNCIO plans (final
                            Commission sessions; report to the President) drafts of Charter and
                            Court Statutes: drafting changes; foreign language texts; seal to be
                            used in binding five language texts of Charter.
1404



June 23
Minutes of the Seventy-Ninth Meeting of the United
                                States Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Saturday, June 23, 1945,
                                4:15 p.m.UNCIO: Arrangements for signing the
                            Charter.
1425



June 23
The Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Chairman of the Soviet Delegation (Gromyko)Charter XII,
                            Territorial trusteeship: eligibility of Soviet Union as potential
                            administering authority.
1428



June 25
Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Hayden Raynor, Special Assistant to
                                the Secretary of StateSecretary Stettinius informed by Ambassador
                                Gromyko of Soviet disapproval
                            of statement in the Committee&#8217;s report on withdrawal from
                            membership.
1429



[Page XLVIII]June 26
The Secretary of the Interior (Ickes) to the Chairman of the United States Delegation
                                (Stettinius)Charter XII, Trusteeship.
1430



June 26
The Secretary of War (Stimson) and the
                                Secretary of the Navy (Forrestal) to the Secretary
                                of StateMilitary opinion on draft charter.
1430



June 26
The Secretary of State to President
                                    TrumanTransmission of certified
                            copy of Charter of the United Nations with Statute of the International
                            Court of Justice.
1431



EFFORTS OF THE UNITED STATES IN THE PREPARATORY COMMISSION OF
                    THE UNITED NATIONS TO EFFECT AN EARLY ESTABLISHMENT OF THE UNITED NATIONS
                    ORGANIZATION; SELECTION OF THE UNITED STATES AS THE PERMANENT LOCATION FOR THE
                    SEAT OF THE ORGANIZATION


Date
Paper
Page



Editorial NoteBackground information
                            relative to establishment and purposes of the Preparatory
                            Commission.
1433



1945 Aug. 15
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Guidance for participation in major
                            policy decisions of the Executive Committee of the Preparatory
                            Commission.
1434



Aug. 23
Memorandum Prepared by the United States
                                Representative on the Preparatory Commission (Stettinius)Matters to be reviewed with the
                            President and the Secretary of State.
1437



Aug. 24
Memorandum by Mr. Charles P.
                                    Noyes, Assistant to the United States Representative
                                on the Preparatory Commission (Stettinius)Meeting of
                            President Truman, Secretary
                                Byrnes, and Mr. Stettinius.
1439



Aug. 24
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Desirability of informal consultations
                            and agreement among the Five Great Powers.
1440



Aug. 27
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateAgreement by
                            representatives of the Five Great Powers to hold informal
                            meetings.
1441



Sept. 5
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateSummary of various preliminary
                            conversations with Bevin, Cadogan, Attlee, and others.
1442



Sept. 7
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateConversation with Gromyko about work of the Executive
                            Committee, schedule for future meetings, and permanent location;
                            conversation with Koo.
1444



[Page XLIX]Sept. 13
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateResolution introduced in Executive
                            Committee to expedite establishing the United Nations.
1445



Sept. 14
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateDiscussions looking toward agreement on
                            the time and place of the first meeting of the General Assembly.
1446



Sept. 18
The Acting Secretary of State to the United States
                                Representative on the Preparatory Commission (Stettinius)Views on the selection of a
                            Secretary-General and the determination of his tenure of office.
1448



Sept. 19
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateInformal discussion by representatives
                            of the Big Five on various organizational problems.
1449



Sept. 20
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateReport for the President on the approval
                            by the Executive Committee of the time schedule proposed by the United
                            States; question of permanent location of U.N. headquarters.
1451



Sept. 28
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Acting
                                Secretary of StateInformal meeting of Big Five; discussion
                            of presidency of Security Council, Secretariat, Secretary-General, and
                            permanent location.
1452



Oct. 3
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to President
                                    Truman and the Secretary of
                            StateRecommendation by the Executive Committee that permanent
                            headquarters of the United Nations should be located in the United
                            States.
1453



Oct. 5
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to President
                                    Truman and the Secretary of
                            StateProblem of specific location of U.N. headquarters in the
                            United States.
1454



Oct. 9
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Secretary
                                of StateDiscussion by Big Five representatives of
                            candidates for Secretary General and for president of Preparatory
                            Commission; question of permanent location.
1455



Oct. 11
Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Leo Pasvolsky, Special Assistant to
                                the Secretary of StateDiscussion with
                                Gore-Booth on the future work of the Executive
                            Committee and British views on permanent location.
1457



Oct. 12
The United States Representative on the Preparatory
                                Commission (Stettinius) to the Secretary
                                of StateSuggestion by Massigli that
                            the organizing meeting of the United Nations be postponed until January;
                            recommendation by Stettinius
                            that the United States continue to press for a December meeting.
1458



[Page L]Oct. 24
Memorandum of ConversationDiscussion by
                                Byrnes, Halifax, and Noel-Baker regarding
                            permanent location of the United Nations.
1459



Oct. 24
The Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic
                                RepresentativesNotification that the U.N. Charter is now
                            in force.
1461



Oct. 27
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Secretary of StateAgreement by Executive Committee to
                            dates for convening meetings of Preparatory Commission and General
                            Assembly.
1462



Nov. 10
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Secretary of StateSynopsis of principal issues
                            developed in meetings of the Executive Committee.
1462



Nov. 15
Secretary&#8217;s Staff Committee Working Paper (SC&#8211;171/8)Tentative U.S. slates for various
                            posts in the United Nations.
1475



Nov. 21
The Secretary of State to the Acting United States
                                Representative on the Preparatory Commission (Stevenson), at LondonNotification that
                                Bevin has informed Byrnes
                            that the United Kingdom will continue to argue that the site of the U.N.
                            should be in Europe.
1479



Nov. 28
The Secretary of State to the Acting United States
                                Representative on the Preparatory Commission (Stevenson), at LondonAuthorization to deny reports that
                            the United States does not wish to have the United Nations headquarters
                            in its territory.
1479



Nov. 28
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Secretary of StateSummary of developments relating to
                            the question of permanent location.
1480



Nov. 30
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Secretary of StateEvaluation of British efforts to
                            locate the U.N. headquarters in Europe.
1484



Dec. 6
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Secretary of StateAgreement by the other American
                            Republics to favor the United States as site for the United
                            Nations.
1485



Dec. 7
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Secretary of StateStatement of the U.S. position on
                            the question of the location of the permanent headquarters of the United
                            Nations.
1486



Dec. 9
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Secretary of StateAssessment of rumors that the United
                            States does not want the headquarters of the United Nations; probable
                            votes: 27 or 28 for the United States, 13 for Europe, several
                            uncertain.
1486



[Page LI]Dec. 15
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateAccount of proceedings
                            leading to decision that the permanent location of the United Nations
                            should be in the United States.
1488



Dec. 17
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateInquiry by Gromyko about U.S. views on
                                Simic of Yugoslavia as possible Secretary
                            General.
1491



Dec. 19
The Acting Secretary of State to the Acting United
                                States Representative on the Preparatory Commission (Stevenson)Suggestion that Gromyko be informed that the United
                            States will base its preferences for Secretary General on individual
                            competence rather than geographical area; the question should be
                            discussed on a five power basis.
1492



Dec. 23
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateAdjournment of the
                            Preparatory Commission.
1493



Dec. 23
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateMain changes by the
                            Preparatory Commission in the report of the Executive Committee.
1494



Dec. 24
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateReport on recent individual
                            talks with Koo,
                                Noel-Baker, and Gromyko on candidates for Secretary General and
                            President of General Assembly and on membership in Security
                            Council.
1504



Dec. 24
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StatePreliminary observations
                            concerning presidency of General Assembly and the Secretary
                            General.
1505



Dec. 24
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateDiscussion with Gromyko, Koo, and Webster
                            regarding Secretary General, membership in Security Council and ECOSOC,
                            and presidency of General Assembly.
1506



Dec. 27
The Acting United States Representative on the
                                Preparatory Commission (Stevenson) to
                                the Acting Secretary of StateAvailability of Trygve Lie for consideration as
                            President of the General Assembly.
1509



PARTICIPATION BY THE UNITED STATES IN THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE
                    UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION


Date
Paper
Page


1945 Apr. 11
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Transmission of draft constitution for
                            UNESCO.
1510



[Page LII]Apr. 24
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateSatisfactory
                            progress of American draft constitution for UNESCO.
1511



June 12
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Suggestion that United Kingdom be asked
                            to call a conference on the basis of the draft constitution.
1512



July 13
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateApproval by
                            conference of Allied Ministers of Education of draft constitution as
                            basis for agenda for United Nations Educational and Cultural
                            Conference.
1513



July 13
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateBritish
                            announcement of forthcoming conference.
1513



Sept. 29
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                the United Kingdom (Winant)Observations on draft proposals.
1514



Oct. 10
The Charg&#233; in the United Kingdom (Gallman) to the
                                Secretary of StateSoviet view that the conference should
                            properly be called by the United Nations rather than by United Kingdom,
                            which will defend propriety of present arrangement.
1515



Oct. 16
The Secretary of State to the Charg&#233; in the United
                                Kingdom (Gallman)Procedural arrangements.
1516



Nov. 5
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateRecommendation that
                            United States take initiative to have UNESCO give suitable attention to
                            educational and cultural problems in non-self-governing
                            territories.
1517



Nov. 5
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                Soviet Union (Harriman)Authorization to suggest to
                            Soviet Foreign Office that it reconsider its previous decision and send
                            a delegation to the conference.
1518



Nov. 8
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the
                                United Kingdom (Winant)Disapproval of plans to take initiative
                            at this time in seeking a UNESCO conference on educational and cultural
                            problems in non-self-governing territories.
1519



Nov. 9
The Department of State to the British
                            EmbassyExpression of the view that UNESCO should be formed by
                            intergovernmental agreement rather than through a resolution of the
                            General Assembly.
1519



Nov. 13
The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (Harriman) to the Secretary of StateRecommendation
                            against approaching the Soviet Foreign Office on the question of sending
                            a delegation to the conference.
1521



[Page LIII]Nov. 15
The Ambassador in the United Kingdom
                                    (Winant) to the Secretary of StateSummary of
                            proceedings and decisions of the UNESCO Conference.
1521



Dec. 5
Memorandum by the Assistant Secreatry of State
                                    (Benton) to the Secretary of StateTransmittal of
                            summary report on the London Conference, November 1&#8211;16, 1945.
1523



PARTICIPATION BY THE UNITED STATES IN THE SESSIONS OF THE
                    INTERNATIONAL LABOR CONFERENCE AND GOVERNING BODY


Date
Paper
Page


1945 500.C 115/7&#8211;1145 (undated)
Report by the Chief of the Division of International
                                Labor, Social and Health Affairs (Mulliken)Report on the
                            95th Session of the Governing Body of the International Labor
                            Organization.
1530



July 6
Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of
                                International Labor, Social and Health Affairs (Mulliken)Presence of a representative of the
                            Polish Government at the meeting in Quebec of the Governing Body of the
                            ILO.
1535



July 11
The Ambassador in Belgium (Sawyer) to the
                                Secretary of StateInquiry by Belgian labor leaders
                            concerning American attitude toward the admission of the Soviet Union to
                            the ILO.
1535



Aug. 7
The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                Belgium (Sawyer)Support for renewal of Soviet membership in
                            the ILO.
1536



Sept. 4
The Secretary of State to the Secretary of
                                Labor (Schwellenbach)Notification
                            that it would be premature to invite Bulgaria and Hungary to the
                            International Labor Conference.
1537



Oct. 10
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)Transmittal of instructions from
                            Departments of State and Labor to U.S. Government representatives at
                            96th session of ILO Governing Body.
1537



Oct. 11
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateUnited Kingdom and Canada favor inviting
                            Bulgaria and Hungary to she ILO meeting.
1539



Oct. 12
The Secretary of State to Miss Frances
                                    PerkinsTransmittal of instructions to the
                            U.S. Government Delegation to the International Labor Conference at
                            Paris.
1539



Oct. 24
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateRequest for instructions on pending
                            articles.
1551



Oct. 26
The Ambassador in France (Caffery) to the
                                Secretary of StateReport of stand taken by U.S. delegation
                            on question of amendments to ILO constitution.
1551



Nov. 1
The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in
                                France (Caffery)Instructions on pending articles.
1552



[Page LIV]Dec. 5
Memorandum by Mr. Edward Miller,
                                    Jr., Special Assistant to the Under Secretary of
                                State (Acheson), to the Under
                                Secretary of StateRecommendation that authority for U.S.
                            participation in the ILO (under its constitution, as amended) be
                            included in the Omnibus Bill now being prepared for submission to the
                            Congress.
1553



Dec. 21
Memorandum by the Legal Adviser (Hackworth) to Mr. Edward Miller, Jr.,
                                Special Assistant to the Under Secretary of State (Acheson)No
                            objection to the proposed amendment of the Omnibus Bill.
1555



SPONSORSHIP BY THE DEPARTMENT OF STATE OF LEGISLATION RESULTING
                    IN THE INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS IMMUNITIES ACT OF 1945


Date
Paper
Page


1945 Apr. 13
The Director General of the United Nations Relief
                                and Rehabilitation Administration (Lehman) to the Secretary of
                                StateRequest for legislative and administrative action by
                            the Government of the United States.
1557



July 2
The Acting Secretary of State to the Attorney
                                General (Clark)Transmittal of a draft bill granting
                            certain privileges and immunities to international organizations.
1558



Sept. 11
Mr. Edward G. Miller, Jr.,
                                Special Assistant to the Under Secretary of State (Acheson), to the Assistant Solicitor General (Judson)Estimate that about
                            3,000 persons would be affected by the proposed bill.
1560



Sept. 18
The Acting Secretary of the Treasury
                                    (Gaston) to the Secretary of StateApproval of the
                            proposed bill, subject to certain changes.
1561



Oct. 2
The Attorney General (Clark) to the Secretary of StateThe Department of
                            Justice will not oppose the legislation but offers certain
                            suggestions.
1562



Oct. 4
The Acting Secretary of State to the Attorney
                                General (Clark)Appreciation for the agreement by
                            the Department of Justice not to oppose the legislation; replies to
                            specific suggestions for changes.
1565














General: The United Nations


Preface

Introductory note

List of papers

Guide to discussions of Dumbarton Oaks proposals and corresponding articles of
                    the Charter of the United Nations, 1944&#8211;1945

The United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco,
                    California, April 25&#8211;June 26, 1945


Efforts of the United States in the Preparatory Commission of the United
                    Nations to effect an early establishment of the United Nations Organization;
                    selection of the United States as the permanent location for the seat of the
                        Organization (Documents 321-359)
Participation by the United States in the establishment of the United Nations
                    Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (Documents 360-374)
Participation by the United States in the sessions of the International Labor
                    Conference and Governing Body (Documents 375-387)
Sponsorship by the Department of State of legislation resulting in the
                    International Organizations Immunities Act of 1945 (Documents 388-393)
Index








Persons

Acheson, Dean
                                    G.Attlee,
                                    Clement R.Bidault,
                                    GeorgesBohlen,
                                    Charles E.Bonnet,
                                    HenriCadogan, Sir
                                    AlexanderCoville,
                                    CabotDulles, John
                                    FosterDunn, James
                                    C.Eden,
                                    AnthonyGerig, O.
                                    BenjaminGrew, Joseph
                                    C.Gromyko,
                                    Andrey AndreyevichHackworth,
                                    Green H.HalifaxHarriman, W.
                                    AverellHartley,
                                    Robert W.Hiss,
                                    AlgerHull,
                                    CordellIckes, Harold
                                    L.Kerr, Sir
                                    Archibald ClarkKoo, V. K.
                                    WellingtonLie,
                                    TrygveMacLeish,
                                    ArchibaldMolotov,
                                    Vyacheslav MikhailovichMulliken, Otis
                                    E.Pasvolsky,
                                    LeoRaynor, G.
                                    HaydenSandifer,
                                    Durward V.Stassen,
                                    Commander Harold E.Stettinius,
                                    Edward R., Jr.Stevenson,
                                    Adlai E.Taussig,
                                    Charles W.Vandenberg,
                                    Arthur H.Webster,
                                    Charles Kingsley




Abbreviations &amp; Terms















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov/about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about</value><value>https://history.state.gov/tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov/conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov/education</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov/open</value><value>https://history.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov../frus1945v01</value><value>https://history.state.govpapers</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/introduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/guide</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_10</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_12</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_14</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_18</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_22</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_23</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XVI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_27</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_34</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_35</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_39</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_46</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_58</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_60</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XVII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_67</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_68</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_69</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_70</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_70</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_71</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_72</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_72</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_73</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_73</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_74</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_75</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_76</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XVIII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_77</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_80</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_81</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_82</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_83</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_83</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_84</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_85</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_86</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_86</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_87</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_89</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_90</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XIX</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_91</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_93</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_95</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_96</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_97</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_98</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_99</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_100</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_100</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_101</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_102</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_103</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XX</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_103</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_104</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_105</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_106</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_106</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_108</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_109</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_110</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_111</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_111</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_113</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_114</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_119</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_116</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_120</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_121</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_121</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_124</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_125</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_126</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_127</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_128</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_128</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_131</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_132</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_134</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_138</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_140</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_141</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_142</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_144</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_145</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_146</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_146</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_147</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_148</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_148</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_150</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_151</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_152</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXIII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_153</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_154</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_154</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_156</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_156</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_158</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_159</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_160</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_160</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_161</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_162</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_163</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_164</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_165</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_165</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXIV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_166</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_168</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_174</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_175</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_179</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_179</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_180</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_181</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_183</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_189</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_192</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_193</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_193</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_194</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_195</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_196</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_198</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_199</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_201</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_203</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_204</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_206</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_207</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_208</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_209</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_211</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_214</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_214</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXVI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_215</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_225</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_226</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_227</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_235</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_240</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_240</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_241</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_259</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_269</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_269</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXVII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_278</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_281</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_283</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_288</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_289</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_290</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_291</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_291</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_292</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_295</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_296</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_310</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXVIII</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXIX</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_355</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_360</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_361</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_362</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_363</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_374</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_379</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_379</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_380</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_385</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXX</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_386</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_402</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_407</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_414</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_444</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_445</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_452</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_459</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_460</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_472</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_473</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_481</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_485</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_486</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_488</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_488</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_499</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_500</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_505</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_506</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_509</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_511</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_528</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_548</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_558</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_562</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXIII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_574</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_581</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_588</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_598</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_603</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_607</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_610</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXIV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_612</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_615</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_628</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_631</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_640</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_641</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_650</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_652</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_652</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_654</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_657</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_663</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_674</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_691</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_706</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_707</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_712</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXVI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_719</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_730</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_737</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_740</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_749</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_749</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_758</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_761</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_768</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXVII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_774</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_778</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_790</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_799</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_803</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXVIII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_812</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_813</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_823</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_825</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_826</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_831</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_837</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_847</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XXXIX</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_849</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_862</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_873</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_889</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_892</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_911</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XL</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_926</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_935</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_954</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_968</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_974</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_989</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1011</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1022</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1056</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1071</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1087</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1094</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1106</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1117</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1119</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1119</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1120</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1131</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1136</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLIII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1137</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1145</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1152</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1159</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1159</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1160</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1170</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1171</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLIV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1176</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1189</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1197</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1211</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1222</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1235</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1236</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1256</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1266</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1269</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1273</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1280</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1288</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1302</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1304</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1313</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1328</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLVI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1331</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1339</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1348</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1353</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1355</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1367</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1377</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLVII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1382</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1382</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1387</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1388</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1397</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1398</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1399</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1404</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1425</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1428</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1429</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLVIII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1430</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1430</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1431</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1433</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1434</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1437</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1439</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1440</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1441</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1442</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1444</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_XLIX</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1445</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1446</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1448</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1449</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1451</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1452</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1453</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1454</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1455</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1457</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1458</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_L</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1459</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1461</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1462</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1462</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1475</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1479</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1479</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1480</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1484</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1485</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1486</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1486</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_LI</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1488</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1491</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1492</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1493</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1494</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1504</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1505</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1506</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1509</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1510</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_LII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1511</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1512</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1513</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1513</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1514</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1515</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1516</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1517</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1518</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1519</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1519</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1521</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_LIII</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1521</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1523</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1530</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1535</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1535</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1536</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1537</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1537</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1539</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1539</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1551</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1551</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1552</value><value>https://history.state.govpg_LIV</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1553</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1555</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1557</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1558</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1560</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1561</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1562</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/pg_1565</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/preface</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/introduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/papers</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/guide</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp3</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp4</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp5</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/index</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_ADG1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_ACR1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_BG1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_BCE1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_BH1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_CSA1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_CC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_DJF1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_DJC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_EA1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_GOB1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_GJC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_GAA1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_HGH1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_H1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_HWA1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_HRW1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_HA1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_HC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_IHL1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_KSAC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_KVKW1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_LT1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_MA1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_MVM1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_MOE1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_PL1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_RGH1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_SDV1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_SCHE1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_SERJ1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_SAE1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_TCW1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_VAH1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_WCK1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/search</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.govmailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/papers</id></item>