<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item><bodyText>

Learn about the beta
























MenuMenu



Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States

About the Foreign Relations Series

Current Status of the Foreign Relations Series

History of the Foreign Relations Series

Ebooks Initiative



Department History

Overview

A Short History of the Department

Biographies of the Secretaries of
                                        State

Principal Officers and Chiefs of
                                        Mission

Travels of the Secretary of State

Travels of the President

Visits by Foreign Heads of State

World War I and the Department

Buildings of the Department of State

U.S. Diplomatic Couriers



Key Milestones

Overview

1750&#8211;1775

1776&#8211;1783

1784&#8211;1800

1801&#8211;1829

1830&#8211;1860

1861&#8211;1865

1866&#8211;1898

1899&#8211;1913

1914&#8211;1920

1921&#8211;1936

1937&#8211;1945

1945&#8211;1952

1953&#8211;1960

1961&#8211;1968

1969&#8211;1976

1977&#8211;1980

1981&#8211;1988

1989&#8211;1992

1993&#8211;2000



Guide to Countries

Guide to Country Recognition and Relations

World Wide Diplomatic Archives Index



More Resources

About Us

Browse Resources by Subject Tag

Conferences

Contact Us

Developer Resources &amp; APIs

Educational Resources

Frequently Asked Questions

Open Government Initiative














Home

Historical Documents

Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic Papers,
                    1945, General: The United Nations, Volume I

List of persons






Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic Papers,
                    1945, General: The United Nations, Volume I








List of persons1


Acheson, Dean
                                    G., Assistant Secretary of State.
Alling, Paul
                                    H., Deputy Director, Office of Near Eastern and
                                African Affairs; Political and Liaison Officer for Europe, United
                                States Delegation.
Andrade,
                                    Victor, Bolivian Ambassador in the United States;
                                Acting Chairman of the Bolivian Delegation.
Armstrong,
                                    Hamilton Fish, Special Adviser to the Secretary of
                                State; Adviser, United States Delegation.
Attlee,
                                    Clement R., British Deputy Prime Minister; British
                                Delegate.
Badawi, Abdel
                                    Hamid Pasha, Egyptian Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Egyptian Delegation.
Bailey, Prof.
                                    K. H., Adviser, Australian Delegation.
Basdevant,
                                    Jules, French Representative, Committee of Jurists;
                                French Assistant Delegate.
Belt Ram&#237;rez,
                                    Guillermo, Cuban Ambassador in the United States;
                                Chairman of the Cuban Delegation.
Bidault,
                                    Georges, Minister for Foreign Affairs of the
                                Provisional Government of France; Chairman of the French
                                Delegation.
Blaisdell,
                                    Donald C, Associate Chief, Division of International
                                Security Affairs; Technical Expert, United States Delegation.
Bloom,
                                    Sol, Representative, New York; Chairman of the House
                                Committee on Foreign Affairs; United States Delegate.
Bohlen,
                                    Charles E., Assistant to the Secretary of State for
                                White House Liaison; Political and Liaison Officer for Europe,
                                United States Delegation.
Boncour. SeePaul-Boncour.
Bonilla Lara,
                                    Alvaro, Costa Rican Delegate.
Bonnet,
                                    Henri, Ambassador in the United States; French
                                Delegate.
Bouchinet-Serreules, Claude, Technical
                                Adviser and Expert, French Delegation.
Bowman,
                                    Isaiah, Special Adviser to the Secretary of State;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Brannan,
                                    Charles F., Assistant Secretary of Agriculture;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Brunauer,
                                    Esther C., Division of International Organization
                                Affairs; Technical Expert, United States Delegation.
Bundy, Harvey
                                    H., Special Assistant to the Secretary of War.
Byington,
                                    Homer M., Jr., Executive Assistant to the Special
                                Assistant in Charge of Press Relations
                                    (McDermott); Press Officer, United States
                                Delegation.
C&#225;ceres,
                                    Juli&#225;n R., Honduran Ambassador in the United States;
                                Chairman of the Honduran Delegation.
Cadogan, Sir
                                    Alexander, British Permanent Under-Secretary of State
                                for Foreign Affairs; Adviser, British Delegation.
Capel-Dunn,
                                    Colonel Dennis Cuthbert, Member of the British
                                Delegation.
Castillo
                                        N&#225;jera, Francisco, Mexican Ambassador in the
                                United States; Mexican Auxiliary Delegate.
Clark
                                    Kerr. SeeKerr.
Connally,
                                    Tom, Senator, Texas; Chairman of the Senate Committee
                                on Foreign Relations; United States Delegate.
Correa, Major
                                    Mathias F., Special Assistant to the Secretary of the
                                Navy.
Coville,
                                    Cabot, Foreign Service Officer, temporarily detailed
                                to Office of Special Political Affairs; Technical Expert, United
                                States Delegation.
Cox,
                                    Oscar, Deputy Administrator, Foreign Economic
                                Administration; Adviser, United States Delegation.
Cranborne, The Viscount, Secretary of State for
                                Dominion Affairs; British Delegate.
Dejean,
                                    Maurice, Assistant Delegate, French
                                Delegation.
Dennery,
                                    Etienne, Technical Adviser and Expert, French
                                Delegation.
Dennis,
                                    Lieutenant Commander Lloyd, Division of Public
                                Liaison; Special Assistant to the Public Liaison Officer, United
                                States Delegation.
Dickey, John
                                    S., Director, Office of Public Affairs; Public
                                Liaison Officer, United States Delegation.
Dulles, John
                                    Foster, Adviser, United States Delegation.
Dunn, James
                                    C., Assistant Secretary of State; Adviser, United
                                States Delegation.
Duparc. SeeFouques-Duparc.
Eaton, Charles
                                    A., Representative, New Jersey; United States
                                Delegate.
Eden,
                                    Anthony, British Secretary of State for Foreign
                                Affairs; Chairman of British Delegation.
Embick,
                                    Lieutenant General Stanley D., Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Evatt, Herbert
                                    Vere, Australian Minister for External Affairs;
                                Australian Delegate.
Fahy,
                                    Charles, Solicitor General of the United States;
                                Adviser, Committee of Jurists; Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Fairchild,
                                    Major General Muir S., Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Fern&#225;ndez,
                                    Joaqu&#237;n, Chilean Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Chilean Delegation.
Fitzmaurice,
                                    Gerald Gray, Legal Adviser, British
                                Delegation.
Fortas,
                                    Abe, Under Secretary of the Interior; Adviser, United
                                States Delegation.
Fosdick,
                                    Dorothy, Division of International Organization
                                Affairs; Special Assistant to the Secretary-General of the United
                                States Delegation.
Fouques-Duparc, Jacques, Secretary-General,
                                French Delegation.
Fraser,
                                    Peter, Prime Minister and Minister of External
                                Affairs; Chairman of Delegation of New Zealand.
Gallagher,
                                    Manuel C., Peruvian Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Peruvian Delegation.
Gates,
                                    Artemus, Assistant Secretary of the Navy; Adviser,
                                United States Delegation.
Gerig, O.
                                    Benjamin, Chief, Division of Dependent Area Affairs;
                                Deputy Secretary-General of the United States Delegation and one of
                                the three Chief Technical Experts of the Delegation.
Gildersleeve,
                                    Virginia C., Dean, Barnard College; United States
                                Delegate.
Golunsky,
                                    Sergey Aleksandrovich, Soviet Professor of
                                International Law; Adviser, United Nations Committee of Jurists;
                                Soviet Delegate.
Gorse,
                                    Georges, Technical Adviser and Expert, French
                                Delegation.
Grew, Joseph
                                    C., Under Secretary of State.
Gromyko,
                                    Andrey Andreyevich, Soviet Ambassador in the United
                                States; Soviet Delegate; Acting Chairman of the Soviet
                                Delegation.
Guerrero, J.
                                    Gustavo, of El Salvador, President, Permanent Court
                                of International Justice; unofficial observer for the Court at the
                                Conference.
Hackworth,
                                    Green H., Legal Adviser; Adviser, United Spates
                                Relegation; U.S. Representative, Committee of Jurists; Chairman,
                                Advisory Committee of Jurists.
Halifax, The Earl of, British Ambassador in the
                                United States; British Delegate; Acting Chairman of the British
                                Delegation.
Hamilton,
                                    Colonel P. M., Technical Expert, United States
                                Delegation.
Harriman, W.
                                    Averell, American Ambassador the Soviet Union;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Hartley,
                                    Robert W., Executive Assistant, Office of the Special
                                Assistant to the Secretary of State for International Organization
                                and Security Affairs (Pasvolsky); Technical Expert, United States
                                Delegation.
Hepburn,
                                    Admiral Arthur J., Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Hertford,
                                    Brigadier General Kenner, Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Hickerson,
                                    John D., Deputy Director, Office of European Affairs;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Hiss,
                                    Alger, Director, Office of Special Political Affairs
                                (Deputy Director, November 1944 to March 1945); Secretary-General,
                                International Secretariat.
Holmes,
                                    Brigadier General Julius C., Assistant Secretary of
                                State; Adviser, United States Delegation.
Hoo, Victor
                                    Chi-tsai, Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs; Adviser
                                to Chinese Representative, United Nations Committee of Jurists;
                                Secretary-General, Chinese Delegation.
Hovde, Bryn,
                                    J., Chief, Division of Cultural Cooperation;
                                Technical Expert, United States Delegation.
Hsu
                                    Mo, Chinese Ambassador in Turkey; Adviser,
                                United Nations Committee of Jurists; Adviser, Chinese
                                Delegation.
Hudson, Manley
                                    O., of the United States, Judge of the Permanent
                                Court of International Justice; unofficial observer for the Court at
                                the Conference.
Hull,
                                    Cordell, former Secretary of State; United States
                                Delegate, and Senior Adviser, United States Delegation.
Ickes, Harold
                                    L., Secretary of the Interior.
Jebb, H. M.
                                    Gladwyn, Adviser, British Delegation.
Jessup, Philip
                                    C., Assistant on Judicial Organization; Technical
                                Expert, United States Delegation.
Johnson,
                                    Joseph E., Acting Chief, Division of International
                                Security Affairs; one of the three Chief Technical Experts, United
                                States Delegation.
Kane, R.
                                    Keith, Special Assistant to the Secretary of the
                                Navy; Aide, United States Delegation.
Kerr, Sir
                                    Archibald Clark, British Ambassador in the Soviet
                                Union; Adviser, British Delegation.
King, W. L.
                                    Mackenzie, Prime Minister of Canada; Chairman of
                                Canadian Delegation.
Koo, V. K.
                                    Wellington, Chinese Ambassador in the United Kingdom;
                                Chinese Delegate; Acting Chairman of the Chinese Delegation.
Kotschnig,
                                    Walter M., Associate Chief, Division of International
                                Organization Affairs; Technical Expert, United States
                                Delegation.
Krylov, S.
                                    B., Soviet Professor of International Law; Adviser,
                                United Nations Committee of Jurists; Soviet Delegate.
Kuznetsov,
                                    Vasili Vasilevich, Chairman of the All-Union, Central
                                Council of Trade Unions of the USSR; Soviet Delegate.
Liang,
                                    Yuen-li, Counselor, Chinese Embassy in the United
                                Kingdom; Technical Counselor, Chinese Delegation.
Lie,
                                    Trygve, Norwegian Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Norwegian Delegation.
Liu,
                                    Chieh, Chinese Minister and Counselor of Embassy in
                                the United States; Deputy Secretary-General, Chinese
                                Delegation:
Lleras
                                    Camargo, Alberto, Colombian Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs; Chairman, Colombian Delegation.
Loudon,
                                    Alexander, Netherlands Ambassador in the United
                                States; Vice Chairman, Delegation of the Netherlands.
Lynch; Robert
                                    J., Special Assistant to the Secretary of State;
                                Special Assistant to the Chairman of the United States
                                Delegation.
Mackenzie
                                    King. See King.
MacLeish,
                                    Archibald, Assistant Secretary of State; Adviser,
                                United States Delegation.
Malkin, Sir
                                    William, Legal Adviser, British Delegation.
Martins,
                                    Carlos, Brazilian Ambassador in the United States;
                                Vice Chairman of the Brazilian Delegation.
McCloy, John
                                    J., Assistant Secretary of War; Adviser, United
                                States Delegation.
Molotov,
                                    Vyacheslav Mikhailovich, People&#8217;s Commissar for
                                Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union; Chairman of Soviet
                                Delegation.
Morgenstierne,
                                    Wilhelm M., Norwegian Ambassador in the United
                                States; Acting Chairman of Norwegian Delegation.
Mulliken, Otis
                                    E., Chief, Division of International Labor, Social
                                and Health Affairs; Technical Expert, United States
                                Delegation.
Naggiar,
                                    Paul-Emile, French Assistant Delegate.
Notter, Harley
                                    A., Adviser, Office of Special Political Affairs;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Novikov,
                                    Kirill Vasilyevich, Chief of the British Department
                                of the Soviet Foreign Office; Soviet Delegate; Secretary-General of
                                the Soviet Delegation.
Novikov,
                                    Nikolai Vasilyevich, Minister-Counselor, Soviet
                                Embassy in the United States; Soviet Representative, United Nations
                                Committee of Jurists.
Padilla,
                                    Ezequiel, Mexican Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Mexican Delegation.
Parra-P&#233;rez,
                                    Caracciolo, Venezuelan Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Venezuelan Delegation.
Pasvolsky,
                                    Leo, Special Assistant to the Secretary of State;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Paul-Boncour,
                                    Joseph, French Delegate; Acting Chairman of French
                                Delegation.
Quintanilla,
                                    Luis, Mexican Ambassador; Adviser, Mexican
                                Delegation.
Raynor, G.
                                    Hayden, Special Assistant to the Secretary of State;
                                Special Assistant to the Chairman of the United States
                                Delegation.
Reiff,
                                    Henry, Legal specialist on international
                                Organization.
Rockefeller,
                                    Nelson A., Assistant Secretary of State; Adviser,
                                United States Delegation.
Rodionov,
                                    Rear Admiral Konstantin Konstantinovich, Soviet
                                Delegate.
Rolin,
                                    Lieutenant Colonel Henri, Member of the Belgian
                                Delegation.
Sandifer,
                                    Durward V., Chief, Division of International
                                Organization Affairs; Secretary General of the United States
                                Delegation, and one of the three Chief Technical Experts of the
                                Delegation.
Savage,
                                    Carlton, Assistant to the Secretary of State;
                                Technical Expert, United States Delegation.
Serrato,
                                    Jos&#233;, Uruguayan Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Uruguayan Delegation.
Smuts, Field
                                    Marshal Jan Christian, South African Prime Minister
                                and Minister of External Affairs and Defense; Chairman of Delegation
                                of the Union of South Africa.
Sobolev,
                                    Arkadii Aleksandrovich, Minister-Counselor of the
                                Soviet Embassy in the United Kingdom; Soviet Delegate.
Soong, T.
                                    V., Chinese Minister for Foreign Affairs and Acting
                                President of the Executive Yuan; Chairman of Chinese
                                Delegation.
Spaak,
                                    Paul-Henri, Belgian Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Belgian Delegation.
Stassen,
                                    Commander Harold E., U.S.N.R., United States
                                Delegate.
Stettinius,
                                    Edward R., Jr., Secretary of State; United States
                                Delegate and Chairman of United States Delegation.
Stevenson,
                                    Adlai E., Special Assistant to the Secretary of
                                State; Special Assistant to the Chairman, United States
                                Delegation.
Stinebower,
                                    Leroy D., Deputy Director, Office of International
                                Trade Policy; Adviser, United States Delegation.
Sweetser,
                                    Arthur, Deputy Director, Office of War Information;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Taft, Charles
                                    P., Special Assistant to the Assistant Secretary of
                                State for Economic Affairs (Clayton).
Taussig,
                                    Charles W., Chairman, United States Section,
                                Anglo-American Caribbean Commission; Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Thompson,
                                    Llewellyn E., Acting Chief of the Division of Eastern
                                European Affairs; Political and Liaison Officer for Europe, United
                                States Delegation.
Tomlinson,
                                    George, Assistant Delegate, British
                                Delegation.
Tomlinson,
                                    John D., Specialist, Division of International
                                Organization Affairs; Technical Expert, United States
                                Delegation.
Tracy, Daniel
                                    W., Assistant Secretary of Labor; Adviser, United
                                States Delegation.
Train, Rear
                                    Admiral Harold C., Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Tsarapkin,
                                    Semen Konstantinovich, Chief of the American Section
                                of the Soviet Foreign Office; Soviet Delegate.
Vandenberg,
                                    Arthur H., Senator, Michigan; United States Delegate;
                                Vice Chairman of the United States Delegation.
Vasiliev,
                                    Lieutenant General Alexander Filipovich, Soviet
                                Delegate.
Velloso, Pedro
                                    Le&#227;o, Brazilian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs;
                                Chairman of Brazilian Delegation.
Wang,
                                    Chung-hui, Chinese Representative, United Nations
                                Committee of Jurists.
Waring, Frank
                                    A., Special Assistant to the Secretary of Commerce;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Warren, Avra
                                    M., Director, Office of American Republic Affairs;
                                Adviser, United States Delegation.
Webster,
                                    Charles Kingsley, Adviser, British Delegation.
White, Harry
                                    D., Assistant Secretary of the Treasury; Adviser,
                                United States Delegation.
Wilcox,
                                    Francis O., Assistant to the Congressional members of
                                the United States Delegation.
Willson, Vice
                                    Admiral Russell, Adviser, United States
                                Delegation.
Wrong, H.
                                    H., Canadian Associate Under Secretary of State for
                                External Affairs; Senior Adviser, Canadian Delegation.
Yost, Charles
                                    W., Executive Secretary, Secretary&#8217;s Staff Committee
                                and Coordinating Committee; Special Assistant to Chairman of United
                                States Delegation.
Zarapkin. SeeTsarapkin.




The list of selected
                                names represents those persons who appear prominently and frequently
                                in the course of this documentary account of the
                            Conference.&#8617;













General: The United Nations


Preface

Introductory note

List of papers

Guide to discussions of Dumbarton Oaks proposals and corresponding articles of
                    the Charter of the United Nations, 1944&#8211;1945

The United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco,
                    California, April 25&#8211;June 26, 1945

Introductory note by the Editor

List of persons





Efforts of the United States in the Preparatory Commission of the United
                    Nations to effect an early establishment of the United Nations Organization;
                    selection of the United States as the permanent location for the seat of the
                        Organization (Documents 321-359)
Participation by the United States in the establishment of the United Nations
                    Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (Documents 360-374)
Participation by the United States in the sessions of the International Labor
                    Conference and Governing Body (Documents 375-387)
Sponsorship by the Department of State of legislation resulting in the
                    International Organizations Immunities Act of 1945 (Documents 388-393)
Index








Persons

Fouques-Duparc, JacquesKerr, Sir
                                    Archibald ClarkPasvolsky,
                                    LeoPaul-Boncour,
                                    JosephTsarapkin,
                                    Semen Konstantinovich




Abbreviations &amp; Terms















Learn more
Home

Search

FAQ



Topics
Historical Documents

Department History

Countries

Milestones of U.S. Foreign Relations



Contact
About Us

Contact Us



Imprint
Privacy Notice

External Link Policy

Copyright Info









Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public AffairsUnited States Department of State

history@state.gov

Phone: 202-955-0200
Fax: 202-955-0268







       </bodyText><name /><urls><value>https://history.state.gov/about-the-beta</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/about-frus</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/ebooks</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/short-history</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/secretaries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/principals-chiefs</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/travels/secretary</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/travels/president</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/visits</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/wwi</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/buildings</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/diplomatic-couriers</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1750-1775</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1776-1783</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1784-1800</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1801-1829</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1830-1860</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1861-1865</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1866-1898</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1899-1913</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1914-1920</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1921-1936</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1937-1945</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1945-1952</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1953-1960</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1961-1968</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1969-1976</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1977-1980</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1981-1988</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1989-1992</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/1993-2000</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries/archives</value><value>https://history.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about</value><value>https://history.state.gov/tags</value><value>https://history.state.gov/conferences</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.gov/developer</value><value>https://history.state.gov/education</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov/open</value><value>https://history.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments</value><value>https://history.state.gov../frus1945v01</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/ch1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/ch2</value><value>https://history.state.gov#fn:1.3.2.2.4.23.3.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov#fnref:1.3.2.2.4.23.3.2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/preface</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/introduction</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/papers</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/guide</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/ch1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/persons</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp2</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp3</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp4</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/comp5</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/index</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_FDJ1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_KSAC1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_PL1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_PBJ1</value><value>https://history.state.govpersons#p_TSK1</value><value>https://history.state.gov/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/search</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/faq</value><value>https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/countries/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/milestones/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/</value><value>https://history.state.gov/about/contact-us</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#privacy</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/152386.htm</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright</value><value>https://history.state.govhttp://www.state.gov</value><value>https://history.state.govmailto:history@state.gov</value></urls><id>https://history.state.gov//historicaldocuments/frus1945v01/persons</id></item>