<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
b'<item><bodyText>\n\n\n\n\nForeign Relations of the United States\n\n\nHome\nSearch\nBrowse\nCopyright\nHelp\nUWDC\n\n\n&#160;\nElectronic Text Help\n\nContents:\n\nAbout Electronic Text\nElectronic Facsimile vs. Encoded Text\nBrowse\nSearch\n\nPhrase (Simple)\nBoolean\nProximity\nTruncation\n\n\nSearch Results\nItem Display\n\nTable of Contents\nPage View\nChange Page Size\nDisplay Page Text (OCR)\nPrinting\nGallery View (coming soon)\n\nNavigation\nSection-level PDF (coming soon)\n\n\n\nAbout Electronic Text\nThe electronic text interface allows you to experience digital \n    books, letters, journals and analogous text-based materials similar to the \n    way you would use the original resources.\nTypically, text-based materials included in this database are scanned cover to cover (including blank \n    pages). The text on every page is captured and processed using Optical Character Recognition \n    (OCR) software. This enables you to perform a full-text search -- a search \n    that includes all of the text that appears within the  \n    resource. Additionally, basic descriptive information such as title, author, \n    publisher, and chapter-level headings are searchable.\nHandwritten texts or texts that contain non-standard characters cannot \n    be processed using OCR software. However, the title, author, publisher, chapter-level \n    headings, and other pertinent descriptive information are  searchable.\n\nElectronic Facsimile vs. Encoded Text\nOur interface intermingles two types of marked-up texts. In addition to the Electronic Facsimile described above, the interface displays Encoded Texts. Encoded texts are marked up using the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) Guidelines. There are many similarities in how these two types of texts are handled in this database. As a result, you may not notice that you have moved from one type of text to another as \n    you search the database. An important difference to note is that an electronic facsimile includes page images and uncorrected text generated from an OCR software application. An Encoded Text is a new electronic edition of the original work rather than a facsimile of a print edition. Additionally, if illustrations appear in \n    the original document, they are reproduced and appear in their appropriate \n    location within the resource.\n\nBrowse\nBrowsing allows you to view the following list of resources within a collection: \n\n\n\nTitle\n\n\nAll non-journal titles in the collection, such as  monographs or letters.\n\n\n\n\nSubcollection\n\n\nAll discrete subcollections  in the collection. For example, selecting "World War II" subcollection will provide a list of all World War II resources within the History Collection.\n\n\n\n\nAuthor\n\n\nAll authors in the collection, organized by author\'s last name. \n\n\n\n\nJournal\n\n\nAll journals in the collection, listed by authorized heading.\n\n\n\nNote that not all items are  included on every \n    list. For example, items without an author are not available in the "Author" list.\n&#160;Top of Page&#160;\nSearch\nSeveral options are available for searching the electronic text database: \n\nPhrase (Simple)\nBoolean\nProximity\n\nFor  information on displaying results sets for each of these search parameters, review Search Results. \nPhrase (Simple) Search\nFollow the Search link in the  navigation menu (located in the left-hand column) to access the main Search page. A Phrase (Simple) Search locates single words or phrases that appear in the text. Note: you cannot use Boolean operators (AND, OR, NOT) to combine search terms in a Phrase search. To learn more about Boolean operators, review  Boolean search. You may also access the phrase search screen by following the Simple \n  Search link located on either the Boolean or Proximity search pages.\nPerforming a Phrase (Simple) Search\n\nKey in the search term or phrase.\nLimit your search by Entire Work, Title, Author, or Illustrations.\n If necessary, further limit your search to a specific Title or Subcollection.\nSelect the Search button to launch your search.\nTo erase your search term(s), select the Clear button.\n\nPhrase (Simple) Search Limits\nUse options available on the pull-down menu to search the Entire Work or limit a search to Title, Author, or Illustrations.\n\n\n\nEntire Work \n\nLocate your search term or phrase anywhere within  the resource. \n\n\n\nTitles \n\nLocate your search term or phrase in title fields.\n\n\n\nAuthors\n\nLocate your search term or phrase in  author fields (search by last name, first name).\n\n\n\nIllustrations\nLocate your search term or phrase in illustration content located within electronic texts. A Phrase search on illustrations will return a partial description of images using the specified search term.      Note this search strategy is only functional for electronic texts and not electronic facsimiles.\n\n\nFrom the pull down menu, select  the default selection All to search an entire collection. To further narrow a search, select a specific Title or Subcollection.\n\n\n\nSubcollections\n\n\nSearch material within a chosen subcollection. For example,  selecting the World War II subcollection will allow \n        you to search all the World War II resources in the History Collection.\n\n\n\n\nJournals/Series\n\n\nSearch only within a chosen journal or series.\n\n\n\n\nOther Titles\n\n\nSearch only within a chosen item. \n\n\n\n\n&#160;Top of Page&#160;\nBoolean Search\nBoolean search logic uses the operators AND, OR, or NOT to further narrow a search. To access the Boolean search screen, follow the Boolean \n    Search link located on either the Phrase or Proximity search pages.\nUsing Boolean Operators\n\n\n\nBoolean operator\n\n\nExample\n\n\nWill retrieve:\n\n\n\n\nAND\n\ndance AND voice\nAll items that contain both terms.\n\n\n\nOR\n\ndance OR voice\nAll items that contain either term, including those with both terms.\n\n\n\nNOT\n\n(Zuni OR Oneida) NOT voice\nAll items that contain either Zuni OR Oneida \n        but do NOT contain voice.\n\n\n\ncombination of \n        AND and OR\n\n(Zuni OR Oneida) AND voice\n All items that contain either Zuni OR Oneida \n        AND that also contain voice.\n\n\nNote that NOT is a very \n    powerful operator and may return an insufficient result set if used incorrectly. For example, the search ((Zuni OR Onieda) NOT voice)  will exclude every record containing the term voice, even if the record contains Zuni and/or Oneida. This may exclude pertinent records. \nBoolean Search Limits\nTo perform a Boolean search, you must first define the scope of operation for your search using Page or Paragraph, Section, or Entire Work.\n\n\n\nPage or Paragraph\n\n\n Terms are matched within the same page of electronic facsimiles, \n          or within the same paragraph of electronic texts.\n\n\n\n\nSection\n\n\n Terms \n          are matched within an intellectual division of the work, such as \n          a chapter, a preface, or an index.\n\n\n\n\nEntire Work\n\n\nTerms are matched within an entire work.\n\n\n\nAs with Phrase or Proximity searching, you may   narrow your search parameters to a specific title or subcollection. You may truncate search terms in a Boolean search. \n\nLimiting Results\nIf your search result set is larger than 100 records, you may limit viewing to the first 100 records, a sample of any 100 records matching your search, or all records matching your search.\n&#160;Top of Page&#160;\nProximity Search\nProximity searching allows you to specify the distance between multiple search terms within one text. Follow the Proximity \n    Search link on either the Phrase or Boolean search pages to access  the proximity search screen.\nPerforming a Proximity Search\n\nConstruct searches that meet the following criteria: Term \n      A "near," "followed by," "not near," or "not \n      followed by" Term B, and optionally "near," "followed \n    by," "not near," or "not followed by" Term C.\n\n\n\nNear\n\nTerms A and Term B appear close to one another. Order does not matter within the number of words specified.\n\n\n\nFollowed by \n\n\nTerm A is  followed by Term B within the number of words specified.\n\n\n\n\nNot Near \n\n\nFind Term A but exclude instances where Term B also appears. Order does not matter within the number of words specified.\n\n\n\n\nNot Followed by \n\n\nTerm A is not followed by Term B within the number of words specified.\n\n\n\n\nYou may set the distance(s) span to search within 5, 10, or 25 words of your desired search term. Note: due to the potential presence of markup codes between words, this number may need to be set higher for Encoded Texts than for Electronic Facsimile searches.\nYou may truncate search terms in a proximity search. \nAs with Phrase and Boolean searching, you may   narrow your search parameters to a specific title or subcollection.\n\n\nLimiting Results\nAs with Phrase (Simple) search, you may limit results sets greater than 100 records to viewing to the first 100 records, a sample of any 100 records matching your search, or all records matching your search.\n\nTruncation (*)\nTo improve your search results, use the truncation symbol, * (asterisk), to replace any word ending. This strategy will retrieve all words that begin with the given letters. For example, searching  root word dog* will return dog, dogs, dogged, dogma, etc. You may apply the truncation symbol   only at the end of a word (i.e., you can\'t use wom*n  to retrieve woman and women ). The truncation symbol may be used  with multiple words in a phrase search (e.g. univers* educ*). You may truncate terms within Phrase (Simple), Boolean, or Proximity searches. \n&#160;Top of Page&#160;\nSearch Results\n The Search Results page will display a maximum of 100 matches out of \n    the total number returned. To view more results,  follow the links at the page top or bottom,  \n    directing you to the next page of matches. \nNote that the appearance of results sets varies, depending on the search strategy performed. \nEntire Work\nWhen searching Entire Work, the results set \n    appears as shown below. The book or issue title, section or chapter title, \n    and page(s) on which your search term(s) can be found are displayed in a hierarchical \n    or nested manner. This structure provides a context for \n  search results. Follow the various links to find the exact region containing the match, the first page of the article or section, or the electronic table of contents for the corresponding book or issue. \n\nNote that results from electronic texts display somewhat differently. Instead of page numbers, you will see a short excerpt of text where your search terms appear. \nTitles\nSearching Titles returns a results set that resembles the list shown below. As with other results sets, search terms are highlighted \n    within each title.\n\nAuthors\nA search within Authors  will return a list of all matching authors and their works, as shown below. \n\nNo Results\nAn unsuccessful search returns the  error message shown below. This message will display "0" matches \n    and provide suggestions for modifying the search strategy. Following the Modify Your Search link will return you to the original search page.\n\n&#160;Top of Page&#160;\nItem Display\nContents\nSelecting an item from a browse \n    or search results list takes you to the Contents view \n    for that item. This page is an artificial table of contents, created \n     to enhance usability of the electronic document. If a true table \n    of contents exists in the original item, that table of contents page will \n    be viewable from the electronic table of contents.\n\nContents contains four sub-sections -- navigation tools, description and source information, item-level searching, and the section- or chapter-level contents of the item. \nNavigation Tools\nThe following navigation tools are located at the page top and bottom.\n\n    Selecting the Volume forward or back arrows  takes you to the table of contents for the item that is listed directly before or directly after the current item.\n\n\n    Entering a page number in the Go to Page text box takes you directly to that page within the item.\nWhen using Go to Page, please note:\n\n1) The page number must be entered as it appears on the page (i.e., 1, 2, 3 or I, II, III).\n2) If the original item contains unnumbered pages, \n          those pages remain unnumbered in the electronic version and cannot be accessed using the Go to Page function.\n3)  If the original item contains duplicate page numbers, \n                  (i.e., all chapters start with page number "1"), \n                  entering page "1" will return all of the page number \n        "1"s in the item.\n\nDescription and Source Information\nDescription and Source Information  includes the name of the current item, bibliographical information about the  item  and \n            the item\'s permanent URL, as shown below.\n\n\nItem-level Search\nItem-level searching allows you to perform a full-text search within \n      the current item. Note that this function depends on OCR availability and accuracy. \n\nSection- or Chapter-level Description\nListed under Section- or Chapter-level Description are sections included within the item. Clicking on any  link takes you  \n          to the page view of the first page of that section or chapter.\n\n&#160;Top of Page&#160;\nPage View\nThe Page View contains an image of the \n  page, navigation tools, source information, and options for other page displays. Options for viewing page text, various image sizes, and page images for printing \n  can be found within the left navigation bar. \n\nChange Page Size\nUse the Change Page Size icons in the left navigation bar to view  smaller or larger versions of the page image.\nDisplay Page Text (OCR)\nIf a page has been processed using OCR, you may view the corresponding unedited page text. Displaying page text also allows you to locate your search term \n  within the page text. Search terms will be highlighted. \n Click Display Page Text to vi</bodyText><pdf /><name /><urls><value>http://digicoll.library.wisc.eduFRUSHome.html</value></urls><id>http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/Help.html</id></item>'